<para>
  {Character Generation}The player starts with points for buying
  statistics and several other pools of points for the rest of
  charcter development. The three pools are Personal Development,
  Status, and Wealth. The player starts with 125 points for
  statistics and 10 points in the Personal Development Pool.
</para>
<para>
  With these points the player buys what is needed for the initial
  character development. This includes the Race, Special Abilities,
  and Culture of the character.
</para>
<para>
  Then the player generates the history of the character. The player
  picks the career path the character will follow and uses the
  results of that career to put points into the other pools.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Initial Point Allocation
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick Primary Statistics
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Buy Limitations and Enhancements
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Buy Racial Template
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick a race
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick a gender (if applicable)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Apply modifiers from the racial description
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Calculate remaining statistics
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Calculate Statistics
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Buy Culture Template
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick a culture
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Apply modifiers from the cultural description
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick base skills from the cultural description
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Career and History generation
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick a career or a set of careers
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Roll out the history
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Rearrange Point Pool Gains
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick the skills gained from those careers
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick any Limitations or Enhancements gained from those careers
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pick any Status or Wealth gains from the careers
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section id="primary-statistics">
  <title>Primary Statistics</title>
  <para>
    In generating the statistics of the character the player
    distributes 125 points among the 10 primary statistics. The minimum
    number of points that may be put into a statistic is 5. The maximum
    amount that may be placed into a statistic is 25.
  </para>
  <para>
    The following gives the name and abbreviation of each primary
    statistic and describes what the statistic represents.
    (Desc:PrimaryStats)
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Strength (PST)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Physical Strength is the overall power of body. This represents the
          character's raw muscle power and is not tied to some particular set
          of limbs. Actions such as lifting are based on PST.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Endurance (PEN)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Physical Endurance is the physical resilience and stamina of body.
          This is a measure of the character's overall endurance and ability
          to resist hardship as well as the ability to bounce back from
          hardship.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Dexterity (DEX)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Dexterity is the eye and hand coordination and speed of hand
          movement. This is specifically tied to the character's hands (or
          any alien equivalent).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Agility (PAG)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Physical Agility is the overall flexibity and responsiveness of
          body. This affects the whole body actions of the character. Dodging
          is an action based on PAG.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Awareness (PAW)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Physical Awareness is how sensitive the character is to the
          physical part of the environment. If you are using any of your
          physical senses, you are using PAW.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Strength (MST)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Mental Strength is raw mental power. It is a measure of the
          characters overall computational and reasoning strength. It is also
          associated with the character's strength of will. Using memory is
          an action based on MST.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Endurance (MEN)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Mental Endurance is resilience and stamina of mind. It is a measure
          of the mind's ability to recover from shock or disorientation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Agility (MAG)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Mental Agility is the overall flexibility and responsiveness of
          mind. In another day and age this might be called
          <quote>Cunning</quote>, <quote>Canniness</quote>, or
          <quote>Shrewdness</quote>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Psi Potential (PSI)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Psi Potential is a measure of how easily a character can gain
          access to their <quote>supernatural</quote> or psychic abilities.
          In fantasy campaigns this also governs the use of magery.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Awareness (MAW)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Mental Awareness is how sensitive the character is to the
          non-physical part of the environment.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    The typical non-player character average and the ranges of the
    primary statistics are given in the table below.
  </para>
  <blockquote>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        Stat &amp; Human &amp; Human <literallayout></literallayout> &amp;
        Range &amp; Average <literallayout></literallayout> PST &amp; 1-30
        &amp; 12 <literallayout></literallayout> PEN &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> DEX &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> PAG &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> PAW &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> MST &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> MEN &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> MAG &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> PSI &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout> MAW &amp; 1-30 &amp; 12
        <literallayout></literallayout>
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      {Primary Statistics}
    </para>
  </blockquote>
</section>
<section id="race">
  <title>Race</title>
  <para>
    Once the primary statistics have been chosen the race of the
    character must be selected. The racial template includes modifiers
    for primary statistics and other statistics as well as any special
    abilities of the race. The racial template includes Stat modifiers,
    Special Abilities and Limitations. Some races will have a cost that
    must be paid from the Personal Development pool.
  </para>
  <para>
    See your obliging GamesMaster for a list of racial descriptions.
  </para>
  <section id="statistic-modifiers">
    <title>Statistic Modifiers</title>
    <para>
      The racial description may include modifiers to the character's
      statistics. Primary Statistic modifiers are applied right away.
      Modifiers to calculated stats are applied after generating the
      background of the character.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="enhancementslimitations">
    <title>Enhancements/Limitations</title>
    <para>
      If there are any Enhancements or Limitations due to race then they
      should be applied at this time.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="gender">
    <title>Gender</title>
    <para>
      The player should note whether the character is male or female (if
      the character's race supports multiple genders). If there are any
      modifiers to statistics for a specific gender they should be
      applied. These modifiers will be listed in the racial description.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section id="calculated-statistics">
  <title>Calculated Statistics</title>
  <para>
    With the race and gender selected all of the primary statistics are
    modified and the secondary statistics are determined. Secondary
    statistics are determined from the primary stats. Like the primary
    statistics they break down evenly into mental and physical
    categories.
  </para>
  <para>
    Their description follows.
  </para>
  <para>
    See the description in section Desc:PrimaryStats on page
    {Desc:PrimaryStats}.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Body (PBD)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of physical damage a character can absorb. Derived from
          PST and PEN.
          (<emphasis>PST</emphasis>+<emphasis>PEN</emphasis>) × {<emphasis>Racial</emphasis>\<emphasis>Modifier</emphasis>}
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Fatigue (PFT)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of energy a character can expend, either in combat or in
          work. Derived from PEN and PAG.
          (2 × <emphasis>PEN</emphasis>)+<emphasis>PAG</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Exhaustion (PEX)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of energy reserve a character can expend as the result
          of damage or from work. Derived from PEN and PAG.
          (4 × <emphasis>PEN</emphasis>)+<emphasis>PAG</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Movement (PMV)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of the character's movement rate. Derived from PST and
          PEN and racial modifiers.
          ((<emphasis>PST</emphasis>+<emphasis>PAG</emphasis>)/5) × {<emphasis>Racial</emphasis>\<emphasis>Modifier</emphasis>}
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Body (MBD)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of mental damage a character can absorb. Derived from
          MEN and MST.
          (<emphasis>MST</emphasis>+<emphasis>MEN</emphasis>) × {<emphasis>Racial</emphasis>\<emphasis>Modifier</emphasis>}
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Fatigue (MFT)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of mental energy a character can expend, either in
          damage or in work. Derived from MEN and MAG.
          (2 × <emphasis>MEN</emphasis>)+<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Exhaustion (MEX)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The amount of mental reserve energy a character can expend, either
          in combat or in work. Derived from MEN and MAG.
          (4 × <emphasis>MEN</emphasis>)+<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Movement (MMV)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of the characters rate of movement in the purely mental
          realms of psionics, magery, and computer interfaces.
          (<emphasis>MST</emphasis>+<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>)/5) × {<emphasis>Racial</emphasis>\<emphasis>Modifier</emphasis>}
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Accuracy (ACC)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of the character's effectiveness with projectile or
          missile weapons. Derived from PST and DEX. Could also be called
          Physical Accuracy.
          (<emphasis>PST</emphasis>+<emphasis>DEX</emphasis>)/2
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Combat Ability (PCA)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of a character's ability to in-flict dam-age in
          hand-to-hand and melee combat. Derived from PST, PAG, DEX.
          (<emphasis>PST</emphasis>+<emphasis>DEX</emphasis>+<emphasis>PAG</emphasis>)/3
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Physical Defense (PDF)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of a character's ability to dodge or evade to avoid
          taking damage in hand-to-hand or melee combat. Derived from PAG,
          DEX. (<emphasis>PAG</emphasis>+<emphasis>DEX</emphasis>)/2
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Focus (FCS)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of the character's effectiveness with focused mental
          actions. Derived from MST and MAG. could also be called Mental
          Accuracy. (<emphasis>MST</emphasis>+<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>)/2
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Combat Ability (MCA)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of a character's ability to inflict damage in Mind to
          Mind combat. Derived from MST, MAG, PSI
          (<emphasis>MST</emphasis>+<emphasis>PSI</emphasis>+<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>)/3
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mental Defense (MDF)
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A measure of a character's ability to avoid taking damage in mental
          combat or highly stressful situations. Derived from MAG.
          (<emphasis>MAG</emphasis>+<emphasis>PSI</emphasis>)/2
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    {tcgen2.tex}
  </para>
</section>
<section id="other-statistics">
  <title>Other Statistics</title>
  <section id="height-ht">
    <title>Height (HT)</title>
    <para>
      Expressed in Centimeters. If the creature being described is
      quadrapedal, the height given is the height to the shoulder.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the player has no preference regarding the height of the
      character the height may be randomly generated using the following
      formula.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Height</emphasis>={<emphasis>Average</emphasis><emphasis>Height</emphasis>}+({{2<emphasis>d</emphasis>10-11}\over{10}} × {<emphasis>Height</emphasis><emphasis>Variation</emphasis>})
    </para>
    <para>
      The Average Height and Height Variation is given in the racial
      template.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="weight-wt">
    <title>Weight (WT)</title>
    <para>
      Expressed in Kilograms. If the player has no preference regarding
      the weight of the character the weight may be randomly generated
      using the following formula.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Weight</emphasis>={<emphasis>Average</emphasis><emphasis>Weight</emphasis>}+({{2<emphasis>d</emphasis>10-11}\over{10}} × {<emphasis>Weight</emphasis><emphasis>Variation</emphasis>})
    </para>
    <para>
      The Average Weight and Weight Variation is given in the racial
      description.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="appearence-app">
    <title>Appearence (APP)</title>
    <para>
      A measure of how physically attractive a character is to others of
      their race. It ranges (typically) from +5 to -5 and has a default
      of 0. Characters that wish to be more or less attractive can buy
      appearance as an enhancement or limitation. See section
      Sec:Enhancements.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="mental-speed">
    <title>Mental Speed</title>
    <para>
      Speed of reaction in mental actions is given by Mental Speed. It is
      derived from the Mental Awareness stat using table  Table:Speed on
      page {Table:Speed}. An average Mental Speed is 4.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="physical-speed">
    <title>Physical Speed</title>
    <para>
      Speed of reaction in mental actions is given by Physical Speed. It
      is derived from the Physical Awareness stat using table
       Table:Speed on page {Table:Speed}. An average Physical Speed is 4.
    </para>
    <para>
      {tcgen5.tex}
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section id="cultural-modifiers">
  <title>Cultural Modifiers</title>
  <para>
    The player should determine the culture and the home environment
    the character is raised in. Both of these will have a major effect
    on the numbers and types of skills that a player character starts
    out with. Some cultural templates may have a cost that must be paid
    from the Personal Development pool.
  </para>
  <para>
    As a result of growing up in a given environment the character
    gains skill in how to maneuver in that environment. i.e. A
    character born and raised in an zero-gravity environment will have
    high skills in {Movement:0-g } and little or no skills in
    {Movement:1-g }.
  </para>
  <para>
    The character will start out with a knowledge of how to use the
    technology common to their culture and what the social dos and and
    donts are.
  </para>
  <para>
    These types of skills are listed in the table below.along with some
    specific examples.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        20 points of education skills.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        20 points of skills in written and spoken language.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        20 points of skill in Cultural Lore. Both local and larger scale.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        20 points of skill in Lore:[Tech Index] of Culture.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        15 points of manuevering skills for the native environment
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
<section id="careers">
  <title>Careers</title>
  <para>
    The next step is determining the career path the character took up
    until the start of play. This is where a majority of a character's
    skills and history will be developed. The process is fairly simple:
    the player selects the career they wish to enter and then they roll
    for the character to gain skills, wealth, and status during each
    year they are in that career. This means three rolls. One for
    Personal Development, one for Wealth, and one for status. These
    three pools : Personal Development, Wealth, and Status are the
    basis of the final resolution of the character's skills, history,
    and station.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each of the available paths has its own advantages and
    disadvantages. Educational careers give one little chance to injure
    one's self but the possible monetary gains are low. Military
    careers are dangerous, but the skills gained there may not be
    available elsewhere.
  </para>
  <para>
    The three pools each have a different basic function. The Personal
    Development pool serves as the point pool for increasing a PC
    statistics, skills, or creating special abilities. The Wealth pool
    contains points to be spent in establishing the character's basic
    financial state. The Status pool contains points to be spent in
    gaining all the possible trappings of status: reputation,
    syncophants, or other recognition.
  </para>
  <para>
    Players do have a limited amount of lateral movement for these
    points. Each career is delineated by a simple set of numbers
    combined with a simple description. It has the following format:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          [Name] Self explanatory
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Personal Development
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          How many PD points are normally recieved during a one year period
          in that career.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Financial Gain
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The base amount of stads(standards) gained in a one year period of
          a career. A stad can be replaced with the name of the standard unit
          of currency.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        DF (Personal|Wealth|Status)
      </term>
      <listitem>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Personal
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The DF for a MAW or PAW roll to determine the number of personal
          points the character gained in a roll. A successful roll adds
          points into the Personal Stat Pool. A failed roll adds nothing and
          a critical failure usually involves the loss of points from the
          personal pool.
          <footnote>
            <para>
              !!!! Add a description in the beginning of the PG for DF and rolls
            </para>
          </footnote>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Wealth
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The DF for a MAW or PAW roll to determine whether or not the
          character gained in the material or financial area. A successful
          roll adds Base Financial Gain to the Wealth Pool. This represents
          the character's gain in free wealth beyond their means of support.
          i.e. their savings.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Status
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The DF for a MAW or PAW roll to determine whether or not the
          character gained in Status. A succesful roll adds 1 to the Status
          Pool. Status is a rather subjective thing but typically, a military
          career leads to increases in rank and possible minor fame. A
          increase in status in a shadowy career would lead to the
          development of a &quot;Rep&quot;. Most careers will have a status
          table that describes the cost of a specific rank or status gain.
          <footnote>
            <para>
              !!!! Add a reputation table
            </para>
          </footnote>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    For example, here is a description of a Terran Law Enforcement
    Officer
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          [Name] Terran Law Enforcement Officer
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Personal Development
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          8 points per year
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Financial Gain
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          3,000 UN Dollars
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        DF (Personal|Wealth|Status)
      </term>
      <listitem>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Personal
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          DF -2
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Wealth
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          DF 0
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Status
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          DF -3
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Status Table
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              3
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Sargent
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              5
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Lieutenant
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              8
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Captain
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              12
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Chief
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    {Typical Careers (in short form)}
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Theif
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          12:4,000 stads : (5/4/6)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Fighter
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          15:7,000 stads : (7/3/2)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mage
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          20:2,000 stads : (7/3/1)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Smuggler
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          20:10,000 stads:(7/5/3)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Terran Space Navy
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          18:14,000stads:(7/3/3)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Healer
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          25:1,000stads:(7/1/3)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Mechanized Infantry
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          25:1,000stads:(7/1/3)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    The example careers listed above would usually be fleshed out with
    additional detail such as a description of rank and status,
    etc<footnote>
         <para>
           An important question is that of when a character is allowed to
           drop out of military and so on careers.
         </para>
       </footnote>
  </para>
</section>
<section id="buying-skills-and-enhancements">
  <title>Buying Skills and Enhancements</title>
  <para>
    In the previous portion of the character generation process we
    added and subtracted points to three <quote>pools</quote>. These
    three pools : Personal, , Wealth, and Status are the basis of the
    final resolution of the character's skills, history, etc The three
    pools each have a different basic function.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Personal pool serves as the point pool for increasing a PC
    statistics, Skills, or creating special abilities. The Wealth pool
    contains points to be spent in gaining an idea of basic financial
    state. The Status pool contains points to be spent in gaining all
    the possible trappings of status. Reputation, syncophants.
  </para>
  <para>
    Players do have a limited amount of lateral movement for these
    points.
    <footnote>
      <para>
        The Wealth and Status pool can exchange to a maximum of 10
      </para>
    </footnote>
    <footnote>
      <para>
        The Wealth and Skill pools can exchange a maximum of 15 points.
      </para>
    </footnote>
  </para>
  <para>
    In addition a player can add and subtract to/from the pools by the
    usage of Enhancements and Limitations. See section
    Sec:Enhancements.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="skill-costs">
  <title>Skill Costs</title>
  <para>
    When characters are first generated they can buy single skills
    using points from the personal pool. During character generation
    all skills cost 1 point per rank to purchase. So rank 0 costs 1
    point, rank 1 costs 2 points , and so on. After characters have
    been generated they advance in their skills according to rules
    described in the Players Guide.
  </para>
  <para>
    In summary single skills cost 1+<emphasis>Rank</emphasis> in
    personal development points.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="skill-ranks">
  <title>Skill Ranks</title>
  <para>
    The meaning of skill ranks varies somewhat based on the rarity of
    the skill and so on but, in general, the skill ranks map to
    expertise according to table  Table:SkillRanks on
    page {Table:SkillRanks}.
  </para>
  <para>
    {tskill9}Someone is familiar with the skill if they have tried it
    enough that the tools and techniques are known even if the
    character has no real practice with them.
  </para>
  <para>
    A character is at a begginer level of skill if they have used the
    skills enough to be comfortable with all the basic techniques
    needed even though they may not be consistent in their execution.
  </para>
  <para>
    A character is at a dedicated amateur level of skill if they are
    consistent in executing all the basic skills even though they have
    no real comfort with any of the advanced techniques.
  </para>
  <para>
    A solid workaday craftsman is consistent and accomplished in
    executing all the basic skills and are familiar with the advanced
    techniques and tools.
  </para>
  <para>
    A professional is consistent and accomplished in te full range of
    basic and advanced techniques used in routine application of the
    skill.
  </para>
  <para>
    An expert is consistent and accomplished in all the basic and
    advanced techniques used in routine application of the skill as
    well as being familiar with techniques and tools needed for less
    common usage of the skill.
  </para>
  <para>
    An master is consistent and accomplished in all the techniques used
    in most applications of the skill. In addition they are familiar
    with some esoteric techniques needed for bizarre and unusual
    applications of a skill.
  </para>
  <para>
    An character at a mystical mastery level accomplished in all the
    techniques used in almost all known applications of the skill. In
    addition they have a whole series of special techniques and tools
    they have developed for themselves.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="statistic-costs">
  <title>Statistic Costs</title>
  <para>
    When characters are first generated they can buy statistics using
    points from the personal pool. During character generation all
    stats are raised using the costs from the table  Table:StatCosts on
    page {Table:StatCosts}. So adding 1 point of PST costs 4 points,
    adding 2 costs 8 points, and so on. After characters have been
    generated they advance in their stats according to rules described
    in the Players Guide.
  </para>
  <para>
    {tcgen4.tex}
  </para>
</section>
<section id="skill-packages">
  <title>Skill Packages</title>
  <para>
    What we have discussed up till now has been single skills. Quite
    often the character will be using a skill package. A skill package
    is a collection of related skills that have a bundled at a bargain
    cost.
  </para>
  <para>
    A typical skill package would be :
  </para>
  <screen>
Terran Law Enforcement Officer Package
    Lore: Terran Law
    Culture Lore: Terran LEO
    Weapon: Pistol 
    Weapon: Tonfa
    Weapon: Taser
    Streetwise
    Interrogation
    Data Analysis
    Computer Ops
    Cost: 5
</screen>
  <para>
    This package would cost 5 points to get rank 0 in all the listed
    skills, 10 points to get rank 1 and so on. This compares well to 9
    points to get rank 0 in all the skills and 18 points to get rank 1
    and so on. After character generation, these skills are raised
    individually just like any other skill according to rules described
    in the Players Guide.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="enhancements-and-limitations">
  <title>Enhancements and Limitations</title>
  <para>
    (Sec:Enhancements) (Sec:Limitations) After a character has some
    points in the three pools associated with character creation (
    personal, wealth, status) they may choose to use them to buy
    Enhancements that will add flavour to the character.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are always the base enhancements allowed to the character.
    The points in the personal pool can be used to buy skills at the
    generation cost. The points in the personal pool can be used to buy
    stats at the costs listed in the stat cost tables.
  </para>
  <para>
    Enhancements are gains in either background or special abilities
    that can be paid for with points from one of the pools. There are
    two main types. There are Character Enhancements and there are
    Environmental Enhancements.
  </para>
  <para>
    Character Enhancements are natural aptitudes that are typically
    permanent and inherent to the character's makeup. Enhanced hearing
    or eidetic memory are examples of Character Enhancements.
  </para>
  <para>
    Environmental Enhancements are typically advantages that depend on
    the character to maintain them. Such as inherited wealth and
    various components of status.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="character-enhancements">
  <title>Character Enhancements</title>
  <para>
    Character Enhancements have both Depth and Scope to help govern
    their cost. Depth refers to the numeric advantage given by the
    enhancemnet in a given area. The scope denotes the number of
    different areas that the spab may be applicable to. In the case of
    raising a character statistic the scope refers to the number of
    other stats affected.
  </para>
  <para>
    A character enhancement that involves enhancing a statistic is
    different from raising the statistic. A raised statistic ends up
    increasing the SB of the character in that stat. The enhanced stat
    increases the Rank of the character for any direct rolls against
    that stat. Thus an Enhanced Stat affects Saving Throws and
    Concentration Checks.
  </para>
  <section id="ambidexterity">
    <title>Ambidexterity</title>
    <para>
      Ambidexterity allows the character to use either hand when
      performing actions. The character takes no off-hand penalties.
      Costs 10 Personal Development Points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="eidectic-memory">
    <title>Eidectic Memory</title>
    <para>
      Exact recall (given successful roll against MST) of events. Adds DF
      2 to any memory roll. Costs 12 Personal Development points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="photographic-memory">
    <title>Photographic Memory</title>
    <para>
      Exact recall of (given successful roll against MST) any image or
      visual happening. Costs 12 Personal Development points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="lightning-calculator">
    <title>Lightning Calculator</title>
    <para>
      Ability to instantly execute complex arithmetic and mathematical
      calculations. Costs 5 Personal Development points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="active-psi">
    <title>Active PSI</title>
    <para>
      Character has concious knowledge and use (though no training) of
      their psionic abilities. Costs 20 Personal Development Points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="mage-ability">
    <title>Mage Ability</title>
    <para>
      Character has concious knowledge and use (though no training) of
      their magical abilities. Costs 20 Personal Development Points
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="enhanced-statistics">
    <title>Enhanced Statistics</title>
    <para>
      Most of the enhancements that involve heightened stats in
      specialised areas have a simple cost equal to 1/2 the purchase cost
      of the stats. So someone with a heightened sense of smell would pay
      one half the cost of Physical Awareness (PAW) or 1/2 × 4=2 for each
      additional point of increase. So someone with a 12 PAW could pay 8
      points of ersonal Development and get a PAW (for smells) of 16.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="psi-gift">
    <title>PSI Gift</title>
    <para>
      The heightening of PSI for broad categories of PSI skills such as
      Temporokinetics has a cost equal to 3/4 of the PSI stat or 8
      points. So someone with a gift for Temporokinetics would pay 8
      points per point of heightened PSI in that area.
    </para>
    <para>
      The heightening of PSI for specific PSI skills such as
      Teleportation has a cost equal to 1/2 of the PSI stat or 5 points.
      So someone with a gift for Teleportation would pay 5 points per
      point of heightened PSI in that area.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="presence">
    <title>Presence</title>
    <para>
      This enhancement reflects other people's innate awareness of the
      character in a given area. A person with a high presence is hard to
      ignore.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is calculated in just the same way as other enhanced stats. So
      Enhanced Physical Presence is 2 points per additional effect.
      Decreased Physical Presence is 2 points per subtracted effect.
      Enhanced Mental Presence is 2 points per additional effect.
      Decreased Mental Presence is 2 points per subtracted effect.
    </para>
    <para>
      The decreased presence enhancements are, in effect, stealth
      enhancements.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section id="environmental-enhancements">
  <title>Environmental Enhancements</title>
  <para>
    Environmental Enhancements have both Depth and Scope to help govern
    their cost. Scope is the number of people affected by the
    enhancement.
  </para>
  <blockquote>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        Scope &amp; Number of People &amp; Cost
        <literallayout></literallayout> 10<superscript>0</superscript>
        &amp; 1 &amp; 1 <literallayout></literallayout>
        10<superscript>1</superscript> &amp; 2-10 &amp; 2
        <literallayout></literallayout> 10<superscript>2</superscript>
        &amp; 11-100 &amp; 4 <literallayout></literallayout>
        10<superscript>3</superscript> &amp; 101-1000 &amp; 8
        <literallayout></literallayout> 10<superscript>4</superscript>
        &amp; 1001-10000 &amp; 16 <literallayout></literallayout>
        10<superscript>5</superscript> &amp; 10001-100000 &amp; 32
        <literallayout></literallayout> 10<superscript>6</superscript>
        &amp; 100001-1000000 &amp; 64 <literallayout></literallayout>
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      {Cost of Environmental Enhancement Scope}(Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts)
    </para>
  </blockquote>
  <para>
    Depth is how deeply they are affected by the enhancement.
  </para>
  <blockquote>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        Depth &amp; DF &amp; Cost <literallayout></literallayout> Low &amp;
        1 &amp; 1 <literallayout></literallayout> Medium Low &amp; 2 &amp;
        2 <literallayout></literallayout> Medium &amp; 4 &amp; 4
        <literallayout></literallayout> Medium High &amp; 6 &amp; 8
        <literallayout></literallayout> High &amp; 8 &amp; 10
        <literallayout></literallayout> Very High &amp; 12 &amp; 20
        <literallayout></literallayout>
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      {Cost of Environmental Enhancement Depth}(Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts)
    </para>
  </blockquote>
  <para>
    So for determining the cost of a single ( Scope =
    10<superscript>0</superscript> ) friend willing to help you all
    (Depth = Very High ) the time is simply 1+20. The DF describes how
    willing the person is to help you. So in the example DF = 12
    implies +60
  </para>
  <para>
    that person.
  </para>
  <section id="wealth">
    <title>Wealth</title>
    <para>
      The first and most commonly used is the wealth advantage. This
      differs from the basic wealth that can be gained by spending the
      points from the wealth pool in that the gain is approximately one
      third that of a pure monetary spend, but the gain so obtained is
      income that will continue to be generated for as long as the PC
      pays attention to the interests that generate the funds. The larger
      the income the more work involved in maintaining it.
    </para>
    <para>
      The scale of the income is derived from table
       Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts. The amount of freedom
      from managing that income is given by the table
       Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="friendsallies-and-contacts">
    <title>Friends,Allies, and Contacts</title>
    <para>
      Another important Environmental Enhancement is that of Friends.
      Number of friends is derived from table
       Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts. The willingness to help
      is given by the table  Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="reputation">
    <title>Reputation</title>
    <para>
      The scale of the reputation is derived from table
       Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts. The amount of
      recognition is given by the table
       Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="continued-careers">
    <title>Continued Careers</title>
    <para>
      A continued career as a Law Enforcement Officer or soldier is a
      balanced ad and disad situation. Yes, the character has enemies,
      but the backing of the organization offsets this.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="variations">
    <title>Variations</title>
    <para>
      [OPTION1] Shortform generation [OPTION2] Allow moving points
      between pools [OPTION3] Allow moving DF between pools [OPTION4]
      Wealth as a function of status
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
