<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Cultural Design.</title>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>External Setting</title>
        <subtitle>The primary setting for any culture</subtitle>
        <para>Cultures are fundamentally shaped by their external environment</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Locale</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>What is the geography?</member>
                        <member>How accessible is this area? </member>
                        <member>What natural features mark the borders? </member>
                        <member>What are the most striking features of landscape, climate, animals,
                            etc. in thisarea? </member>
                        <member>How will these features affect travel time, communication,
                            etc.?</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Climate</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>What is the climate?</member>
                        <member>What kinds of clothes and shelter are needed?</member>
                        <member>Will the climate only allow survival activities or will there be
                            time for leisure developments such as art, philosophy, etc?</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Resources</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>What are the resources for survival?</member>
                        <member> Noticeable Raw Materials</member>
                        <member> Hidden Raw Materials</member>
                        <member> Noticeable Other Assets</member>
                        <member> Hidden Other Assets</member>
                        <member> Nearby Assets</member>
                        <member>What water resources available, and for what uses (a mill wheel
                            requires flowing water, i.e., river or stream; irrigation needs a large,
                            dependable water source like lake or large river: etc.)?</member>
                        <member>How do most of the citizens make their living — farming, fishing,
                            trade, manufacturing? </member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Flora</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>What sorts of food can be grown, hunted, caught?</member>
                        <member>What are the people's main crops?</member>
                        <member>What flora are especially helpful? Like hemp and flax.</member>
                        <member>What are known delicacies.</member>
                        <member>What fruits vegetables can be turned into a liquor and/or drugs or
                            medicines.</member>
                        <member>Are there predatory plants?</member>
                        <member>What are the sources of poisons?</member>
                        <member>How much of the country is farmland? Forest? Desert? Mountains?
                            Plains?</member>
                        <member>What are the primary crops (e.g., potatoes, cotton, tobacco, coffee,
                            rice, peanuts, wheat, sugarcane, etc.)? </member>
                        <member>Are any grown mainly for export? </member>
                        <member>What crops can not be grown here because of the soil, climate, or
                            for other reasons?</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Fauna</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>What animals are especially helpful to your world?</member>
                        <member>What is a creature that preys on other nuisance creatures?</member>
                        <member>What are he domesticated animals?</member>
                        <member>What are the food animals?</member>
                        <member>Whether the food taboos?</member>
                        <member>Which animals are used in medicine.</member>
                        <member>What animals are used for poisons.</member>
                        <member>What wild animals, actual or imaginary, live in this area? </member>
                        <member>Are any of them potentially useful — e.g., for fur, whale oil,
                            hides, magical ingredients, hat feathers?</member>
                        <member>Which animals, actual or imaginary, are commonly domesticated in
                            this area? </member>
                        <member>Which aren’t here, but are elsewhere? (Example: water buffalo in
                            India vs. oxen in Europe vs. camels in desert areas.)</member>
                        <member>If there are imaginary animals (dragons, unicorns, etc.), how do
                            they fit into the ecology? </member>
                        <member>What do they eat? How much habitat do they require? </member>
                        <member>Can they live anywhere, or do they prefer or need specific kinds of
                            climate or terrain? </member>
                        <member>Are they intelligent and/or capable of working spells, talking,
                            etc.?</member>

                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Natural Resource</term>
                <listitem>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>Which areas are the most fertile farmland? </member>
                        <member>Where are mineral resources located?</member>
                        <member>Which animals, birds, fish, and other wildlife are commonly found in
                            which areas? </member>
                        <member>If there are imaginary animals such as dragons, where do they
                            live?</member>
                        <member>Which natural resources, if any, have been depleted in which areas
                            over time?</member>
                        <member>Which resources (e.g., coal, oil, iron ore, gold, diamonds,
                            limestone, etc.) are particularly abundant, and in which areas?</member>
                        <member>Which are scarce?</member>
                        <member>Are there places where there are rich deposits that haven’t been
                            discovered yet, or where they haven’t been fully exploited?</member>
                        <member>How much conflict has been or might be caused by these imbalances in
                            resources? </member>
                        <member>How much active, peaceful trade?</member>
                        <member>What water resources available, and for what uses ?</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Other</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What kinds of natural phenomenon might influence beliefs? </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>History</title>
        <subtitle>The secondary setting for any culture. All human cultures possess some earlier
            developments in their culture.</subtitle>
        <simplelist>
            <member>Succession of rulers and/or changes in the form of government</member>
            <member>Invasions, movements of peoples, or dramatic mass migrations</member>
            <member>Disaster related to plague, fire, disease, famine, pestilence, etc.</member>
            <member>Victory in war, establishment or expansion of colonies, major changes in
                borders, etc.</member>
            <member>Take note of dates when a natural event reduced or increase the amount of
                natural resources (food, water, timber etc.) </member>
            <member>Take note of dates when a unnatural event change the resources as well</member>
            <member>Keep in mind recovering from war takes about a generation without any major
                wars.</member>
            <member>Track specific dates one power shifted in civilizations (through who, death of a
                monarch that something) and one of the powershift was smooth.</member>
            <member>How far back are there records or tales of historical events? </member>
            <member>How widely known are these stories?</member>
            <member>Do average people believe old tales, or do they dismiss some that have a basis
                in fact (e.g., Troy)?</member>
            <member>Who are the neighboring countries/peoples and what are they like?</member>
            <member>Why did people settle in this country in the first place — strategic location,
                trade route, water transport, minerals, good farming, etc.? \</member>
            <member>Have things changed much since, or do they still depend on whatever brought them
                in the first place?</member>
            <member>Who are the rivals or enemies of this country? How close are they physically?
                How powerful?</member>
            <member>Who are the heroes and villains of each country’s history (e.g., Washington and
                Lincoln in the U.S.; Henry V in England, etc.)? </member>
            <member>Why are they heroes/villains and what do this say about the country and the
                people who admire them?</member>
            <member>Which peoples/countries/races have been in conflict in the recent past? Why?
                When and why was the most recent war? Who won?</member>
            <member>Which peoples/countries/races fought, allied, traded, or were traditional
                rivals? Where are there still hard feelings about old events?</member>
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Forces</title>
        <subtitle>Some outside influences have helped to mold a culture into its condition, so, it
            has its own set of past values, beliefs, and activities.</subtitle>
        <sect2>
            <title>Static Forces</title>
            <para>Static force provides stability. It allows people to hold to the familiar and put
                brakes on the forces of change that may be rapid</para>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Established religion</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Dynamic Forces</title>
            <para>Dynamic force provides change. These are the forces that work toward
                change.</para>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Interactions with Other Cultures</member>
                <member>Interdependence between groups of people brings change.</member>
                <member>Conflict between people brings change. </member>
                <member>Communication may bring change.</member>
                <member>Is population shifting from rural to urban, south to north, mountains to
                    coast, etc.? </member>
                <member>Why — invasion, plague, gold rush, etc.? </member>
                <member>What effects has this had on the places being left? </member>
                <member>The places gaining people?</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Magic</title>
        <para>These need to be generally answered but they are also culture specific...</para>
        <simplelist>
            <member>What things can magic not do?</member>
            <member>What are the limits to magical power?</member>
            <member>How do magicians try to get around these limits?</member>
            <member>What is the price magicians must pay in order to be magicians — years of study,
                permanent celibacy, using up bits of their life or memory with each spell,
                ...</member>
            <member>Does anyone ever try to get around the price of magic?</member>

            <member>Is there a difference between miracles and magic?</member>
            <member>If so, how are they distinguished?</member>
            <member>Where does magic power come from: the gods, the “mana” of the world, the
                personal willpower of the magician?</member>
            <member>Is magic an exhaustible resource?</member>
            <member>If a magician must feed his spells with his own willpower, life-force, or
                sanity, what long-term effects will this have on the health and/or stability of the
                magician?</member>
            <member>Do different races/species have different sources for their magic, or does
                everybody use the same one?</member>
            <member>How does a magician tap his/her magic power?</member>
            <member>Does becoming a magician require some rite of passage (investing one’s power in
                an object, being chosen by the gods, constructing or being given a permanent link to
                the source of power) or does it just happen naturally, as a gradual result of much
                study or as a part of growing up?</member>
            <member>What do you need to do to cast a spell — design an elaborate ritual, recite
                poetry, mix the right ingredients in a pot?</member>
            <member>Are there things like a staff, a wand, a familiar, a crystal ball, that are
                necessary to have before casting spells?</member>
            <member>If so, where and how do new wizards get these things?</member>
            <member>Do they make them, buy them from craftsmen, inherit them from their teachers, or
                order them from Wizardry Supplies, Inc.?</member>

            <member>Is there a numerical limit to the number of wizards in the world?</member>
            <member>What is it?</member>
            <member>Why?</member>

            <member>How long does it take to cast a spell?</member>
            <member>Can spells be stored for later, instant use?</member>
            <member>Does working spells take lots of long ritual, or is magic a “point and shoot”
                affair?</member>

            <member>Can two or more wizards combine their power to cast a stronger spell, or is
                magic done only by individuals?</member>
            <member>What makes one wizard more powerful than another — knowledge of more spells,
                ability to handle greater levels of power, having a more powerful god as patron,
                etc.?</member>

            <member>Does practicing magic have any detrimental effect on the magician (such as
                becoming addictive, fomenting insanity, or shortening life-span)?</member>
            <member>If so, is there any way to prevent these effects?</member>
            <member>Are the effects inevitable to all magicians, or do they affect only those with
                some sort of predisposition?</member>
            <member>Do they progress at the same rate in everyone?</member>
            <member>Are they universal in all species, or are some races (dwarves, elves, whoever)
                immune to these detrimental effects?</member>

            <member>How much is known about the laws of nature, physics, and magic?</member>
            <member>How much of what is commonly known is wrong (e.g., Aristotle’s ideas about human
                anatomy, which were wrong but accepted for centuries)?</member>

            <member>What general varieties of magic are practiced (e.g., herbal potions, ritual
                magic, alchemical magic, demonology, necromancy, etc.)?</member>
            <member>Do any work better than others, or does only one variety actually work?</member>

            <member>Are certain kinds of magic practiced solely or chiefly by one sex or the
                other?</member>
            <member>By one race or another?</member>
            <member>Is this because of inborn ability, natural preferences, or legislation?</member>

            <member>Does a magician’s magical ability or power change over time — e.g., growing
                stronger or weaker during puberty, or with increasing age?</member>
            <member>Can a magician “use up” all of his/her magic, thus ceasing to be a
                magician?</member>
            <member>If this happens, what does the ex-magician do — die, retire, take up teaching,
                go into a second career, start a freelance consulting business?</member>

            <member>Can the ability to do magic be lost?</member>
            <member>If so, how — overdoing it, “burning out,” brain damage due to fever or a blow,
                etc.?</member>

            <member>Can the ability to work magic be taken away?</member>
            <member>If so, how and by whom?</member>


            <member>How do various religions,if any, view magic?</member>
            <member>Do any forbid it?</member>
            <member>Why or why not?</member>
            <member>Do any require priests/priestesses to be magicians?</member>
            <member>Do any forbid magicians from holding some or all religious offices?</member>

            <member>How long does it take to learn magic?</member>

            <member>Is magic a profession, an art, or just a job?</member>
            <member> What is the status accorded to magicians in this society?</member>
            <member>Are they the equivalent of shyster lawyers, politicians, and used car salesmen,
                or are they considered average working stiffs, or are they looked up to and
                admired?</member>

            <member>Are wizards organized?</member>
            <member>How?</member>
            <member>What hierarchy, if any, do they recognize?</member>
            <member>What happens if the person/people at the top get killed?</member>
            <member>Who takes over?</member>
            <member>How soon?</member>

            <member>Can anyone become a wizard, or does one need to be born with some special talent
                or gift?</member>

            <member>Are different races/intelligent species good at different types of
                magic?</member>
            <member>If so, what types are associated with what races/species?</member>
            <member>Are there species that use magic more or less unconsciously?</member>

            <member>Can you make a living practicing magic, or do you have to have independent
                means?</member>
            <member> If you can make a living, what are you doing — making magic swords, or making
                it rain for local farmers?</member>
            <member>What’s a wizard’s job market like?</member>
            <member>What’s a wizard’s average income, relative to the rest of society?</member>

            <member>Are magicians a force in politics, or are they above it?</member>
            <member> Are there national politics that revolve around magic/wizards (i.e., trying to
                outlaw, protect, or promote certain kinds of magic licensing of magicians, </member>
            <member>Do wizards have a lobby?</member>
            <member>Do they need one?</member>

            <member>Does it require a license to be a wizard?</member>
            <member> Who certifies wizards: government, wizard’s guild/AMA, local priests?</member>

            <member>How do local people view wizards?</member>
            <member>Are they good guys, bad guys, Clint Eastwood (call in only to get rid of
                dragons), regular working stiffs, ivory-tower academics, nuisances who make it rain
                when you’re plowing, dangerous folks to stay away from?</member>
            <member>How do you get to be a wizard/magician?</member>
            <member>Does it require inborn talent, study and hard work, practice, or all of the
                above?</member>

            <member>Are wizards barred from certain kinds of government jobs or offices?</member>
            <member>Do some government jobs require that their holder be a wizard?</member>

            <member>If magic requires study, where do you go to learn about it?</member>
            <member>How do people fund their training?</member>
            <member>Is there an apprenticeship system, or are there wizard schools, or is it
                one-on-one tutoring/mentoring?</member>
            <member>Is an untrained wizard dangerous, or just an ordinary person?</member>

            <member>Do wizards have a special language that is used for magic?</member>
            <member>If so, where do they learn it?</member>
            <member>Is it safe to chat in this language, or is everything said in it automatically a
                spell?</member>
            <member>If so, how can it safely be taught to new students?</member>

            <member>Is magic considered a science, or are scientists and wizards enemies or
                rivals?</member>
            <member>Are magic and science compatible?</member>
            <member>To what degree does the presence of magic, magical objects, and wizards replace
                technology ?</member>
            <member>Duplicate technology?</member>
            <member>Supplement technology?</member>

            <member>Can two or more wizards combine their power to cast a stronger spell, or is
                magic done only by individuals?</member>
            <member>What makes a powerful magician?</member>

            <member>What do you need to do to cast a spell — design an elaborate ritual, recite
                poetry, mix the right ingredients in a pot?</member>
            <member>Are there things like a staff, a wand, a familiar, a crystal ball, that are
                necessary to have before casting spells?</member>
            <member>If so, where and how do new wizards get these things?</member>
            <member>Do they make them, buy them from craftsmen, inherit them from their teachers, or
                order them from Wizardry Supplies, Inc.?</member>

            <member>Where does magic power come from: the gods, the “mana” of the world, the
                personal willpower of the magician?</member>
            <member>Is magic an exhaustible resource?</member>


            <member>Are there fashions/fads in magic — are herbal spells “in” this year and ritual
                spells “out,” or vice versa?</member>

            <member>Are certain spells (as opposed to magic generally) illegal?</member>
            <member>Why — because of the effect of the spell, or because of the ingredients or
                procedures needed to cast it, or what?</member>
            <member>If so, how would a criminal magician be detected?</member>
            <member>Apprehended?</member>
            <member>Punished?</member>
            <member>Is catching and punishing illegal magicians the responsibility of the magician’s
                guild, or do the ordinary courts have to handle it?</member>

            <member>Are there magical means of transportation (teleport spells, magic carpets,
                dragon-riding)?</member>
            <member>How do they compare in speed, safety and expense to non-magical means?</member>
            <member>Are there any drawbacks to magical travel (for example, teleport
                sickness)?</member>
            <member>How commonly are they used, and for what purposes (industrial shipping vs.
                travel for fun)?</member>

            <member>Are there magical means of rapid communication?</member>
            <member>How commonly are they used?</member>
            <member>For what purposes?</member>

            <member>Are magical weapons available?</member>
            <member>Can magic be used in warfare?</member>
            <member>In what ways?</member>
            <member>Are spells fast enough to be useful in hand-to-hand combat, or is magic more of
                a siege weapon, used only for long, slow things?</member>

            <member>How has the presence of magic affected weapons technology?</member>
            <member>Can magic make weapons more effective?</member>
            <member>Do you have to do anything special to walls, armor, or weapons to make them
                better able to resist enemy spells?</member>

            <member>How has the presence of magic affected weapons technology?</member>
            <member> Can an ordinary, non-weapon-type object be enchanted to make it extremely
                lethal or will this work properly only on things that are already weapons?</member>
            <member> Can ordinary objects be enchanted to make them (or their user) supremely good
                at something (the Frying Pan of Ultimate Gourmet Cooking)?</member>
            <member>How common and useful are such enchantments?</member>

            <member>Can spells and/or magical items be mass-produced?</member>
            <member>Are there magic carpet factories and boutiques selling magic rings?</member>

            <member>Can spells and/or magical items be used to increase the efficiency of
                manufacturing or mass production?</member>
            <member>Do businesses keep a wizard on retainer, as modern businesses might keep a
                lawyer or efficiency expert?</member>
            <member>What, exactly, are they paying for?</member>


            <member>Are there magical artifacts (rings, swords, etc.)?</member>
            <member>If so, who makes them and how?</member>
            <member>Are the spells permanent, or do they wear off after a while?</member>

            <member>Where is scientific and/or magical research done — universities, private labs,
                under the auspices of the ruler/government, etc.?</member>

            <member>Given the magical/technological level of this society, what is an appropriate
                ration of farmers or food producers to urban residents?</member>
            <member>If farm production is based on magic, how many urban residents are going to
                starve if the spells supporting farming (weather, land fertility, etc.) fail
                suddenly?</member>
            <member>Are the laws of nature and physics actually different in this world (to
                accommodate magic), or are they the same as in real life?</member>
            <member>How does magic fit in?</member>
            <member>How do magical beasts fit in?</member>

            <member>In what ways can magic or spells be abused?</member>
            <member>How often does this happen?</member>

            <member>Is magic legal?</member>
            <member>All magic, or only some types?</member>
            <member>Do laws vary widely from country to country, or is the attitude generally
                similar?</member>

        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Internal Influences</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Economic</title>
            <para>Sweping adventure means nothing if you cant buy a bite to eat.</para>
            <simplelist>
                <member>How important is trade to the economy? </member>
                <member>How is currency exchange handled, and by whom? </member>
                <member>What is the system of coinage, and who mints it?</member>
                <member>Resources</member>
                <member>Transportation</member>
                <member>Scarcity</member>
                <member>Production</member>
                <member>Distribution</member>
                <member>Type of economy</member>
                <member>decision-making</member>
                <member>technology</member>
                <member>division of labor</member>
                <member>needs</member>
                <member>Trading partners</member>
                <member>What does this country import? </member>
                <member>Export? </member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Dynamic Forces</title>
            <para>Dynamic force provides change. These are the forces that work toward
                change.</para>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Interactions with Other Cultures</member>
                <member>Interdependence between groups of people brings change.</member>
                <member>Conflict between people brings change. </member>
                <member>Communication may bring change.</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Social</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Family life</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Customs</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class or Caste</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Roles</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Decision-making</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Education</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Leisure activities</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Belief</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Myth</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Ritual.</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Political</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Decision-making</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Citizenship</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Leadership institutions.</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Aesthetic</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Music</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Dance</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Literature</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Leisure activities</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member/>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Social Structure</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member> What classes exist?, </member>
            <member> How is the hierarchy of classes organized?</member>
            <member> Upon what is the stratification of the classes based?</member>
            <member> What are the roles of the men, women, children?</member>
            <member> What is the family structure?</member>
            <member> What social problems exist?</member>
            <member> Who cares for and provides education to the children?</member>
            <member> is there prejudice, persecution, etc.?</member>
            <member> If so, what groups are involved? </member>
            <member> How are the children socialized?</member>
            <member> Who provides care for the infirmed?</member>
            <member> Who cares for the elderly?</member>
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Religion</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member>What are the beliefs of the society concerning life and death?</member>
            <member>What is considered good and what is considered evil?</member>
            <member>Who do they worship?</member>
            <member>Where do they worship?</member>
            <member>Are there any sacrifices?</member>
            <member>What role does religion play in their social lives?</member>
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Communication and Education</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member>What languages are spoken?, </member>
            <member>How is the language recorded?, </member>
            <member>How are messages and information passed along?, </member>
            <member>How is history recorded?,</member>
            <member>is the society literate or illiterate?, </member>
            <member>Who provides education?, </member>
            <member>Who receives education?, </member>
            <member>What is the "technology" involved in long distance communication?</member>

        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Power and Authority</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member> What are the rules? </member>
            <member> Who made the rules?</member>
            <member> How does society get its rules?</member>
            <member> What is the source of power?</member>
            <member> How is justice dispensed?</member>
            <member> How are criminals apprehended?</member>
            <member> What punishments are used?</member>
            <member> Who are the rulers?</member>
            <member> How are the rulers chosen?</member>
            <member> How is power passed on to the next leaders?</member>
            <member> What groups have the most political power?</member>

        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Leisure and Recreation</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member> In what sports does people participate?, </member>
            <member> What games are played?, </member>
            <member> What institutions or organizations provides recreation?</member>
            <member> What type of sports are considered spectator sports?</member>
            <member> What toys does children use?, </member>
            <member> What other types of participatory recreation exist?</member>
            <member> What other types of spectator recreation exist?</member>
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Artistic Expression</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member> What are the mediums of the graphic arts?</member>
            <member> What dances do the people do?</member>
            <member> What types of music are there?</member>
            <member> What themes are present in art, music, dance?</member>
            <member> What is the source of these themes?</member>
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Technology</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>General</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Medical</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>What do people do for pain?</member>
                <member>What are do they do about disease?</member>
                <member>How do people heal?</member>
                <member>Are there hospitals, healers, infirmary's, or medics?</member>
            </simplelist>

        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Weapon</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Magick</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>General</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Medical</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Weapon</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Kinship</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Family</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>What is considered a normal family unit?</member>
                <member>How extended is an extended family?</member>
                <member>How important are family connections and responsibilities?</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Ethics, Morals and Mores</title>
        <para/>
        <simplelist>
            <member>What will people swear a binding oath by?</member>
            <member>What do people use as curse words?</member>
            
            <member>What is the most desired/most valuable stuff in this society — gold, jewels, drugs, money, furs, reindeer, etc.?</member>
            <member>Why is it desired/valued?</member>
            <member>Do different races value different things?</member>
            <member>Is there a race/culture for whom non-material things (information, time) are the most valuable things?</member>
            <member>How did they get that way?</member>
            
            <member>What things are considered normal and acceptable in this society that would not be considered normal or acceptable in yours?</member>
            <member>What things are considered shocking in this society that are not considered shocking in yours — e.g., eating left-handed, reading in public?</member>
            <member>What would be the reaction of an ordinary person who sees someone doing one of these things — to turn away, call the cops, challenge the offender to a duel, </member>
            
            <member>What are the acceptable limits to honor and/or honesty in this society?</member>
            <member>Are “white lies” acceptable socially, or is lying in any form considered beyond the pall?</member>
            <member>Is thievery an accepted, if disreputable, occupation, or is it a crime?</member>
            
            <member>Is a binding oath unbreakable no matter what, or can you get out of it if the other party turns out to be evil scum or if you weren’t fully informed?</member>
            <member>What is considered the right thing to do if two oaths come into conflict — do you have to decide as best you can, hold to the oath to the most/least powerful person, commit suicide?</member>
            
            <member>What are attitudes toward ownership?</member>
            <member>What constitutes “theft” and what can be stolen — gems, gold, someone’s good name or reputation?</member>
            <member>Are thieves independent criminals, members of an illegal guild, business people licensed by law, or what?</member>
            <member>What are the controversial subjects in this culture?</member>
            <member>What things can you start a friendly argument about in any bar?</member>
            <member>What things will automatically start an unfriendly argument?</member>
            
            <member>What are the social taboos — what things are “not done,” like wearing a bathing suit to the office?</member>
            <member>What things are not talked about?</member>
            <member>What would happen if someone did?</member>
            <member>How do these taboos vary among the different races?</member>
            
            <member>What are the biggest social faux pas — burping loudly, drawing steel in the presence of a queen/noble, asking a dwarf whether it’s male or female?</member>
            <member>What subjects or actions cause embarrassment or discomfort?</member>
            
        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Language</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member>How many languages are there? </member>
            <member>Which ones are related (e.g., the Romance languages) and why? </member>
            <member>Which languages borrow words or phrases from other languages? </member>
            <member>Which is likely to be most widely spoken?</member>
            <member>Is there a “trade language” that facilitates commerce between countries that
                don’t speak the same tongue? </member>
            <member>Is there a “universal language” spoken by educated or noble persons, as Latin
                was in the Middle Ages?</member>
        </simplelist>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language Tree</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Mapping</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Dialects</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Literacy</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Writing Forms</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Sounds</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Vocabulary and Grammar</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Cosmology</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Deities</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Myths</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>History</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Customs and Traditions</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Greeting and Meeting</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>When meeting someone, how are they greeted — wave, handshake, bow, some other gesture?</member>
                <member>How did the greeting gesture originate (example: shaking hands to prove one’s weapon hand was empty)?</member>
                <member>Is there a special I-am-not-armed gesture for wizards?</member>
                
                <member>Is there a difference between the greeting offered to an equal and that offered to a superior or inferior?</member>
                <member>Is there a difference between the greeting offered a man or a woman?</member>
                <member>Human/non-human?</member>
                
                <member>Is there a way of changing a greeting gesture to make it insulting?</member>
                
                <member>How are two people who have never met normally introduced to each other?</member>
                <member>What is the order of precedence when there are several people of differing sex or social status present, all of whom need to be introduced to each other?</member>
                
                <member>Are there classes of people/beings who are never introduced to other classes of people/beings?</member>
                <member>Are “true names” significant, and if so, under what circumstances would someone be given another person/being’s true name?</member>
                
                <member>Are there customs involving the way in which someone is named when being introduced </member>
                
                <member>Is there any difference in the way you greet someone you already know, compared to greeting a stranger (or does everybody just always hug or shake hands?</member>
                
                <member> How does someone acknowledge seeing an acquaintance at a distance (passing on the other side of the street) — by a nod, tipping the hat, wave, smile, or not at all?</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Wedding</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Bedding</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Birthing</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>What customs surround a birth and the introduction of a new child to the
                    family?</member>
                <member>Is the mother sequestered for some period?</member>
                <member>Is the child?</member>
                <member>Is there a formal presentation of the new child to parents, grandparents,
                    overlord, priest?</member>
                <member>Is a feast and celebration declared, or does everyone keep a low profile to
                    keep from attracting demons or bad luck?</member>

                <member>Who is normally present for births?</member>
                <member>Is it strictly a matter for women, or are men involved, or is the only woman
                    present the expectant mother?</member>

            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Battle</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Burying</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>What customs surround death and burial?</member>
                <member>Is there a special class of people (doctors, priests, funeral directors, untouchables) who deal with dead bodies?</member>
                <member>What things must be done and why (burn hair to free spirit, burn body to prevent necromancy, coins on eyes for ferryman, etc.)?</member>
                <member>Are the dead feared, revered, or ignored?</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Other</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Institutions</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Rites of Passage</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>What are the rites of passage in this culture?</member>
                <member>Are they formalized rituals, such as being dubbed a knight, or are they
                    informal?</member>
                <member>Are they different for men and women?</member>
                <member>For nobility and peasants?</member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Clergy</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Rites and Rituals</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religious Norms</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
        <para/>

        <sect2>
            <title>Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Common Motifs</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Significant Numbers</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Architecture</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Politics</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Leadership</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Stated</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Actual</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Class Structure</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member>Are there non-human/foriegn residents of the culture</member>
            <member>Do foriegn tend to take up different trades from humans? </member>
            <member>Are they legally limited to certain trades?</member>

        </simplelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Judicial Structure</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member>How has the presence of magic and magicians affected law and government? </member>
            <member>Are wizards barred from certain kinds of government jobs or offices (judge,
                jury, police)? </member>
            <member>Do some government jobs require that their holder be a wizard?</member>
            <member>What are considered normal and legal ways of gathering evidence and determining
                guilt? </member>
            <member>Is torture allowed? </member>
            <member>Are arbitrary judgments by the lord or landowner allowed, or is there an
                independent standard of justice?</member>
            <member>What personal weapons are available to anyone who can afford them? </member>
            <member>Are some considered “for nobles only” either by custom or by law? </member>
            <member>Are there laws forbidding certain classes from being armed at all? </member>
            <member>Are there laws requiring certain classes to learn particular weapon skills, as
                England for some centuries required yeomen to be proficient with the
                longbow?</member>
            <member>Is forensic magic possible? </member>
            <member>Commonly used? </member>
            <member>Used only for certain types of crimes (and if so, what)? </member>
            <member>Are the results of forensic spells admissible in court as evidence? </member>
            <member>Is it something any wizard can do, or do you have to specialize?</member>
            <member>Are certain spells (as opposed to magic generally) illegal? </member>
            <member>Why — because of the effect of the spell, or because of the ingredients or
                procedures needed to cast it, or what? </member>
            <member>If so, how would a criminal magician be detected? Apprehended? Punished? </member>
            <member>Is catching and punishing illegal magicians the responsibility of the magician’s
                guild, or do the ordinary courts have to handle it?</member>
            <member>Are there separate civil and criminal courts? </member>
            <member>Human and non-human courts? </member>
            <member>Is there a separate court or procedure for magical crimes? </member>
            <member>What is different about each type of court? </member>
            <member>Are judges or other court officials required/forbidden to know magic? </member>
            <member>Is evidence obtained by magic acceptable in court? </member>
            <member>Is evidence obtained by magic considered more reliable or less reliable than
                physical evidence or eyewitness accounts?</member>
            <member>What things are considered truly serious crimes and why? </member>
            <member>What are the normal punishments for serious vs. minor crimes? </member>
            <member>Are there prisons, or are people punished and released? </member>
            <member>Are there degrees of punishment — branding vs. cutting off ears vs. cutting off
                a hand vs. decapitation — or do they just hang everybody?</member>
            <member>Who is responsible for catching criminals? </member>
            <member>Who pays the crook-catchers — the ruler, the city government, a consortium of
                merchants, somebody else? </member>
            <member>How are they organized — into independent police precincts, or into overlapping
                districts, or just according to whoever wants to hire them? </member>
            <member>Are they full-time, part-time, or volunteers? </member>
            <member>Private or public? </member>
            <member>What sort of facilities do they have? </member>
            <member>What arms are the allowed to carry?</member>
            <member>Are there lawyers or advocates? </member>
            <member>Who can afford them? </member>
            <member>Who trains/certifies them?</member>
            <member>Are people guilty until proven innocent, innocent until proven guilty, or does
                it depend on the mood the lord is in when they bring the case before him?</member>
            <member>Are there judges other than the ruler, lord, or landowner? </member>
            <member>If so, how are they chosen, how are they paid, and who pays them? </member>
            <member>Are appeals possible, and if so, to whom? </member>
            <member>How often are outlying areas likely to see a judge? </member>
            <member>Is “mob justice” common or uncommon? </member>
            <member>Approved of or disapproved of?</member>
            <member>Are there sumptuary laws regulating what different classes/races may wear? </member>
            <member>Do judges and lawyers wear special clothes (robes, wigs) to indicate their
                calling?</member>
            <member>Are wizards above or below the law i.e., do they have full rights as citizens,
                no rights, or can they do as they like without regard to anyone else’s rights </member>
            <member>Are highwaymen, muggers, and pirates common or rare? What sorts of crimes is the
                average citizen likely to run across during his/her lifetime?</member>
            <member>Who can make or repeal laws — a group (an elected Senate, an appointed Council,
                or an hereditary House of Lords), or only the ruler or head of state? </member>
            <member>How much can the nobility, middle class tradesmen, etc. influence the laws that
                are made?</member>
            <member>How are alleged criminals treated before and after their convictions? </member>
            <member>Do the police/military/city guard make a practice of roughing up suspects, or is
                this frowned upon?</member>

        </simplelist>
        <sect2>
            <title>Making the Laws</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Enforcing the Laws</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Legal Code</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Ownership of Goods</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Land</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Male and Female Roles</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Church and State</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Death by Suicide</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Death by Anothers Hand</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Death in Self Defense</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Military</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Standing</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Command</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Routine</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Arms</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Outfitting</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Theory</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

</article>
