<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>The Arcanus</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Jim</firstname>
                <surname>Mochel</surname>
            </personname>
            <email>jmochel@saltations.org</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <part>
        <title>That which is unseen</title>
        <chapter>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>The Spirit World</title>
                <para>..Spirit Winds.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>The Occult</title>
                <para>..Ley lines, Nexus.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>The Divine</title>
                <subtitle>The Word</subtitle>
                <para>.Under all lies the word...Dragon Lines ... Holy Places.. Clearings...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>The Spirit World</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>Spirit</title>
                <para>...<quote>Embracing, you become embraced. Clearing your vision, you become
                        clear. Accepting the World, you embrace Spirit. Bearing and nurturing,
                        Creating but not owning, Giving without demanding, Controlling without
                        authority, This is Spirit</quote></para>
                <para>What spirit is...what it looks like...</para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>At the Center</title>
                    <subtitle>Totems</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Pulls from</title>
                    <subtitle>...</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Spirit Monks</title>
                        <para>...Flows with...Ki</para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Summoners</title>
                        <para>...Uses...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Pushed to</title>
                    <subtitle>...</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Shaman</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Spirit Talker</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Useing their own </title>
                    <subtitle>...</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Psychics</title>
                        <para>Psi...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>The Occult</title>
            <para>Magic Is the ability to manipulate mana. Spell casters use their own internal
                energies to manipulate Mana. It is not known where Mana comes from, but mana is
                generally all around us, it flows and pool. The caster uses their own energy to
                raise, focus, and apply mana. The act of raising, focusing and applying energy is
                called spell casting. That spellcasting can be very unstructured all the way up to
                very structured. </para>
            <para>If you view mana as a kind of water then the very unstructured forms of spell
                casting are like scooping the water up in your hands and splashing them at someone
                as opposed to creating dams and dikes and pipes and hoses to deliver the water where
                you want to go. As you go from less structured to more structured it takes less
                energy to achieve the same result while taking more time and often requiring more
                care and detail work. The simplest form of casting are cantrips, which of the
                equivalent of splashing water out of a pool with your hand. They are blazingly
                quick, not particularly effective for anything beyond very small results like
                lighting a candle. The next form is slightly more structured, and it is called
                sorcery. A sorcerer is kind of like a kid with a hand pump who can pull up the water
                and direct it while dynamically changing with the circumstances so that they can
                redirect the water at the drop of a hat. The next level up, Wizardry, is much more
                structured but it does come in a range of complexities from simple structures with
                tightly focused purposes (Squirt guns), to more general Complicated structures
                (household plumbing), all the way up to monumental works (the Hoover dam)</para>
            <para>Many has types or flavours</para>
            <para> Each type of mana behaves in its own particular way especially when being
                manipulated by the caster or when interacting with each other. Some of these ways
                are very logical. The magical element of water is very effective in combating the
                magical element of fire. The magical element of fire takes more work to control but
                produces more damage than the magical element of air. The magical element of dark is
                diametrically opposed to the magical element of light. There are some energies that
                human mages can barely get access to and even when they are casting with them they
                are often on the edge of being out of control. There are also energies that are so
                phenomenally dangerous that only the most powerful of mages can even attempt to work
                with them. </para>
            <para>Mana is often used in or generated by the activities of word or spirit, but never
                as aprimary part of the activity.</para>

            <sect1>
                <title>The Fundamentals</title>
                <para>The insanely dangerous energies. Chaos or Wild Magics. Wild magics are the
                    magic of creation. They are profoundly chaotic, almost impossible to control,
                    and wildly powerful. The world is designed so that the structure of the world
                    prevents easy access to wild magics. Casting with wild magic is very much like a
                    human trying to redirect lightning with their bare hands. They have a name for
                    that type of spellcaster, the name is "fuse".</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>The Eternals</title>
                <para>The sometimes I can cast with them energies The eternal energies are a set of
                    energies that are slow to summon, slippery to hold, hard to redirect, often
                    difficult to banish and often have lasting effects and echoes. In general even
                    though they are actually highly ordered and structured, that Order is rarely
                    apparent to the spellcaster. These energies are known as Belief, Stream, and
                    Fabric</para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Belief</title>
                    <para> Belief is the energy generated by the exercise of faith. It is very
                        difficult to get a handle on and generally only the gods can reliably use
                        it. This really is the power of miracles. It can be cast and manipulated by
                        mages and is used by priests and priestesses. It despite that there is a
                        fundamental difference between when a mage or priest attempts to manipulate
                        belief and when the divine is present. Don't make the mistake of believing
                        that a priest is simply a mage. A priest is a channel for their
                        deity.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Stream</title>
                    <para>Stream is the energy of time and possibilities. Like belief is very
                        difficult to get a handle on and generally only the gods can reliably use
                        it. Mages and shamans and others such as oracles can use it in much the same
                        way that humans can ride a rhinoceros. You may be physically able to do it,
                        but you really don't have much ability to control the direction it goes.
                        Someone who is using Stream can see what is happened in the past (Generally
                        much easier than any other type of usage of Stream) as well as get a sense
                        of what may be in the future. In general the foreseeings done with Stream
                        are highly influenced by the mental state of the person doing the seeing. In
                        other words, they often see the types of things they would expect to
                        see.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Fabric</title>
                    <para> Fabric is the energy of space. Like belief and stream is very difficult
                        to get a handle on and only the gods can reliably use it. But it is
                        relatively easier to control spell castings with Fabric. This is the energy
                        associated with seeing things at a distance (clairvoyance) as well as being
                        associated with the Really cool spells like teleportation.</para>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>

            <sect1>
                <title>The Elementals </title>
                <para>The bread-and-butter of most spell casters Elemental powers are fairly easy
                    for a spellcaster to get a handle on. The world is designed in such a way that
                    mages have relatively easy access to the elemental energies. They are generally
                    fast to summon and easy to manipulate and behave according to various rules and
                    principles. They have their own kind of order and will behave in predictable
                    ways. Elemental energies are less likely to have lasting magical effects then
                    the Eternal energies and they can have have fairly lasting physical effects.
                    Most creatures are actually composed of a balance of the elemental energies in a
                    dynamic balance. Too much exposure to any one elemental energy can imbalance an
                    individual and make them sick. One of the first things that most spell casters
                    learn is how to manipulate the energy without taking it into themselves and thus
                    unbalancing themselves. The elemental energies are: </para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Basic Elementals</title>
                    <para/>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>Fire - Fire is quick to summon hard to control or banish. Losing
                            control usually means something gets scorched. In general fire likes to
                            do damage and consume things. </member>
                        <member>Water - Water is less quick to summon, almost as hard to control as
                            fire, but it is rarely necessary to banish it because you can usually
                            just let it dissipate and run off itself. Water is harder to focus in
                            order to damage. </member>
                        <member>Air - Air is quick to summon and hard to control or banish the
                            losing control rarely involves major damage. Air is very hard to focus
                            in order to damage though it moves quickly</member>
                        <member>Earth - Earth is slow to summon, hard to move, and slow to stop.
                            Once going, Earth can do a great deal of damage</member>
                        <member> Light - Light is quick to summon, easy to move, relatively easy to
                            stop although you do need to do it quickly. In general Light does not
                            tend to do a great deal of damage but it's side effects are often more
                            significant ( temporarily blinding someone, distracting someone etc.) </member>
                        <member>Dark - Dark is also quick to summon, easy to move and relatively
                            easy to stop. Like light it does not tend to do a great deal of damage
                            but again its side effects are often significant.</member>
                        <member> Life - Life energies are slightly slower to summon then light and
                            dark, as well as being very hard to focus on something. Life energies
                            are lousy for doing damage with. You can conceivably hit somebody with
                            so much life that they are unbalanced. Life energies are better for
                            certain types of healings and divinations. They are very useful for
                            doing damage to creatures animated by deah such as the undead.</member>
                        <member> Death - Death energies are slightly slower to summon them light and
                            dark, as well as being very hard to focus on something. By the very
                            nature Death energies are useful in injuring living creatures. </member>
                    </simplelist>

                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Ephemerals</title>
                    <para>
                        <simplelist>
                            <member>Shadow - Shadow is normally a fleeting type of energy that is
                                created by the interaction of light and dark. Sometimes you can find
                                pools of shadow at twilight but generally it exists in those
                                locations between light and dark. While shadow is not the most
                                reliable of elemental materials it does have some advantages for
                                several key actions: such as confusing a person's eyes, clouding
                                their minds or causing fear. Shadow also has a "resonance" with
                                other blocks of shadow. As a result, Shadow mages have easier access
                                to the ability to walk from shadow to shadow.</member>
                            <member>Nature - "Life is, Nature will be". In general nature occurs
                                where there is a preponderance of life and a small amount of death.
                                There is a natural dynamically generated energy called nature.
                                Nature is the energy that binds most living things to the natural
                                order. </member>
                            <member>Shamans often deal with Nature. Decay - Decay occurs where there
                                is a preponderance of death and a smaller amount of life. Decay is
                                the energy that binds most Undead to that unnatural order.</member>
                        </simplelist>
                    </para>
                </sect2>



            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Practicioners</title>
                <subtitle>Mana</subtitle>
                <para>Text</para>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>wizard</title>
                    <para>A wizard (wyzard) is a male practicer of magic(k). Often this title was
                        used interchangeably with witch. In the middle ages, the title became more
                        common with users of HIGH magic(K), or what is known as ceremonial magic(k).
                        This was different from the magic(k) practiced by many people of the heath,
                        known as heathens or pagans, who tended to practice low or natural herbal
                        magic which relied less on christian and Hebrew themes and overtones and
                        more on nature spirits. </para>
                </formalpara>

                <formalpara>
                    <title>Magician</title>
                    <para>A Magician historically was not sex specific and was applied to either
                        males or females who practice a form of magic(k). In time it has been used
                        almost exclusively to mean stage magicians, who use illusions and slight of
                        hand to appear to obtain some sort of occult knowledge. But a practicing
                        magician, not a stage magician, is simply a practitioner of magic(K).</para>
                </formalpara>

                <formalpara>
                    <title>sorcerer</title>
                    <para>A sorcerer is a practitioner of magic(K), male or female with the female
                        version of the word often being sorceress but sorcerer is still appropriate,
                        but this label has been historically associated with malicious intent, so
                        someone who uses magic(k) for ill or for negative ends. (also sorcerers are
                        also associated with conjurations and not just ritual magic(k) or talisman
                        work though a sorcerer may be proficient in both. </para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>witch</title>
                    <para>A warlock is a badly used term. People ignorantly use it interchangeably
                        for the male version of the word witch, but it is not. It means a liar or
                        someone who is a traitor. In it's worse terms it means a person who has
                        sealed his soul with an demonic entity, hence why the name was labeled onto
                        male witches (or wizards) during the 14th century in Europe, as a form of
                        disgrace. I hope that helps you. </para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>warlock</title>
                    <para>A warlock is a badly used term. People ignorantly use it interchangeably
                        for the male version of the word witch, but it is not. It means a liar or
                        someone who is a traitor. In it's worse terms it means a person who has
                        sealed his soul with an demonic entity, hence why the name was labeled onto
                        male witches (or wizards) during the 14th century in Europe, as a form of
                        disgrace. I hope that helps you. </para>
                </formalpara>

            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>The Divine</title>
                <subtitle>Word</subtitle>
                <para>Text</para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Self</title>
                    <subtitle>...</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Demi-deities</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>

                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Dragons</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Namers</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Granted</title>
                    <subtitle>...</subtitle>
                    <para>...</para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Avatars</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Priests</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Oracles</title>
                        <para>...</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>The Divine</title>
            <para> Ur. They ruled, they hunted, and were solitary. They knew only the rule of power.
                Cooperation did not exist for them. They ruled by sword. Their magic was of the most
                savage and basic but powerful. They rode the dragons. Children Urvile Granted
                Demondim "Tor'' and their noble leaders the "Lordim-Tor'' Duwan Kurrok Mergoth.
                Kailm (Forerunners of the Haroch) </para>
        </chapter>


    </part>
    <part>
        <title>Spirit</title>
        <subtitle><quote>Spirit is in us. Spirit is all around us. Spirit is the
                balance.</quote><quote>Spirit does not knock, yet does not
            intrude!</quote></subtitle>
        <chapter>
            <title>Totem </title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>

        <chapter>
            <title>Spirit Talker</title>
            <subtitle>AKA Shaman, Witch doctor, Wiseman</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>Shamans live in two worlds, the world of flesh and the world of spirits. Since
                    the world was young there have been those who walked between both worlds,
                    existing in both but belonging to neither. It is a shaman’s job to serve both
                    worlds. The shaman serves the spirit world by helping keep a balance between the
                    realm of spirit and the physical realm. The shaman usually aids the spirits by
                    performing rituals of cleansing, or performing rituals to thank the spirits or
                    offer the spirits his body to interact with this world for a short time. Spirits
                    will often grant boons for such services. Deals can also be made with spirits. </para>
                <para> Shamans will often take on strange taboos which can last for month to years,
                    or maybe his entire life. If these taboos are broken then the shaman loses face
                    in the eyes of the spirit world. But remember, there must always be
                    compensation. The way of the spirits is the way of balance. There is always a
                    cost for every service. Everything must balance in the end. That is not to say
                    that a shaman cannot do something from the goodness of his own heart, but that
                    every favor given is a favor owed and every gain comes with a loss. In the
                    description of some of the shaman’s bonuses and rituals it mentions things like
                    pure places or natural places. Anywhere it says anything like this it means a
                    place either taken back by nature and relatively left alone by man, or places
                    that man have never been. </para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Becoming a Shaman</title>
                    <para> They say the first step is the hardest, and this is especially true of
                        shamans. In order to become a shaman one must die first. When the
                        shaman-to-be has a near-death experience (whether intentional or not) and
                        his soul leaves his body, he is met by a spirit guide. It is the spirit
                        guide’s duty to explain all that is expected of the shaman, the hardships he
                        may have to endure and that he will never again be truly a part of mortal
                        society. The spirit will not sugarcoat this, the shaman must be fully aware
                        of what will become of him if he makes this deal. If the deal is made, the
                        guiding spirit becomes the shaman's totem spirit and the shaman is given a
                        permanent taboo, the first of many. The totem spirit will teach the shaman
                        what he needs to know to carry out his duties, and what his rewards will
                        be</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Constraints</title>
                    <para>Shamans must honour at least one taboo to connect himself to his totem.
                        This Taboo is a life long Taboo. Taboos need not be difficult to fulfill,
                        but it does make the shaman stand out. All Shamans get -1 to Social stat.
                        This negative does not count when dealing with the spirits. If a shaman
                        breaks a taboo he loses the favor of the spirit world. He still retains the
                        ability to interact with the spirit world but loses all bonuses and powers
                        gained from spirits, and none but the most corrupt and wicked spirits will
                        deal with the shaman until the shaman makes amends with the spirit whose
                        taboo he broke. </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Benefits</title>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Spirit Sight</title>
                        <para> While performing specific rituals, or while under the effect of
                            certain drugs, the shaman can see and hear the spirit world as vague
                            shadows. Also, spirits can see through to this world as a vague shadow,
                            but shamans glow brightly for them. Once a spirit sees a shaman, the
                            spirits can then communicate with the shaman. </para>
                        <para> Only alcohol or natural drugs will allow the shaman to see the spirit
                            world. Shamans are immune to hallucinogenic or mind- altering effects of
                            these drugs and alcohol (though they may still suffer from slurred
                            speech and lowered reflexes and reaction time). Synthetic, man-made
                            drugs will not allow the shaman to see the spirit world. The shaman can
                            look into the spirit world without the use of drugs or alcohol or
                            without performing a ritual. </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Spirit Possession/Channel</title>
                        <para> The spirit can use any powers it has in the Material realm while
                            possessing the shaman. Shamans know the difference between spirits and
                            demons and get a + 5 to save against demonic possession. </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Commune</title>
                        <para> ...</para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Awaken the Spirit</title>
                        <para> All things, be they animate or inanimate, have a spirit. This is not
                            to say all things have a soul (a common mistake), but deep down all
                            things are aware. A shaman can awaken the spirit in an object or being
                            and communicate with it. An awakened object will strive to become the
                            utmost of what the object can be. Basis of Native Borne Craft agic ?
                        </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Create Fetish</title>
                        <para> Fetishes are object imbued with either the essence of a spirit or a
                            spirit itself making it a magical item. The items containing the essence
                            of a spirit can be used to contact the spirit whose essence it contains.
                        </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Natural Healer</title>
                        <para> Shamans have a long tradition as healers. They can fight off corrupt
                            spirits causing illness and can ask the plants and herbs what medicinal
                            usage they may have. All shamans get a +5 ranks in Holistic Medicine.
                        </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Totem Spirit</title>
                        <para> All shamans get a totem spirit. The shaman can always reach out his
                            voice and call his totem guide to him. A shaman will usually only do
                            this if absolutely necessary. The totem spirit is under no actual
                            obligation to come as soon as called, but most will do their best to get
                            to the shaman as quickly as possible. </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> The Spirit Way</title>
                        <para> Shamans must learn the way of the spirit in order to help them and
                            make deals with them. After the shaman makes the deal with his totem
                            spirit, the totem spirit begins teaching him the ways of the spirit. All
                            shamans get +5 to Spirit Lore. They also get a +2 to Law skill. They
                            also understand the language of the spirits. </para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title> Rituals</title>
                        <para> The shaman deals with the spiritual world through magical rituals
                            usually taught by the shaman's totem spirit. All shamans get +1 ranks in
                            Magic Skill. </para>
                    </sect3>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
                <formalpara>
                    <title/>
                    <para/>
                </formalpara>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>

        <chapter>
            <title>Psychic </title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Spirit Monk </title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Mystic </title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Summoner </title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Rupa-Kechil</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of word .</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Native Borne</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of word .</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>

    </part>

    <part>
        <title>Occult</title>
        <subtitle><quote>...</quote></subtitle>
        <chapter>
            <title>Elves</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Mystic</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Sorcerer</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Wizard</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Changelings</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Lycanthropes</title>
            <subtitle>..Partakes of Spirit and Magery.</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Duwan</title>
            <subtitle>..Partakes of Spirit .</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Uru</title>
            <subtitle>..Partakes of Spirit.</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Kurrock</title>
            <subtitle>..Partakes of Magery.</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Occult Casting</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>The flow of casting.</title>
                <para>There are three steps in any manipulation of mana. (whether it be cantrip,
                    spell, ritual or rite). The first is gathering the energy, the second is
                    focusing that energy and the third is releasing it.</para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Gathering</title>
                    <para>athering the energy is a fundamental part of the casting process. Most
                        spells will use the mage's internal energy to summon and manipulate the
                        specific type of energy needed. How well a character can access their own
                        power is governed by their PSI stat. Using the power to gather energy
                        expends Mental Fatigue. This MFT can be supplemented by energy from Material
                        Components, Magic Items, Living Sacrifice, Worship, Physical Exertion, or
                        just by being given the energy by another. The skill used in gathering the
                        energy is Manipulate Energy. An ME skill is needed for each type of energy
                        to be manipulated. ME: skills such as ME:Fire can be used to make perception
                        rolls for detecting the energy in question. A perception skill for a
                        specific energy type can be used to determine the intensity and extent of
                        the energy.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Focusing</title>
                    <para>In focusing the energy the caster directs and channels the energies toward
                        a specific end. Material components used during this part of the spell would
                        be used for channeling the energies involved \footnote{ Material Component
                        could be damaged (magically) if it cannot contain the energies involved}.
                        Somatic and verbal components add to this part of the spell process as does
                        any meditative state or trance.. The mage determines how much energy will be
                        applied at this point. The time taken in focusing the energies is spent in
                        setting up the various actions to be performed by the energy. The time spent
                        in applying the energy is fairly constant compared to the time spent
                        focusing the energies.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Applying or loosing</title>
                    <para>The energy released should follow the form laid out by the caster when he
                        focused on the spell</para>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Casting Types</title>
                <para>Spell types Spells vary in their complexity and in the time it takes to cast
                    them. There are special names for spell casts of a given complexity and cast
                    time. Those names are Sorceries, Cantrips, Spells, Rituals and Rites. </para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Cantrips</title>
                    <para>Cantrips are simple magicks. They are simple in structure and low powered.
                        Often simple material components will supply the power needed. A caster
                        casting cantrips needs to have a skill in Casting:Cantrips in order to be
                        considered ranked in the action they are attempting. </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Sorceries</title>
                    <para>Sorceries are castings that have a structure imposed by the caster at the
                        time of cast and are generally fairly flexible. </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Spells</title>
                    <para>Spells are ritualized sorceries. They have a structure and effect that are
                        determined when they are designed. Thus a caster using a ``Throw Fire''
                        spell may only vary the specific effects of the spell taht are designed to
                        be varied. </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Ritual</title>
                    <para> A ritual is a highly structured and detailed spell that involves the
                        manipulation of more than one mages worth of energy at a time. In order to
                        do this the caster must gather power from some outside source. To cast
                        rituals requires the Hold Energy skill for energy type being used.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Rites</title>
                    <para> A rite is a ritual that requires the work of two or more casters during
                        its casting.</para>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>



        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Occult Castings Design</title>

            <para> Spell design consists of isolating the various attributes of the spell such as
                the energies to be used and the actions to be taken and using these attributes to
                add or subtract from a pool of Spell Design Points (SDP). Factors in Spell Design
                are </para>
            <sect1>
                <title>Attributes used in spell design</title>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Energy Type - This describes the types of energies to be manipulated. </member>
                    <member>Actions </member>
                    <member>This is what the energies are to be used for. </member>
                    <member/>
                    <member/>
                    <member/>
                </simplelist>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Energy Types</title>
                <para>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>Personal Energies: Power and Psi. Both are easy to summon from
                            within or raise via sacrifice. </member>
                        <member>Eternal energies : Belief, Fabric and Stream. Belief is the energy
                            created by the worship or investment of faith in another entity, being,
                            or object. Stream is the energy derived from the dynamics of the time
                            continua. Fabric is the energy derived from the shifts of equilibrium of
                            seemingly static forces involved in the here and now. </member>
                        <member>The Elemental energies are Light, Dark, Fire, Air, Water, Earth,
                            Life, Death.</member>
                        <member>The Ephemeral energies are Shadow, Nature, and Decay</member>

                    </simplelist>
                </para>
            </sect1>

            <sect1>
                <title>Actions</title>

                <para> This is what the energies are to be used for. These actually spend time
                    during the Focusing process. These actions are often described in a pairing
                    between an action and its opposite. <segmentedlist>
                        <title>Actions</title>
                        <?dbhtml list-presentation="table"?>
                        <?dbfo list-presentation="table"?>
                        <segtitle>Name</segtitle>
                        <segtitle>Description</segtitle>

                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Detection </seg>
                            <seg>Identifying the existence of something.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Concealment </seg>
                            <seg>Hiding the existence of something</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Divination </seg>
                            <seg>Determining something about an objects nature.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Anti-Divination</seg>
                            <seg> Blocking the determination of the attributes of an object or
                                occurence.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Summoning </seg>
                            <seg>Bringing energy to the immediate locale .</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Banishment </seg>
                            <seg>Returning energy from the immediate locale to its origin.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Creation </seg>
                            <seg>The generation of an energy from nothing.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Destruction </seg>
                            <seg>The elimination of an energy from existence.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Concentration </seg>
                            <seg>The gathering of energy from the nearby region to a more intense
                                whole.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Dissapation </seg>
                            <seg>The scattering of energy into a more diffuse form.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Transport </seg>
                            <seg>To move through a distance.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Anti-transport</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Binding </seg>
                            <seg>To tie energy to a physical object.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Releasing</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Transmutation</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Stasis</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Translocation </seg>
                            <seg>To travel a distance without passing through the fabric of the
                                current plane.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Anchoring </seg>
                            <seg>To prevent translocation.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Influence</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Control</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Damage </seg>
                            <seg>To rend or otherwise hurt.</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Restore</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Shield</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Activate </seg>
                            <seg>Activates a spell</seg>
                        </seglistitem>
                        <seglistitem>
                            <seg>Hold</seg>
                            <seg/>
                        </seglistitem>
                    </segmentedlist>
                </para>
            </sect1>

            <sect1>
                <title>Components</title>
                <para> Casting Components covers external props, preparation, and other components. <simplelist>
                        <member>Verbal - Verbal Components are vocal actions that aid in the casting
                            of the spell. This is the default. It assumes a normal speaking voice
                            chant.</member>
                        <member>Somatic - Somatic Components are physical actions such as hand
                            waving or finger moving.</member>
                        <member>Material - Material components are physical objects or materials
                            that aid in supplying, channeling, or directing energy.</member>
                        <member>Preparation - Preparation covers any activity that may be performed
                            before the spell is cast.</member>
                        <member>True Name></member>
                    </simplelist>
                </para>
            </sect1>

            <sect1>
                <title>Components Properties</title>
                <para> Each casting components value to the design of the spell may be modified by
                    the various properties of the Casting Components. If the material is rare or
                    particularly fine, it will add to the spell's abilities. <simplelist>
                        <member>Expensive</member>
                        <member>Cheap</member>
                        <member>Rare</member>
                        <member>Common</member>
                        <member>Renewable</member>
                        <member>Non-Renewable</member>
                        <member>Reusable</member>
                        <member>Non-Reusable</member>
                        <member>Complex</member>
                        <member>Loud</member>
                        <member>Quiet</member>
                        <member>Long</member>
                        <member>Short</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </para>
            </sect1>


            <sect1>
                <title>Target Type</title>

                <para> Factors involved in the Application of the Energy Target type describes
                    whether the energies affect a target, multiple targets, or no targets at all. A
                    Target Type is what the spell is directed at. A spell with no Target Type is
                    directed at the energy used in the spell. A ``Summon Fire'' spell has no target
                    type. A ``Blast'Em'' spell has a target type. <simplelist>
                        <member>No Target The spell is not intended to effect anything other than
                            the base energy type used in the spell.</member>
                        <member>Target,Self The spell is intended to effect the caster.</member>
                        <member>Single Target The spell is intended to effect on one object or
                            entity.</member>
                        <member>Multiple Targets The spell is intended to effect multiple targets.
                            The assumption here is that the Quantitative Effect is {\bf split}
                            between the multiple targets wheareas an Area of Effect spell has that
                            Quantitative Effect apply equally among all of the targets.</member>
                        <member>Area of Effect The spell is intended to effect everything in a given
                            area.</member>
                    </simplelist> A spell that has a range and a target but no Area of Effect would
                    look like this: A spell that has a Target and an Area of effect but no range
                    would look like: A spell that has a range and an Area of Effect would look like
                    this: Target Components A spell targeted at living creatures may be narrowed
                    down to effect only what is desired.Magic, Psi and Ki 8 Physical Form Mind
                    Perception </para>
            </sect1>




            <sect1>
                <title>Spell Statistics</title>
                <para> Each spell has six statistics that are manipulatable and balanced by the
                    spell designer. </para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Resistance (RES). Resistance is how easily can the spell be resisted.
                        The higher this value is the better it is for the caster. When doing spell
                        design the designer will be modifying Resistance. When the spell design is
                        complete the value for RES will be used to generate the Resistance
                        Difficulty Factor (RDF) Equation 1. Resistence RDF = 7 - Resistance</member>
                    <member>Quantitative Effect (QE). A quantitative value for the total effect a
                        spell can have. QE is a numeric constant. This is translated to actual
                        effect via a table. For Damage or Restoration spells this directly
                        translates as the damage done by the spell.</member>
                    <member>Casting Diffulty Factor (CDF). The Difficulty Factor involved in casting
                        the spell.</member>
                    <member>Energy Cost (EC). The Energy Cost is the amount of Mental Fatigue used
                        to cast the spell from start to finish.</member>
                    <member> Casting Time (CT). Casting Time is the time taken in pulses or any
                        appropriate time unit. More casting time is lower cost, less casting time is
                        higher cost.</member>
                    <member>Range</member>
                    <member/>
                </simplelist>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Attriubutes that are purchased in design.</title>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Casting Time</title>
                    <para/>
                    <table>
                        <title>Cost of Casting Time Scale in SDP</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Casting Time Scale</entry>
                                    <entry>Cost in SDP</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Pulse</entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Second</entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 5 Seconds</entry>
                                    <entry> 6 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1/2 Min</entry>
                                    <entry> 8 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 2 Minutes </entry>
                                    <entry>12 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 10 Minutes </entry>
                                    <entry>16 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Hour </entry>
                                    <entry>24 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 4 Hours </entry>
                                    <entry>32 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Day </entry>
                                    <entry>40 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Week </entry>
                                    <entry>48 </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>

                </sect2>

                <sect2>
                    <title>Range</title>
                    <para> Touch range spells require the caster to come into physical contact with
                        the target. Numeric range spells have a scale and value that is bought with
                        SDP. No Range Implies that the caster is the origin of the spell emanation
                        Touch Requires the casters body to come into contact with the Target. </para>
                    <table>
                        <title>SDP Range Scale</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Range Scale </entry>
                                    <entry> SDP </entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>


                                <row>
                                    <entry> 0 </entry>
                                    <entry> 0 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 0.1 Meter </entry>
                                    <entry> -2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 0.5 Meter </entry>
                                    <entry> -4 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Meter </entry>
                                    <entry> -8 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 5 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry> -12 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 10 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry> -16 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 100 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry> -24 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Km </entry>
                                    <entry> -32 </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>

                </sect2>

                <sect2>
                    <title>Duration</title>
                    <para> Duration(DUR). Duration is the length of time that the effect of the
                        spell lasts. An Instaneous spell lasts for a very small and fleeting
                        duration. Active Concentration duration spells last for as long as the
                        caster concenmtrates on the spell. Any other actions the caster may partake
                        of will be considered florentine actions. Passive Concentration duration
                        spells last for as long as the caster is concious and or clear minded.
                        Permanent spells last until dispelled or disrupted. Spells that have a
                        numeric duration buy the scale and value of the duration. By default the
                        scale is in pulses and the value is the mage's PSI. .</para>


                    <table>
                        <title>SDP Duration Time Scale</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Duration Time Scale </entry>
                                    <entry> SDP </entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>


                                <row>
                                    <entry> Instantaneous </entry>
                                    <entry> 0 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Pulse </entry>
                                    <entry> -1 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Second </entry>
                                    <entry> -2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 5 Seconds </entry>
                                    <entry> -3 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1/2 Min </entry>
                                    <entry> -4 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 2 Minutes </entry>
                                    <entry> -6 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 10 Minutes </entry>
                                    <entry> -8 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Hour </entry>
                                    <entry> -12 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 4 Hours </entry>
                                    <entry> -16 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Day </entry>
                                    <entry> -20 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> 1 Week </entry>
                                    <entry> -24 </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>

                </sect2>

                <sect2>
                    <title>AOE. </title>
                    <table>
                        <title>Cost of Area of Effect in SDP</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Scale of AOE</entry>
                                    <entry>Cost in SDP</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>0 </entry>
                                    <entry>0 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>1 Meter </entry>
                                    <entry>2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>2 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry>4 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>5 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry>8 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>10 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry>16 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>20 Meters </entry>
                                    <entry>32 </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>

            <sect1>
                <title>Basic Rules of Spell Design</title>
                <para/>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>One or more energy types must be used in the spell.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To bring energy into use the caster must Summon, Create, Concentrate
                            or have the energy otherwise available.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To bring the power into use the caster do one of the following:
                            Translocate it, Transport it, Bind it and physically move it, or Hold it
                            and physically move it.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Spells designed to inflict damage on a target must use the Damage
                            action.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Bindings are only needed when the energy needs to be anchored to an
                            object or place.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Spells that use Influence, Control, Damage and Restoration must have a
                            target.</para>
                    </listitem>





                </itemizedlist>
                <para>A spell is designed by starting with 25 + Mages MST in SDP. All spell
                    statistics are 0. CDF = 0, Resistance = 0; DUR = 0; RNG = 0; QE = 0; EC =
                    0.</para>
                <para>A {\it Laser} spell is designed as follows.</para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>We start with the Base spell type. </member>
                    <member> We choose the Energy Type of Light. </member>
                    <member> The first action needed is the Summoning of the Light. </member>
                    <member> The next action is to transport the Light to the target.</member>
                    <member> After transporting the Light, we must apply it to the target in order </member>
                    <member> to damage it.</member>
                </simplelist>
                <para>Now let us design another spell. We will design a {\it Lightnings Hand} spell.
                    We specify multiple targets. \section{Other Notes that are of interest}
                    Investment Rituals are specific to the energy being used. Normally, invested
                    items can resist. With sufficient preparation the resistance can be dropped to
                    0. Warding rituals are similiar. \section{Spell Design Tables} \tiny </para>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP:Energy Types</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Energy Type </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                                <entry> Speed </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Power </entry>
                                <entry> -7 </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Belief </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                                <entry> 7 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Stream </entry>
                                <entry> -2 </entry>
                                <entry> 5 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Fabric </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 6 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Light </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Dark </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Life </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Death </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Fire </entry>
                                <entry> -5 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Water </entry>
                                <entry> -5 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Air </entry>
                                <entry> -5 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Earth </entry>
                                <entry> -5 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Shadow </entry>
                                <entry> -6 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Starlight </entry>
                                <entry> -6 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Nature </entry>
                                <entry> -6 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Decay </entry>
                                <entry> -6 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Telekinetics </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Phanokinetics </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Temporokinetics </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Energetics </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Biokinetics </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP: Actions</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Action Type </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                                <entry> Speed </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>


                            <row>
                                <entry> Det/Conceal </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Div/A-Div </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Summon/Banish </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Create/Destroy </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 10 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Conc/Dissapate </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Transport/A-Tra </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Bind/Release </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 7 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Trans/Stasis </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 8 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Translocate </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 9 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Hold </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Activate </entry>
                                <entry> -2 </entry>
                                <entry> 5 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Fast Activate </entry>
                                <entry> -3 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry> Influence </entry>
                                <entry> -2 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Control </entry>
                                <entry> -3 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Damage </entry>
                                <entry> -3 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Restore </entry>
                                <entry> -2 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP:Casting Component Type</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Casting Component </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Verbal </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Somatic </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Material </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Preparation </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Runes </entry>
                                <entry> 6 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> True Name </entry>
                                <entry> 8 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Requires to-hit roll </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Energy Held for duration </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP:Casting Component Properties</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Component Properties </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>

                            <row>
                                <entry> Cheap </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Moderate </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Expensive </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Common </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Uncommon </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Rare </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Renewable </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Non-Renewable </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Reusable </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Non-Reusable </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Simple </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Moderate Complex </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Complex </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Quiet </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Normal Speech Level </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Loud </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Short </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Same Length as Spell </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Long </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP:Target Types</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Factor Name </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> No Target </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Directed,Self </entry>
                                <entry> -2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Single Target </entry>
                                <entry> -4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Multiple Targets </entry>
                                <entry> -8 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Spells </entry>
                                <entry> -10 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Area of Effect </entry>
                                <entry> -16 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>SDP Target Components</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Target Component </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>


                            <row>
                                <entry> Matter(Inanimate) </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Body(Animate) </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Mana(Inanimate) </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Lifeforce(Animate) </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Thought </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Perception </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Essence(Soul) </entry>
                                <entry> -1 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>Costs for Misc. Factor Changes</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Factor </entry>
                                <entry> SDP </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>


                            <row>
                                <entry> Rank linked QE </entry>
                                <entry> 5/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Rank linked AOE </entry>
                                <entry> 5/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Rank Linked RES </entry>
                                <entry> 4/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Rank Linked DUR </entry>
                                <entry> 3/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Rank Linked RNG </entry>
                                <entry> 3/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>Costs for Factor Changes</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry> Factor Manipulation </entry>
                                <entry> Factor/SDP Ratio </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>


                            <row>
                                <entry> AOE </entry>
                                <entry> 1/2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> CDF </entry>
                                <entry> 1/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> RES </entry>
                                <entry> 2/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> QE </entry>
                                <entry> 2/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> DUR </entry>
                                <entry> 1/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> RNG </entry>
                                <entry> 1/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry> EC </entry>
                                <entry> 3/1 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
    </part>

    <part>
        <title>Word</title>
        <subtitle><quote>...</quote></subtitle>
        <chapter>
            <title>Deity</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Demi-deity</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Tor</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Ur-vile</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of Occult.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Demondim</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of Occult.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Nator</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of Occult.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Monk of the Word</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Dragon</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Namer</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Avatar</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Oracle</title>
            <subtitle>.AKA Spaewife..</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Priest/Priestess</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Paladin</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of spirit as a call for balance.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Vampyr</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of spirit .</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
        <chapter>
            <title>Dhampyr</title>
            <subtitle>...</subtitle>
            <sect1>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para>..Partakes of spirit .</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Constraints</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Benefits</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Typical Castings</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Opinions of others ..</title>
                <para>...</para>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>




    </part>
</book>
