<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Book of the MerovanX</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>Jim Mochel</orgname>
            <address>
                <city>Bellingham, MA</city>
                <street>7 Walter Morse Rd</street>
                <postcode>02019</postcode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <email>jmochel@saltations.org</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <subtitle>A Darker, Rougher Camelot</subtitle>
        <para>Merova presents a picture of Norman Knights and Men at Arms (Chain, Plate and Leather, Long Swords and Bastard Swords, Spears and Pole Arms, 
            and Cross bows rather then Self Bows). The Merovan language is mixture of the original language with a growing collection of loan word from
            the Native Borne language. 
            The absolute core of Merova is Meara Bay and the King's lands around it. Surrounding the Kingsland  is a set of 39+ Ducal fiefdoms. 
            On the outskirts of all the Ducal fiefdoms are the Marches which act as a buffer to the outside world.            
            The Dukes have the population and the wealth while the Marches have the arms and the pride. 
            Their only real common ground is the king. The king is from a small neglected branch of one of the Ducal families (Almost Native is the phrase....). 
        </para>
        <para>Merova lies on the northeastern edge of the continent. Merovans are built like the Norman French with many
            brunettes and ash blondes. Merova is the King Arthur’s court of the world. Merova looks like the traditional 
            fantasy version of feudal society composed of Knights, Nobles and Ladies. Is a single kingdom with 39 strong 
            dukes newly united under one king. It has high wizards and sorcerers as well as priests and priestesses. 
            If you want to play a traditional men at arms or a knight, this is the culture to be from. Women’s roles are more limited,
            with only priestesses easily being able to travel and adventure. Typical Merovan characters would be Knights or men at arms. 
            Priests or priestesses. Thieves. Wizards and sorcerers of various types.</para>
        <para audience="cultural-outsider">Merova has an established relationship of trade with the Hairochan. In addition, they have a strong ruling tradition over the.
            existing Native Borne population who act as the serf populkation of the Dukedoms and Marches.</para>
        <note audience="cultural-insider" >
            <para>It is not obvious tro outsiders that Merovan culture involves a strangely strong, and sometimes uneasy, 
                relationship between three cultures: Merovans, the Hairochan, and the Native Borne. The Merovan "settled" know that the Hairochan are more 
                than they seem but try 
                not to talk about it. And all of the settled know that while the Native Borne negotiated the role of servant for themselves
                it might be catastrophically dangerous to push them. They all have the feel of that gypsy wise woman that you don't want to transgress against. 
            </para>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment">
        <title>Physical Environment</title>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-geography">
            <title>Geography</title>
            <para>The geography is filled with rugged hills and valleys.
                It is bounded on the western boundary by a sheer mountain range with a few passes through to the vallys to the west.
                There are morraines, high ridges formed from glacial debris especially in the northernn areas of Merova. The southern islands expecially
                are composed of that kind of morraines. Many of those morraines have ridges cut out by meltwater streams often 
                framed by large boulders at the base.  There is a significant number of valleys filled with rivers, lakes and ponds.
                Glacial till (a mix of sand, clay, gravel, and rocks) left behind poor, rocky soil in much of the region, though river valleys often 
                have fertile floodplains.
            </para>
            <para>The southern and eastern border are edged in rocky coastline with peninsulas, islands, and estuaries. 
                Most of the coastline is edged in rock, not sand. 
                There are two large bays in the region, Meara Harbor, and Badger Bay (Narragensat).
                Merova is easily accessed via small boats throughout the coast.</para>
            <para>There are a set of<link linkend="glossentry-torgan-road">Torgan roads</link> running east to west and north to south. The largest, the
                <emphasis>King's Road</emphasis> is a 16m wide road that runs from Meara Harbor in the east to the Great Doors in the westward pass. 
                It has 1-2m high walls on each edge. Periodically there 
                are <link linkend="glossentry-torgan-road-trivium">Trivia</link>.
            The roads enable a very high rate of individual and cargo travel.</para>
            <para>
                On the far western edge of Merova lies the Western Wall <indexterm><primary>Western Wall</primary><secondary>West Shelf</secondary></indexterm>, a sheer mountain range which has very few passes that are usable.
                The most commonly used pass is the the Great Gate <indexterm><primary>Great Gate</primary></indexterm>which is guarded by and managed by the Uru, who charge tolls for passage,        
            </para>
         </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-climate">
            <title>Climate</title>
            <para>The climate is characterized by four distinct seasons, 
                including cold winters, warm summers, and moderate precipitation 
                throughout the year. The region’s climate is influenced by its 
                latitude, proximity to the Ocean, and varying topography.
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Winter</title>
                <para>
                    Winters are cold and dry inland but moderated along the coast by the Ocean.
                    Averages range from 10°F to 30°F (-12°C to -1°C) in the 
                    north and 20°F to 40°F (-6°C to 4°C) in southern coastal areas.
                    Subzero temperatures are common in the northern regions, especially at night.
                    Heavy snowfalls are typical, with annual snow accumulations of 60–100 inches (1.5–2.5 meters) in the northern and mountainous areas.
                    Coastal areas receive less snow but can experience intense nor’easters (winter storms bringing snow, wind, and coastal flooding).
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Spring</title>
                <para>Gradual warming, with highs ranging from 40°F (4°C) in March to 70°F (21°C) in May. Rainfall increases, and melting snow can lead to flooding in some areas.
                    Spring is often unpredictable, with a mix of snow, rain, and warm, sunny days. Budding trees and blooming flowers mark the season.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Summer</title>
                <para> (June to August). Daytime highs average 75°F to 85°F (24°C to 29°C) across the region, with 
                    cooler temperatures in the mountains and along the coast.
                    Heatwaves can push temperatures above 90°F (32°C), especially inland.
                    Summers are humid, especially in southern Merova.
                    Frequent thunderstorms, particularly in the late afternoon and evening.
                    Summers are warm and humid, with plenty of sunny days for outdoor activities.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Autumn</title>
                <para>(September to November).
                    Crisp, cool weather with clear skies makes autumn one of the most popular seasons in Merova
                    Cooling from 70°F (21°C) in September to 40°F (4°C) by November.
                    Has vibrant fall foliage, with trees displaying brilliant shades of red, orange, and yellow. 
                </para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-resources">
            <title>Resources</title>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Rivers and Streams</title>
                <para>Abundant rivers are used for transportation, trade, and as sources of fresh water.
                    Fast-flowing rivers power water mills for grinding grain and sawing lumber.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Coastal Waters</title>
                <para>The ocean provides opportunities for near shore fishing, some deep sea fishing, and trade.
                    Bays and harbors, like Meara Harbor, supported shipbuilding and commercial activity.
                    Merova's waters, particularly the Grand Banks, are rich in cod, which are a cornerstone of the economy.
                    Lobsters, clams, and oysters are also significant food and trade sources. In addition, the more shallow waters 
                    are used to form fish weyrs to farm fish and some shellfish in.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Soil and Agriculture</title>
                <para>The soil is rocky and less fertile compared to the southern polities, making large-scale farming difficult. 
                    It typically takes around 3-7 acres of land to feed a family, with most farms ranging between 50 and 100 acres, 
                    as the rocky soil and harsh climate limits the amount of crops that can be grown, requiring families to focus on 
                    subsistence farming to feed themselves directly. 
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Granite and Slate</title>
                <para>Abundant Granite quaries. Granite is used for building foundations, mills, and gravestones.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Metals</title>
                <para>Iron Ore found in bogs and streams, iron is smelted for tools, nails, and household items. There are also large deposits of
                    Lead, Copper, Tin, and Antimony, Coal, Zinc 
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Precious metals and gems</title>
                <para>There are large silver deposits with smaller gold and mercury ore fields. Merova is blessed with multiple, 
                    easily accessible gem Tourmaline, Spinel,Sapphires and Rubies,Zircon rose quartz, garnets, beryl, amethyst, 
                    rhodonite and garnets,quartz crystals, beryl, lepidolite
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Talc and Asbestos</title>
                <para>
                    Asbestos is known for its fire resistance and durability and it is used
                    for rudimentary fireproof cloth and insulation for indoor ovens and stoves.
                    In a few situatins it is used for Wicks in tepls. Talc in Colonial America
                    Talc is a soft mineral that is used for its smooth texture and absorbent properties.
                    It is used for personal hygiene powders – Finely ground talc is used as a body 
                    powder to reduce moisture and friction under heavy robes or armour.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-flora-wild-trees">
            <title>Wild Trees</title>
            <para>Merova is heavily forested, with a mix of old growth conifers and deciduous trees.
                The types of trees vary based on the region's soil, climate, and elevation. 
                Below are some of the most common trees found in Merova.</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>White Pine</title>
                <para>A tall, straight tree growing up to 200 feet, with soft, lightweight wood. 
                    Highly valued for ship masts as well as  Timber for construction, furniture, and export.
                    Resin used for making pitch and tar.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Spruce</title>
                <para>                
                    Medium-sized evergreen trees with dense, needle-like foliage.
                    Timber for building and ship planking.
                    Resin for pitch and tar.
                    Native Borne Spruce beer made from its needles
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Hemlock</title>
                <para>A shade-tolerant evergreen tree with soft needles and scaly bark.
                    Bark used for tanning leather (high tannin content).
                    Wood for framing and fuel</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Fir</title>
                <para>A fragrant evergreen with short, soft needles.
                    Firewood and basic construction.
                    Resin used for medicinal purposes and sealing.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Oak</title>
                <para> A strong, durable hardwood tree with many species, such as white oak and red oak.
                    Shipbuilding (hulls, keels, and frames).
                    Furniture, tools, barrels (cooperage), and construction.
                    Firewood, as it burns long and hot.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Maple</title>
                <para>A medium-sized tree known for its striking autumn foliage and sweet sap.
                    Sap for making maple syrup and sugar.
                    Wood for furniture, tools, and flooring.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Birch</title>
                <para>A fast-growing hardwood tree with white, yellow, or gray bark.
                    Wood for furniture, tools, and firewood.
                    Bark used by Native Americans for canoes and containers.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Beech</title>
                <para>A large, smooth-barked hardwood tree.
                    Durable wood for furniture and tools.
                    Nuts provided food for wildlife and humans.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Chestnut</title>
                <para>A tall hardwood tree producing edible nuts.
                    Timber for building, as it was resistant to rot.
                    Nuts were a significant food source for colonists and livestock.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Elm</title>
                <para>
                    A tall, graceful tree with a spreading canopy.
                    Wood for wheel hubs, furniture, and construction.
                    Popular for shade and ornamental purposes in colonial towns.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Ash</title>
                <para>A tall, straight tree with strong, flexible wood.
                    Handles for tools, baseball bats, and other items requiring durability.
                    Construction and firewood.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Hickory</title>
                <para>Valued for its strong wood and as fuel for high-heat fires.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Willow</title>
                <para>Found along rivers and wetlands, used for baskets and medicinal purposes.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Poplar</title>
                <para> Used for light construction and firewood</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Black Walnut</title>
                <para>They are found primarily in southernMerova, though less commonly in the northern parts of the region due to colder temperatures.
                    Produces edible nuts enclosed in a green husk. Eaten by colonists and used as a food source,
                    though extracting the meat from the tough shells was labor-intensive. Highly prized for its rich, dark color, black walnut wood was used for furniture, cabinetry, and gunstocks.
                    The husks of the nuts were used to produce a dark brown dye.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Butternut (White Walnut)</title>
                <para>More common than black walnut in northern parts of Merova, as it is better adapted to colder climates.
                    Wood: Used for furniture, paneling, and small crafts, though it was softer and less durable than black walnut.
                    Nuts: Butternut nuts were sweeter and easier to process than black walnuts, making them a popular food source.
                    Dye: The husks were used to create a yellowish-brown dye.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>
                    Pine, Hemlock, Tamarack, Spruce,
                    Cedar, Juniper, Fir, Sycamore,
                    Witchhazel,Locust,
                    Paper Birch,
                    River Birch,
                    Smooth Alder,
                    Hophornbeam,
                    Green Alder,Hazelnut ,
                    Beech ,
                    Black Oak , 
                    Pin Oak ,White Oak, 
                    Chestnut, Cottonwood, Weeping willow , Red Mulberry ,
                    Black Cherry, 
                    Shadbush,
                    Mountain Ash,
                    Slippery Elm ,
                    Basswood,
                    Smooth Sumac,
                    Red Maple,
                    Horse-Chestnut,
                    Staghorn Sumac,
                    Silver Maple,
                    Sugar Maple,
                    Boxelder,
                    Black Tupelo,
                    Flowering Dogwood,
                    Northern Catalpa,
                    Black Ash,
                    Walkingstick,
                    Downy Hawthorn
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-flora-cultivated-trees">
            <title>Cultivated Trees</title>
            <para>...</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Apple</title>
                <para>
                    Apples were grown for eating, cooking, and fermenting into cider (a staple beverage).
                    Seeds and saplings were brought by Merova settlers and quickly became a staple of agriculture.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Pear</title>
                <para>Cultivated for eating and cooking, as well as cider. though less popular than apples.
                    Hardy and adaptable to Merova's climate</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Cherry</title>
                <para> Valued for their fruit and ornamental appeal.Sweet cherries and sour cherries were both introduced by Merovan settlers
                </para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-flora-wild-plants">
            <title>Wild Plants</title>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Elderberries</title>
                <para>Found along rivers and wetlands </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Wild Plums</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Wild Grapes</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Nanny Berry</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Ground Nuts</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Hazelnuts</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Chestnuts</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Acorns</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Sage</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Yarrow</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Brabeans</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Squash</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Pumpkins</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Corn</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Potatoes</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-flora-cultivated-plants">
            <title>Cultivated Plants</title>
            <para>...</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Barley</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Oats</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Rye</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Wheat</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Cabbage</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Asparagus AKA Spear Greens</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-wild-fauna">
            <title>Wild Fauna</title>
            <para>...</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Fisher Cats</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Beaver</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Catamount</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Black Bear</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Rattlesnake</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Deer</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Moose</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-cultivated-fauna">
            <title>Cultivated Fauna</title>
            <section>
                <title>Dogs</title>
                 <formalpara>
                     <title>Alaunts</title>
                     <para>A hunting dog breed that is expensive to buy and maintain. A sight hunter
                        used as a large game catch dog, as a war and guard dog. <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="reference/merova/alaunt-gentil.jpg"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></para>
                 </formalpara>
                 <formalpara>
                     <title>Mastiffs</title>
                     <para>A hunting dog breed that is expensive to buy and maintain but excels as a
                        trainable guard and war dog. Height: Males 62–70 cm; Females 58–66 cm.
                        Weight: Males 45–50 kg (100–110 lb) Females 40–45 kg (90–100 lb)  <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="reference/merova/merovan-mastiff.jpeg"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                    </para>
                 </formalpara>
                 <formalpara>
                     <title>Wulfhund</title>
                     <para>Large sight hound used to hunt dangerous game. Very popular in the
                        Marches. Height ranges from 79 cm to 86 cm for males. From 71 cm to 86 cm
                        per females. Weight ranges from 40 to 50 kg for females and 54 to 75 kg for
                        males. Lifespan is from 5 to 12 years. <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="reference/merova/wulfhund.jpg"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject></para>
                 </formalpara>
                 <formalpara>
                     <title>Diggers</title>
                     <para>Also called Creuseurs. Small scent hound (About Beagle size) used to hunt rodents and burrowing creatures.
                         It it's height varies from 33 to 42 cm. Weight ranges from 9 to 11 kg for the females and 10 to 14 kg for the males.
                         Average lifespan is about 12 years.
                     </para>
                 </formalpara>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Horses</title>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Merova Cob</title>
                    <para>Typically used as war horses (though sometime as draft houses),  
                        Cobs are generally gray or black in coloring with white verigation. 
                        The head has a straight profile, broad forehead, large eyes and long thin ears. T
                        he chest is deep and wide and the croup long and level. The legs are heavily muscled,
                        and the lower legs generally have heavy white feathering. 
                        Enthusiasts describe the temperament as alert, and members of the breed are considered 
                        intelligent, willing workers with good dispositions, 
                        and easy keepers.
                        <table  xml:id="tbl-merova-cob-attributes" frame='all'>
                            <title>Cob</title>
                            <tgroup cols="3">
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="attribute-col" />
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="male-attr" />   
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="female-attr" />   
                                <thead>
                                    <row>
                                        <?dbfo bgcolor="aqua" ?>
                                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                                        <entry>Stallion</entry>
                                        <entry>Mare</entry>
                                    </row>
                                </thead>
                                <tbody>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Height</entry>
                                        <entry>18-21 hands (182-213 cm)</entry>
                                        <entry>16.5-19 hands (168-193 cm)</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Weight</entry>
                                        <entry>540-1270 kg</entry>
                                        <entry>417-950 kg</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Walking Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">3-8 kph, 7 hrs, 21-56 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Trotting Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">13 – 19 kph, 2 hrs, 26-38 km </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Canter Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">10-17 kph, hrs , 6 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Gallop Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">30-45 kph, 3 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Average Lifespan</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">25 to 30 years</entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Merova Trotter</title>
                    <para>Primarily used as a riding and harness horse is  usually brown to dark brown in color.
                        It has a very high endurance and are able to travel up to 75 km per day,
                     usually outstripping the endurance of their riders.      
                        <table  xml:id="tbl-merova-trotter-attributes" frame='all'>
                            <title>Trotter</title>
                            <tgroup cols="3">
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="attribute-col" />
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="male-attr" />   
                                <colspec align="left"  colname="female-attr" />   
                                <thead>
                                    <row>
                                        <?dbfo bgcolor="aqua" ?>
                                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                                        <entry>Stallion</entry>
                                        <entry>Mare</entry>
                                    </row>
                                </thead>
                                <tbody>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Height</entry>
                                        <entry>15 to 17 hands (152-172 cm)</entry>
                                        <entry>15 to 16.5 hands (152-168 cm)</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Weight</entry>
                                        <entry>540 to 1,270 kg</entry>
                                        <entry>500-1200 kg</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Walking Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">3-6 kph, 9 hrs, 27-54 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Trotting Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">14–21 kph, 3 hrs, 42-63 km </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Canter Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">17-25 kph, 6 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Gallop Speed and Range</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">33-48 kph, 3 km</entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry>Average Lifespan</entry>
                                        <entry namest="male-attr" nameend="female-attr">25 to 30 years</entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Livestock</title>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Cattle</title>
                    <para>Several breeds brough by Merova settlers.Used for meat, and farmers trained oxen to pull heavier loads.</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Pigs</title>
                    <para>Several breeds brough by Merova settlers.</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Sheep</title>
                    <para>Several breeds brough by Merova settlers.</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Chickens</title>
                    <para> Raised in coops</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Ducks</title>
                    <para> Raised in fenced-in yards</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Otters</title>
                    <para>Tamed by settlers after they arrived in Merova</para>
                </formalpara>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Beavers</title>
                    <para>Tamed by settlers after they arrived in Merova</para>
                </formalpara>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-physical-environment-esoterica">
            <title>Esoterica</title>
            <para>Merova is a region filled with esoteric energies especially mana, spirit and the divine </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Ley Lines</title>
                <para>
                It is common knowledge that Merova has several large ley lines of great strength .      
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Eruptions</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Still Pools</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-history">
        <title>Merovan History</title>
        <para>A culture’s history, including colonization, wars, migrations, and revolutions, impacts its identity and traditions..</para>
        <para>...</para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-history-prehistory">
            <title>Merovan Pre History</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-history-meme">
            <title>Merovan Historical Memes</title>
            <para>...</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-history-zzz3">
            <title>Merovan ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-history-zzz4">
            <title>Merovan ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-external-influences">
        <title>External Influences</title>
        <para>...</para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-external-influences-zzz1">
            <title>Other Cultures</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-external-influences-zzz2">
            <title>Economic</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-external-influences-zzz3">
            <title>Other Religions</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-external-influences-zzz4">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-beliefs-and-values">
        <title>Merovan Beliefs and Values</title>
        <para>...</para>
        <section>
            <title>Memes</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-language-and-communication">
        <title>Language and Communication</title>
        <para>The primary means of communication, including spoken and written languages, dialects, and non-verbal cues (gestures, body language, etc.).
            Language often reflects cultural priorities (e.g., Inuit languages have multiple words for snow).</para>
        <para>...</para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-language-and-communication-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors">
        <title>Merovan Social Norms and Behaviors</title>
        <para>The social mores and unwritten rules that govern acceptable behavior in a society.
            Examples: Greetings, table manners, dress codes, and etiquette.</para>
        <para>...</para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-general-social-traditions">
            <title>General Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-general-rituals">
            <title>General Social Rituals</title>
            <para>...</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-social-traditions">
            <title>Childbirth Social Traditions</title>
            <para>...</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-rituals">
            <title>Childbirth Rituals</title>
            <para>
            ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-expectations">
            <title>Childbirth Expectations</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Childbirth Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-social-traditions">
            <title>Childhood Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-rituals">
            <title>Childhood Rituals</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-expectations">
            <title>Childhood Expectations</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-value-of-learning">
            <title>Value of Education</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-why">
            <title>Why?</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Childhood Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-social-traditions">
            <title>Young Adult Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-rituals">
            <title>Young Adult Rituals</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Young Adult Expectations of Work</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Young Adult Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Young Adult Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Young Adult Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-social-traditions">
            <title>Adulthood Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-rituals">
            <title>Adulthood Rituals</title>
            <para>
                ...
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Adulthood Expectations of Work</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>


                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the full adult expected to innovate, to teach his craft, to explore new ideas?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Conversely, is his role to prevent innovation, to guard tradition, to maintain an unbroken line from past history to the future?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does gender, race, or social status change the expectations with which the culture views the full adult and his work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is open to the full adult that is not open to young adults or children?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is closed to the full adult that is available to children or young adults?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the full adult in your culture regard future career advancements?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to change jobs?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to choose different work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to pursue dreams?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Adulthood Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>


                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will the full adult of your culture find or keep a mate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he or she replace an unsatisfactory mate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he deal with a mate lost to desertion or death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he deal with sexuality if single?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the culture press the full adult to continue adding to family, to expand numbers of wives or concubines, to support the households of his young adult children and their families?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Must the full adult gather dowries?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the full adult permitted sexual experimentation of any sort, or is that something that must be put aside?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens to those adults who stray outside of the permissible modes of sexual expression?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Punishment, shunning, banishment, execution?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Adulthood Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-social-traditions">
            <title>Old Age Social Traditions</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-rituals">
            <title>Old Age Rituals</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Old Age Expectations of Work</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Old Age Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Old Age Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture view the rebellion of the elderly?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it treat the rebellious elder? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the elder who wants to rebel do so and still survive the experience?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Cost of Aging</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does your culture fight to prolong life? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In which cases?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What place has it made for dying elders? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do families care for dying elders? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the community care for them? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does religion care for them? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does government care for them?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What respect does the culture show dying Elders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Old Age Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect elderly male in your culture will ....? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect elderly female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed elderly male in your culture will....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed elderly female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-social-traditions">
            <title>Death Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the culture treat the death of one of its members? Does it treat the deathdifferently by age, by status, by gender, by singleness, or if the dead was paired, or familied?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does it treat the death differently when it occurs by different means–suicide or murder,disease or illness, when caused by congenital problems, accident or old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the family deal with the death of a member, and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the community deal with death and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does religion deal with death and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does government deal with death andthose bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-rituals">
            <title>Death Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals do the family and/or friends perform or require for the dead?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does the community perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does religion perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does the government perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-expectations">
            <title>Death Expectations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the culture as a whole view the future of the dead person?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does that future vary related to the life the person lived?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does that future vary related to the person’s status, or gender, or age at death, or religious or government affiliation?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Death Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Razors</emphasis>Razors
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>So with that in mind, how does your culture define a success in death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it define a failure in death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What variables in religion, age, status, gender and so on will change whether the deceased dies a success or a failure?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization">
        <title>Merovan Social Organization</title>
        <para>How a culture structures relationships and roles in society.
            Includes family dynamics, gender roles, class systems, and community hierarchies</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the rules? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who made the rules?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does society get its rules?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is justice dispensed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are criminals apprehended?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What punishments are used?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are the rulers?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How has the presence of magic and magicians affected law and
                        government?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are wizards barred from certain kinds of government jobs or
                        offices?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do some government jobs require that their holder be a wizard?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What forms are used in neighboring countries, and why are they the same or
                        different?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What services does the government or head of state provide: schools, wells,
                        courts, an army to protect people from the Vikings?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What services are provided locally or privately?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who has the right to levy taxes?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For what?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On what or whom?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Can taxes be paid in kind, or do certain things require money?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who provides support services for the head of state?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are they called: King’s Counselors, Cabinet Ministers, Secretary of
                        State, Good Ol’ Girls?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they hereditary offices, civil servants, appointees, military,
                        elected?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is the relative power of a country or ruler usually measured by the size of
                        its army, the number and ability of its wizards, or the amount of money/trade
                        flowing through it?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is considered a citizen, with the rights and privileges
                        thereof?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are those rights and privileges (voting, protection from thieves, the
                        right to a hearing in Rome) and what responsibilities go along with them (jury
                        duty, providing funds or knights for the lord’s army?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there certain classes of people (wizards, foreigners, children,
                        peasants, women) who have fewer legal rights or less recourse than full
                        citizens?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they considered mentally or morally deficient, a danger to the state, or
                        is there some other rationale?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the easiest/most common ways to advance in status — amass more
                        money, marry well, get the ruler’s eye, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much resistance is there to someone advancing in social status?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who will take over running the government if the current head of state is
                        incapacitated?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is this determined?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there an heir apparent (either actual or political)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What happens if the heir is a minor?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who gives orders?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are they picked?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is responsible for protecting the head of state?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>His personal guard, the Secret Service, an elite group affiliated with the
                        regular military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What safeguards have they got against assassins, poisoning, direct assault,
                        magical attack?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who can give orders (to military, to tax collectors, to servants, to
                        ordinary folks on the street)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are such people chosen?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is responsible for coinage: the ruler, local barons, someone else
                        (merchant guilds)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there generally acceptable standards?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How easy/common is counterfeiting?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there an organized system of education?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If so, who provides it: government, churches, private persons?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is it supported?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who can call up men for an army, and how?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the ruler ask the nobility for men, who in turn draft their peasants,
                        or can the ruler go straight to the bottom?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much formal spying and intelligence gathering is normally done by
                        governments?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Merchant guilds and wealthy tradesmen?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there actual organizations, or is spying done by diplomats and/or
                        freelance agents?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How effective is it currently?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do relations between countries depend mainly on the relations between the
                        heads of state, or can two rulers hate each other’s guts without being able to
                        just declare war and drag their countries into it?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there times when people are expected to fast, or feast (e.g., before
                        solstice, after the birth of a child, during Lent or Ramadan, after the death of
                        a ruler, etc.)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there occasions when the ruler is expected to provide a celebration or
                        spectacle for the people to enjoy, (e.g., the Roman gladiatorial
                        games)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much influence do “special interest groups” such as merchants, wizards,
                        or various religions, have on court politics?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they exercise their influence — indirectly (by talking nobility or
                        council members into taking their sides) or directly (by bribery, coercion,
                        having their own representatives on the council)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there any shaky political alliances between disparate groups?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why were they formed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How long is it likely to be before they fall apart?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When they do, what will the effects be?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What ancient rivalries and hatreds still affect current attitudes and
                        political positions (examples: Scottish and Welsh separatist groups; Catholics
                        vs. Protestants vs. Muslims; dwarves vs. elves; Hatfields vs. McCoys)?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-power">
            <title>Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the source of power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What groups have power and who are the players?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What groups have the most political power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-government-type">
            <title>Type of Government</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the basic style of government: feudal, aristocratic, oligarchy,
                        absolute ruler, democracy, what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who are the rulers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are the rulers chosen?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is power passed on to the next leaders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the basic style of rule</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who will take over running the moeity if the current ruler is incapacitated?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is this determined?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is there an heir apparent (either actual or political)?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens if the heir is a minor?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who gives orders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are they picked?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who is responsible for protecting the ruler?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What safeguards have they got against assassins, poisoning, direct assault, magical attack?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What impact on the above does Magic or Magic Users have?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                THE GREAT COMPACT
            </para>
            <para>
                Merovan feudalism is a hierarchical system of governance, landholding, and social organization. 
                Merova is rooted in mutual obligations and relationships between different social classes, 
                with the king at the top flowing downward through the Dukes and the Marches down to the lower vassals.
                Here's a breakdown of its structure and key features.
            </para>
            <para>
                The King is at the apex of the system. The king holds all the land in the realm and distributes it to loyal followers (nobles) to hold in exchange for their service.
                The king provides overall governance, protection, and the right to occupy and farm the land through his nobles. He is the ultimate authority and arbiter.
                The current king is Kelwyn Derian Lusignan
            </para>
            <para>
                The Vassals Principal (Dukes and Marches). These are the most powerful nobles who hold the land directly 
                from the king, known as "Demesne" <footnote><para>Day-Meen</para></footnote>. The Vassals Principal are obligated to the King to  
                provide military service of Knights and Men-at-Arms. Participate in the king’s court and provide counsel.
                The Vassals Principal  act as local arms and voices of the King over their territories, administering justice and overseeing the land.
            </para>
            <para>
                The Magie Principal (Grand Magicien and Grand Sorcier). These are the most powerful nobles who hold the land directly 
                from the king, known as "demesne" <footnote><para>Day-Meen</para></footnote>. The Vassals Principal are obligated to the King to  
                provide military service of Knights and Men-at-Arms. Participate in the king’s court and provide counsel.
                The Vassals Principal  act as local arms and voices of the King over their territories, administering justice and overseeing the land.
            </para>
            <para>
                Vassal Armes (Knights and Sergent Principal)
                The Vassals Principal hold their land divided their land among loyal vassals in exchange for further military service. Knights who owe mounted service of 
                themselves and some men-at-arms. Sargeants Main who owe training service (Kinghts and men-at-arms)
                Obligations to the Vassals Principal:
                Serve as warriors for their lords in times of conflict.
                Provide loyalty and support in governance and administration.
                Privileges: In return, knights and nobles received protection and income from the land they managed (often through the labor of peasants).
            </para>
            <para>
                Vassal Magie (Magicien and Sorcier)
                The Magie Principal hold their ..TBD.. 
            </para>
            <para>
                The merchants and such owe their serviuces via..TBD.. 
            </para>
            <para>
                a. Land as the Basis of Power
                All land technically belonged to the king, who distributed it in exchange for services.
                Land was divided into manors, each controlled by a lord who governed the local population.
                b. Mutual Obligations
                Feudalism was built on the principle of reciprocity: Lords provided land, protection, and justice, while vassals and peasants provided labor, military service, or loyalty.
                c. Castles and Military Control
                Norman feudal lords constructed castles to assert their dominance over the land, maintain military power, and protect against rebellion or invasion.
                Castles also served as administrative centers for the local area.
                d. Feudal Justice
                Lords exercised judicial authority within their domains, holding courts to resolve disputes, enforce laws, and collect fines.
                e. Hereditary Nature
                Titles and land were usually passed down through inheritance, solidifying the power of noble families over generations.
            </para>
            <para>The Great Compact.. with the Hairochan</para>
            <para>The Land Compact.. with the Native Borne</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Dukes of Merova</title>
                    <listitem><para>Amis . Quincy</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Amond. Lynn</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Beauchamp . Salem</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Beaufort . Gloucester</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Beaumont . Northhampton</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Boudreaux . Pittsfield</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Challis. Springfield</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Champlain. Lawrence</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Chauncey. Newburyport</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Courtenay. Haverhill</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>D'Arcy. Amherst</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>D'Burgh. Leominster</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>D'Norris. Nashua NH</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Devereux. Manchester NH</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>D'Gascur . Brattleboro VT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>D'Quincey. N. Adams</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Duchene. Warwick</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Estelle Exeter, NH</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Fortescue. Providence</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Fortmayne. Worcester</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Freemantle. Framingham</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Gascoyne. Greenfield</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Gaston. Warwick</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Granville. Taunton</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Harcourt. Newport</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Keynes. Hartford CT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Lavigne. New Haven, CT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Levere. Westerley RI</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Mallory. Portsmouth NH</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Mandeville. Keene NH</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Mayeux. New London CT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Moran. Vineyard</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Rochelle. Pawtucket</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Sant Clair. Fall River</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Sant John. Waterbury</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Sant Leger. Norwich CT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Sudamore. Newton</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Taillefer. Middleton CT</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Vasey. Billerica</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Vavasour. Revere</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>The Marches of Merova</title>
                    <listitem><para>Golden Badger . Aka or blaireau</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Blood Hawk. Aka faucon de sang</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>White Horse. Aka cheval blanc</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Red Stallion. Aka rouge Etalon</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Stone Dagger. Aka Pierre Dague</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Wolverine . Aka carcajou</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Death Wolf . Aka mort loup</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Demon Boar . Aka Sanglier démon</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Cat of the Mountain . Aka Chat de la montagne</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Shadow Eyes . Aka Yeux ombre</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Silver Spear . Aka Argent Lance</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Fox . Aka renard</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Mongoose . Aka mangouste</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Saber . Aka sabre</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Terror Cat . Aka chat terreur</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Giant Bear . Aka géant ours</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Sea Dragon . Aka dragon de mer</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>River Terror . Aka Terreur du fleuve</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-government-executive-power">
            <title>Executive Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who or what is the recognized head of your government?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>King, President, Council of Regents, Office of Bureaucratic Muckety-Mucks, High Priestess, Supreme Warchief, guy with the biggest stick, guy with the biggest brain?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the executive office a figurehead office, or one with real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your leader delegate power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To whom does your leader willingly listen and from whom does he willingly take advice? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To whom does your leader unwillingly listen, and from whom does he unwillingly take advice? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If your leader is a figurehead, who holds the real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How did that person or group get real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does he or the group hold it?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who opposes your leader? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How deep does the power of your head of government go?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is he responsible for the gathering and ordering of armies? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The making of laws? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The dispensing of justice to individuals? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can he go into individual homes and claim property or people? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is he above the law, or must he, too, obey it?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-legislative-power">
            <title>Legislative Power</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-judicial-power">
            <title>Judicial Power</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-surreptitious-power">
            <title>Surreptitious Power</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-social-organization-zzz3">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-clothing">
        <title>Merovan Clothing</title>
        <para/>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-clothing-birth">
            <title>Merovan</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-art-and-aesthetics">
        <title>Merovan Art and Aesthetics</title>
        <para>Forms of creative expression, including art, music, literature, dance, and architecture.
            Reflects the culture's sense of beauty, symbolism, and storytelling.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is the status of the arts (dance, music, theater, etc.) in this
                        society?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are artists revered or mistrusted?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they considered noble or immoral?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who supports the arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which arts are most highly valued and why?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there permanent theaters or concert halls for the performing
                        arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If so, who owns and runs them?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they profitable?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there also traveling troupes of players/musicians/dancers?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do their performances differ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Can magic be used in the arts, and if so, how — paint that glows,
                        pictures that move, flutes that play themselves, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do “normal” artists feel about this?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a separate branch of purely magical art, such as
                        illusion?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have paper-making and the printing press been invented, or are books and
                        scrolls rare, expensive, handwritten items?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things are considered appropriate subjects for representational
                        arts such as painting and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which are not?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>(Examples: some cultures/religions forbid the painting or sculpture of
                        the human figure, and have abstract art; some have limited painters to doing
                        only “uplifting” religious works, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there non-human races who tend to be naturally talented painters,
                        dancers, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this affect human practitioners of these arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are certain races/cultures considered better at some arts than other
                        races/cultures?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Where do the best dancers, painters, musicians, actors, etc. come
                        from?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have paper-making and the printing press been invented, or are books and
                        scrolls rare, expensive, handwritten items?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things are considered appropriate subjects for representational
                        arts such as painting and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which are not?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>(Examples: some cultures/religions forbid the painting or sculpture of
                        the human figure, and have abstract art; some have limited painters to doing
                        only “uplifting” religious works, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there non-human races who tend to be naturally talented painters,
                        dancers, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this affect human practitioners of these arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are certain races/cultures considered better at some arts than other
                        races/cultures?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Where do the best dancers, painters, musicians, actors, etc. come
                        from?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What are the mediums of the graphic arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What dances do the people do?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What types of music are there?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What themes are present in art, music, dance?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What is the source of these themes?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-art-and-aesthetics-art">
            <title>Art</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-art-and-aesthetics-music">
            <title>Music</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-art-and-aesthetics-dance">
            <title>Dance</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-art-and-aesthetics-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-religion-and-spirituality">
        <title>Merovan Religion and Spirituality</title>
        <para>Beliefs about the divine, the sacred, and humanity’s place in the universe.
            Includes organized religions and informal spiritual practices.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-religion-and-spirituality-dieties">
            <title>Deities</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-religion-and-spirituality-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-food-and-cuisine">
        <title>Merovan Food and Cuisine</title>
        <para>The types of food a culture prepares, how it is cooked, and its significance in social or ceremonial contexts.
            Example: Mediterranean cultures are known for olive oil and seafood, while Japanese cuisine emphasizes rice and fish.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-food-and-cuisine-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-technology-and-material">
        <title>Merovan Technology and Materials</title>
        <para>Tools, technology, and objects a culture creates and uses.
            Example: Clothing styles, architecture, transportation, and tools reflect cultural adaptation to the environment.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Metal technology ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Power technology?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Magic technology?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-technology-and-material-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para> </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-economics-and-trade">
        <title>Economics and Trade</title>
        <para>How resources are produced, distributed, and consumed.
            Examples: Subsistence farming, industrial economies, or global trade networks.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-economics-and-trade-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-military">
        <title>Merovan Military</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of military does your culture have?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To whom or what does it swear allegiance?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does it have a history of coup attempts, or successful coups?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it permanent in nature, or is it something that gathers during threats?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of training does it get?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of hierarchy does it have?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is military membership voluntary or involuntary?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there benefits to belonging to the military, such as citizenship at the end of service (as in Rome), or healthcare and housing, or regular meals?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are the families of military members cared for in any way?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the dangers of military membership?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the surrounding population approve of the military, or are parts or all of it anti-military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the military have definite outside threats to deal with? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is the culture or country at war? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it threatened by invasion? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it threatened by war?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the military have a positive peacetime role?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-military-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="merova-culture-esoterica">
        <title>Esoterica</title>
        <para>Use of Psionics, Spirit, Magic etc.. .</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do people relate to Esoterica?.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do people relate to Esoteric Practictioners.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="merova-culture-esoterica-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <index xml:id="book-of-merova-index">
        <title>Book of Merova Index</title>        
    </index>
    
    <glossary>
        <title>World of Tanah Glossary</title>
        <glossentry xml:id="glossentry-torgan-road">
            <glossterm>Torgan Roads</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>
                    <indexterm><primary>Torgan Road</primary></indexterm>
                    Torgan roads are found everywhere on the continent. Ranging from 2 meters wide to 24 meters wide in a few places.   
                    The roads are built with layered construction. Like Roman viaducts, they are often accompanied by aquaducts carrying water, 
                    and interspersed with different features, such as widened plazas and fountains The roads are usually edged with walls 
                    that vary from half a meter tall on the smaller roads to 2 m tall on the larger ones.
                    Often the roads rise up on elevated structures consisting of a series of arches, spans, or piers designed to carry a road over a valley, lowland, 
                    or other obstacles like rivers and wetlands. 
                    The roads are built with a slight arch or camber to allow water to run off into ditches on either side, preventing flooding and erosion.
                    Deep side ditches collect and direct rainwater away from the road with culverts and drainage pipes were built under the road when needed.
                </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="glossentry-torgan-road-trivium">
            <glossterm>Trivium (plural triva)</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>
                    A trivium is a widened plaza, usually found on a <link linkend="glossentry-torgan-road">Torgan road</link> usually containing 
                    some combination of stone benches, walled stalls, and fountains. Often a combination of meeting place and open market for Torgan cities.
                </para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
    </glossary>
    
</book>
