<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Book of Thenea</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>Jim Mochel</orgname>
            <address>
                <city>Bellingham, MA</city>
                <street>7 Walter Morse Rd</street>
                <postcode>02019</postcode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <email>jmochel@saltations.org</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <subtitle>Its a house eat house world</subtitle>
        <para>
            Cultures are comprised of people:
            <simplelist>
                <member>Who share common ground of some sort</member>
                <member>and are born of a shared set of conversations</member>
                <member>Who share common rituals</member>
                <member>who adhere to specific goals
                    which require the setting aside of differences</member>
                <member>and demand of each member personal initiatives that create value</member>
                <member>in order for all members to benefit by their exchange of individual effort</member>
                <member>and to survive, propagate, and grow beyond the lifetimes of the current members
                </member>
            </simplelist>
            Subcultures - Share all the basic tenets of their main culture, but which
            <simplelist>
                <member>share common ground of some sort that is not universal to the main culture</member>
                <member>Results in a NARROWER common ground the group shares, making membership in a subculture more exclusive but also more restrictive than membership in a culture.
                </member>
            </simplelist>
            Countercultures (rather than a rabble)
            <simplelist>
                <member>Contain each characteristic of a culture in a fully formed fashion.</member>
                <member>Provide a complete philosophy of their own , not simply state we are against the main culture.</member>
                <member>Provide creative, not destructive, goals for its members (creative != positive)</member>
                <member>Propagate by recruiting member hip from those dissatisfied with the main culture who want to create something different and, in their eyes, better.</member>
            </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>{Resources}</para>
        <para>The Thenaen culture is limited to a fertile but small set of islands called,
            appropriately enough, the Thenaen Islands. The area is rich in good soil, jewels, gems,
            and the bounty of the sea. The trade currents of both the south and north lead to
            Thenae, though the northerly current subsides to deep water before reaching the islands.
            The trade currents, combined with the volcanic nature of the region, provide for a great
            variety in the flora and fauna of the ocean. There is little in the way of iron ore. The
            Thenaens depend on two very light metals called {\it Limena } and {\it Taen}. Both are
            ill suited for sword blades but useful for structural tasks.</para>
        <para>Most of the islands are high mana areas. Almost all of the major clans have a meeting
            house or demense in a high mana area. The Thenaens depend on wind power to provide them
            with much of their basic energy needs. Windmills and windturbines as well as water
            turbines are common.</para>
        <para>{Technology}</para>
        <para>A strange combination of magic and mechanics the Thenaens have a good knowledge of
            leverage and simple engines such as windmills. They have almost no knowledge od the use
            of beasts of burden and thus lack much of the attendant skills. Little or no leather
            craft. No ability to make  steel. </para>
        <para>A set of relatively predatory trade houses had held in check to a certain extent by veryrigid rules and dueling code
            Bargains and balance and dealings and deals are the heart and soul of the nation culture.
        </para>
        <para>Italian Latin in here as well</para>
        <para>Have the Venetian houses typically run day today by a woman while the politics are managed by the mail head of the clan or head of the house</para>
        <para>There is no distinction between mid house and trading house.
            Look up typical's windows and scheming on the part of venetian houses
            Do the Venetian houses have slaves? Do we have equivalent of the D'Angelo's?
            What does healing look like for the Venetians?
        </para>
        <para>
            Notes and points 
            <simplelist>
                <member>I am betting that they have a relatively mechanistic healing set of surgeons who combined with magical speedups make the difference.</member>
                <member>Venetian culture considers the actual house or clan house to be somewhat sacred. No one would ever be harmed in the clan house itself unless that was an actual war to take out the entire clan.</member>
                <member>Injuries and tools and everything else happen in neutral territory</member>
                <member>There are probably bravos or dandies who are both great rape your man rapier wielders as well as magic wielders</member>
                <member>Whatever happens it involves something mysterious and semi invisible that knocks over duelists duelists</member>
                <member>Start the story with a set of Nobles at a training club board Goulding club dueling club do I</member>
                <member>In the rare cases where a subclan or clan leader dual there may be some situations where the winner incur such debt that they are not responsible for the family of the loser</member>
                <member>Every venetian has a balance book</member>
                <member>The name of the house Takeda translates to instrument of balance</member>
                <member>Which also happens to be the name of a weapon used in a duel in a dual</member>
                <member> Women of the Venetian houses</member>
                <member>Have an extraordinary amount of freedom, they are able to bed whoever they which wish as long as they do not get pregnant and most venetian women have the basic magics that prevent them from being pregnant</member>
                <member>But it is not unusual for venetian women to be told who they're going to marry as part of an attempt to create alliances or suitable children</member>
                <member>In the magic of the Venetians is such that they tried to breed them true</member>
                <member>It is not unusual for Lohaus women to be trained in weapons and where pantaloons just as a mail would</member>
                <member>By the same token it is not unheard of the wood is much rarer for a mid house woman to do the same.</member>
                <member>Only one of the great houses of the Venetiansis truly notable for their magic while many of them have great mages or higher grade mages</member>
                <member>There is one family that's known for producing great rages mages wizards</member>
                <member>Corsons are normal and courtesans are a normal part of the nation culture</member>
                <member>Where does the wind come from</member>
                <member>They definitely have honey</member>
                <member>Do they grow olives?</member>
                <member>Keep in mind that the customs house is the great strengt</member>
                <member>Banking is very highly developed</member>
                <member>And many of the houses that are not high house but it affect the foundation of guilds for the important needs become we're constantly jockeying for position especially for the ships builders and some of the other specialized groups</member>
                <member>Look at having three distinct classes in effect Highhouse mid house in Lohaus constitutions</member>
            </simplelist>
            
        </para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment">
        <title>Physical Environment</title>
        <para>The physical environment (climate, landscape, resources) 
            shapes cultural practices, such as food, clothing, and housing.</para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-geography">
            <title>Geography</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The geography is...</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The area looks like...</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The area is accessed...</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What natural features mark the borders? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the most striking features of landscape, climate, animals, etc.
                        in this area? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will these features affect travel time, communication,
                        etc.?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What kinds of natural phenomenon might influence beliefs?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                The Thenaen culture is limited to a fertile but small set of islands called, appropriately enough, the Thenaen Islands. The area is rich in good soil, jewels, gems, and the bounty of the sea.
                The trade currents of both the south and north lead to Thenae, though the northerly current subsides to deep water before reaching the islands. The trade currents, combined with the volcanic nature of the region, provide for a great variety in the flora and fauna of the ocean.
                There is little in the way of iron ore. The Thenaens depend on two very light metals called {\it Limena } and {\it Taen}. Both are ill suited for sword blades but useful for structural tasks.
                Most of the islands are high mana areas. Almost all of the major clans have a meeting house or demense in a high mana area.
                The Thenaens depend on wind power to provide them with much of their basic energy needs. Windmills and windturbines as well as water turbines are common.
                
            </para>
            <para>Technology
                A strange combination of magic and mechanics, the Thenaens have a good knowledge of leverage and simple engines such as windmills. They have almost no knowledge of the use of beasts of burden and thus lack much of the attendant skills. Little or no leather craft. No ability to make steel.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-climate">
            <title>Climate</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The climate is...</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the climate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What of are the resources for survival?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What kind of clothes and shelter are needed?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What kind of food can be so grown, hunted, caught?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the climate allow only survival activities or is there for leisure  developments such as art philosophy etc.?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Winter</title>
                <para>Averages temp range. Snowfall. </para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Spring</title>
                <para>Averages temp range. Precipation..</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Summer</title>
                <para>Averages temp range. Precipation..</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Autumn</title>
                <para>Averages temp range. Precipation..</para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-resources">
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which areas are the most fertile farmland? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Where are mineral resources located?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which animals, birds, fish, and other wildlife are commonly found in
                        which areas? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there are imaginary animals such as dragons, where do they
                        live?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which natural resources, if any, have been depleted in which areas
                        over time?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which resources (e.g., coal, oil, iron ore, gold, diamonds,
                        limestone, etc.) are particularly abundant, and in which areas?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which are scarce?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there places where there are rich deposits that haven’t been
                        discovered yet, or where they haven’t been fully exploited?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How much conflict has been or might be caused by these imbalances in
                        resources? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How much active, peaceful trade?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What water resources available, and for what uses ?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the contested resources?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para>.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-flora-wild-trees">
            <title>Wild Trees</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para>.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-flora-cultivated-trees">
            <title>Cultivated Trees</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Apple</title>
                <para>
                    Apples were grown for eating, cooking, and fermenting into cider (a staple beverage).
                    Seeds and saplings were brought by Merova settlers and quickly became a staple of agriculture.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-flora-wild-plants">
            <title>Wild Plants</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-flora-cultivated-plants">
            <title>Cultivated Plants</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-wild-fauna">
            <title>Wild Fauna</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What animals are especially helpful to your world?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is a creature that preys on other nuisance creatures?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are he domesticated animals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the food animals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Whether the food taboos?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which animals are used in medicine.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What animals are used for poisons.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What wild animals, actual or imaginary, live in this area? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are any of them potentially useful — e.g., for fur, whale oil,
                            hides, magical ingredients, hat feathers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which animals, actual or imaginary, are commonly domesticated in
                            this area? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which aren’t here, but are elsewhere? (Example: water buffalo in
                            India vs. oxen in Europe vs. camels in desert areas.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there are imaginary animals (dragons, unicorns, etc.), how do
                            they fit into the ecology? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What do they eat? How much habitat do they require? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can they live anywhere, or do they prefer or need specific kinds of
                            climate or terrain? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they intelligent and/or capable of working spells, talking,
                            etc.?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-cultivated-fauna">
            <title>Cultivated Fauna</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What animals are especially helpful to your world?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is a creature that preys on other nuisance creatures?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are he domesticated animals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the food animals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Whether the food taboos?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which animals are used in medicine.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What animals are used for poisons.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What wild animals, actual or imaginary, live in this area? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are any of them potentially useful — e.g., for fur, whale oil,
                            hides, magical ingredients, hat feathers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which animals, actual or imaginary, are commonly domesticated in
                            this area? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Which aren’t here, but are elsewhere? (Example: water buffalo in
                            India vs. oxen in Europe vs. camels in desert areas.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there are imaginary animals (dragons, unicorns, etc.), how do
                            they fit into the ecology? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What do they eat? How much habitat do they require? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can they live anywhere, or do they prefer or need specific kinds of
                            climate or terrain? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they intelligent and/or capable of working spells, talking,
                            etc.?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Thenean</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-physical-environment-esoterica">
            <title>Esoterica</title>
            <para>Magical resources are ....</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-history">
        <title>Thenean History</title>
        <para>A culture’s history, including colonization, wars, migrations, and revolutions, impacts its identity and traditions..</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Where did it begin?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What directions did it spread?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Impact of magic?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Impact of non-human races, if any?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Impact of actions or direct interventions of the gods?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Conflicts ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Succession of rulers and/or changes in the form of government</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Invasions, movements of peoples, or dramatic mass migrations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Disaster related to plague, fire, disease, famine, pestilence,
                        etc.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Victory in war, establishment or expansion of colonies, major changes in
                        borders, etc.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Take note of dates when a natural event reduced or increase the amount
                        of natural resources (food, water, timber etc.) </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Take note of dates when a unnatural event change the resources as
                        well</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Keep in mind recovering from war takes about a generation without any
                        major wars.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Track specific dates one power shifted in civilizations (through who,
                        death of a monarch that something) and one of the powershift was
                        smooth.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How far back are there records or tales of historical events? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How widely known are these stories?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do average people believe old tales, or do they dismiss some that have a
                        basis in fact (e.g., Troy)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are the neighboring countries/peoples and what are they
                        like?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why did people settle in this country in the first place — strategic
                        location, trade route, water transport, minerals, good farming, etc.?
                        \</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have things changed much since, or do they still depend on whatever
                        brought them in the first place?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are the rivals or enemies of this country? How close are they
                        physically? How powerful?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are the heroes and villains of each country’s history (e.g.,
                        Washington and Lincoln in the U.S.; Henry V in England, etc.)? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why are they heroes/villains and what do this say about the country and
                        the people who admire them?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which peoples/countries/races have been in conflict in the recent past?
                        Why? When and why was the most recent war? Who won?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which peoples/countries/races fought, allied, traded, or were
                        traditional rivals? Where are there still hard feelings about old
                        events?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do the weapons of this country compare with those of surrounding
                        cities and countries?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have there been recent innovations that may upset the balance of power,
                        or is everyone more or less equal?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How many people are there in this country?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this compare with world population?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is considered a small town/large town/city in terms of number of
                        people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How diverse is the population of this country — how many different races
                        (human or non-human), creeds, etc. normally live in various cities and towns
                        in this country?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In what percentages?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do the weapons of this country compare with those of surrounding
                        cities and countries?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have there been recent innovations that may upset the balance of power,
                        or is everyone more or less equal?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-history-prehistory">
            <title>Thenean Pre History</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-history-meme">
            <title>Thenean Historical Memes</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the cultural conversations ? (Russians: I am not complaining)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the powerful myths ?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the memes?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-history-zzz3">
            <title>Thenean ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-history-zzz4">
            <title>Thenean ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-external-influences">
        <title>External Influences</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-external-influences-zzz1">
            <title>Other Cultures</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-external-influences-zzz2">
            <title>Economic</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-external-influences-zzz3">
            <title>Other Religions</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-external-influences-zzz4">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-beliefs-and-values">
        <title>Thenean Beliefs and Values</title>
        <para>
            The foundational principles and ideas that a culture holds to be true or important.
            Examples: Concepts of morality, spirituality, freedom, equality, or honor.
        </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are this culture’s historic heroes and villains (e.g.,
                        Washington and Lincoln in the U.S.; Henry V in England, etc.)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why are they admired as heroes/villains and what does this say about
                        the people who admire them?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Memes</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-language-and-communication">
        <title>Language and Communication</title>
        <para>The primary means of communication, including spoken and written languages, dialects, and non-verbal cues (gestures, body language, etc.).
            Language often reflects cultural priorities (e.g., Inuit languages have multiple words for snow).</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How many languages are there? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which ones are related (e.g., the Romance languages) and why? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which languages borrow words or phrases from other languages?  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which is likely to be most widely spoken?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a “trade language” that facilitates commerce between countries that don’t speak the same tongue? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a “universal language” spoken by educated or noble persons, as Latin was in the Middle Ages?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What languages are spoken?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is the language recorded?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are messages and information passed along?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is history recorded?,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>is the society literate or illiterate?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who provides education?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who receives education?, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is the "technology" involved in long distance communication?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a “trade language” that facilitates commerce between countries that don’t speak the same tongue?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a “universal language” spoken by educated or noble persons, as Latin was in the Middle Ages?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are some or all people bilingual?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a common second language many people know?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there “secret” languages or codes known only by priests, soldiers, wizards, guild members, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why were they developed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the variations in speech patterns, syntax, and slang from one social class to another?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>One occupation to another?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>One region to another?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>One race to another?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What areas do local slang phrases come out of?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What kinds of colorful turns of phrase do people use?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things in this culture would their language have many specific words for ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What do the people in this culture consider important enough to name?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What does this say about the way they look at the world?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things would the people of this culture not have a name for, or have one word that covers numerous variations?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What do they consider too unimportant to name?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this affect the way they see the world?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there words that must never be spoken except at particular times, in ceremonies, or under particular circumstances?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there words that must not be spoken in polite company?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do these words differ from culture to culture or race to race?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What will people swear a binding oath by?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What do people use as curse words?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-language-and-communication-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors">
        <title>Thenean Social Norms and Behaviors</title>
        <para>The social mores and unwritten rules that govern acceptable behavior in a society.
            Examples: Greetings, table manners, dress codes, and etiquette.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-general-social-traditions">
            <title>General Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-general-rituals">
            <title>General Social Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the holidays?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-social-traditions">
            <title>Childbirth Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What preparations for the birth do the parents make before birth?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there any taboos that must be avoided?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there any foods that must be eaten, or clothes that must be worn, or colors that must be avoided.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What restrictions are put on the mother during her pregnancy?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What restrictions are put on the father during her pregnancy?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the birth surrounded by fear or by joy?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are evil spirits considered present, so that they must be warded off?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are good spirits lured in?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the process moved from the realm of the natural into the realm of the medical, with families held apart from the woman in labor, and the entire endeavor treated as a disease, or a problem that must be fixed?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the new child welcomed or dreaded?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>During childbirth, do families gather while the woman is celebrated and cheered, or is she hustled away to a dark tent somewhere, looked at as filthy, and treated as if she were in need of cleansing?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under what circumstances will the newborn be welcomed?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under what circumstances will the newborn be welcomed: Does gender matter?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under what circumstances will the newborn be welcomed: Does health matter?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Under what circumstances will the newborn be welcomed: Does parentage matter, or the social status of the family, or the marital status of the parents?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is the newborn welcomed?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the culture in some way test its newborns for their ability to survive (as the Romans did with some newborns and exposure)?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there circumstances in which a newborn might be marked for death, as were firstborns offered as sacrifices in some cultures?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will some babies be killed before or after birth because of issues like gender, known or suspected deformity, questions about paternity, or something else?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-rituals">
            <title>Childbirth Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the family have community obligations to fulfill before, during, or after the birth of the child? If yes, describe them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the family have religious obligations to fulfill before, during, or after the birth of the child? If yes, describe them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the family have government obligations to fulfill before, during, or after the birth of the child. If yes, describe them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-expectations">
            <title>Childbirth Expectations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What expectations does a family have regarding the birth of the child? That it will be male? That it will be Female? That it will be Healthy? Have a specific birthmark? Fill a specific role in society when it grows up?                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the time or date of birth figure into these expectations? .</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-birth-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Childbirth Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>While in general a live birth and a healthy mother will be considered successful, and a dead mother or child will be considered a failure, there might be circumstances wherethis will not be true.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there are, what are the circumstances?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The culture might have other criteria that determine the success or failure of the birth, from the gender of the child to whether the child was a lucky or unlucky number (the lucky first kid, the unlucky fourth), to whether the child had a specific birthmark, or was born at a specific date or hour, or whether the child did something at birth that was considered good or bad.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What sort of other criteria does the culture use to determine the success or failure of the birth?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-social-traditions">
            <title>Childhood Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Before they can walk and talk, how are children treated and tended, and by whom?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Once they are able to walk and talk, how does this change?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Once they can reason (about age six), how does this change?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>At what age are they considered useful?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are these stages of their lives marked off?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do they have special clothes that they wear?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do they have hairstyles that mark their status?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-rituals">
            <title>Childhood Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Does the culture celebrate rituals that mark the passing stages of childhood?
                            If so, what are the stages, and what are the rituals</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-expectations">
            <title>Childhood Expectations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What expectations do parents have of a child at each stage of childhood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do these expectations vary from child to child in a family?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do boys have different roles than girls?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are expectations different for the  firstborn than the lastborn? (For example, the firstborn is expected to take over the family farm, the lastborn is expected to stay home,never marry, and take care of the parents as they grow old.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are expectations different across social  strata?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do the occupations of the parents affect expectations on the children?   </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-value-of-learning">
            <title>Value of Education</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is the education of the young carried out in your culture?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By apprenticeships?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By learning at home?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By fostering out?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By  mentoring with masters? By sitting in a classroom reading textbooks?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What sorts of careers are possible in your culture, and how do children prepare to achieve them?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they chosen by status?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By ability?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By competition?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By lottery?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By gender?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By race?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>By oracle from the time of birth?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Aside from innate intelligence, are there barriers that prevent a child of your culture from obtaining the education another child could have?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Slavery or caste status?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Poverty?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Illegitimate birth, ill-favored birth, bad birthmark, ugliness, race, gender, or something else?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-why">
            <title>Why?</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>So. How does your culture answer the question “Why?”</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it treat those who persistently dare to ask “Why?”</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-childhood-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Childhood Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect child of your culture will do.... what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will be.... what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will achieve what by the end of the age that your culture defines as the end of childhood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed child of your culture will do.... what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will be.... what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will achieve what by the end of the age that your culture defines as the end of childhood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-social-traditions">
            <title>Young Adult Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture determine who is and who is not a young adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What part do the actions of the would-be adult play in becoming a young adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is adulthood seen as an achievement, or do people glorify the more helpless state of childhood as some sort of ideal lost Eden?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges does the young adult earn by making this passage?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges are withheld for a later level of achievement, or later status? (If any)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are these later increases in achievement given?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-rituals">
            <title>Young Adult Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What family rituals mark the entrance of the child into young adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The choosing of a spouse?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Sending off to a craft master for additional education?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The deeding of a piece of land?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The building of an independent home?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The gift of money, or a set of tools?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What community rituals mark the entrance of the child into young adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Hazing?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A huge party?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A gathering in which young adults are presented to society as available for matrimony?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What religious rituals mark the entrance of the child into young adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A coming of age ceremony?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The assumption of a role in the religion, either as an acolyte or a full member?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The taking of vows to the religion?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What government rituals mark the entrance of the child into young adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Swearing fealty to a king or lord?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Entrance into military service?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The duty of taxes?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The requirement of a gift to the leader?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Right to vote, own property, become self-determining?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Young Adult Expectations of Work</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the young adult a fully functioning member of society, or is he still considered untried?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does gender, race, or social status change the expectations with which the culture views the new young adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is open to the young adult that is not open to full adults or children?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is closed to the young adult that is available to children or full adults?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the young adult in your culture regard future career improvements?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to change jobs?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to choose different work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to pursue dreams?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Young Adult Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will the young adult of your culture find a mate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will he or she seek one out, or will the culture provide approved methods of presenting acceptable candidates?                     </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does your young adult have any choice in the selection process?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the creation of a family an immediate requirement of the young adult, or is a period of singleness (with or without possible experimentation) permissible, or evenxpected?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If singleness is permissible or accepted, what expressions of sexuality are permitted within your culture?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens to those young adults who stray outside of the permissible? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Punishment, shunning, banishment, execution?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Young Adult Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture view the rebellion of the young adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it treat the rebellious young adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the young adult who wants to rebel do so and still survive the experience?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-young-adult-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Young Adult Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect young adult male in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect young adult female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed young adult male in your culture will....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed young adult female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-social-traditions">
            <title>Adulthood Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture determine who is and who is not a full adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there tests?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Rituals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Mandatory forms of government or religious service?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Gender barriers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Race barriers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Caste barriers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What part do the actions of the young adult play in giving him access to full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is full adulthood seen as an achievement, or is it something people just age into?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture view full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges does the adult earn by achieving this passage?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there multiple layers of full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges are withheld for a later level of achievement, or later status? (If any)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are these later increases in achievement given?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-rituals">
            <title>Adulthood Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>What family rituals mark the entrance of the young adulthood into full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The successful birth of a first child?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The opening of a personal business, studio, or craft?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A place of prestige in the family hierarchy?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What community rituals mark the entrance of the young adult into full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Admission into a secret society?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A place of prestige in a community group?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The newly minted full adult taking on apprentices?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What religious rituals mark the entrance of the young adult into full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The assumption of a role in the religion, either as an elder or a full member?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A ceremony?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The assumption of a leadership role that will see the new leader teaching, or in other ways presenting the religion to others?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What government rituals mark the entrance of the young adult into full adulthood?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recognition by a king or lord?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Completion of military service, or a raise in rank or status?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The right to collect taxes?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ability to become a leader?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Right to bestow property, or bestow rank or privilege on others?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Adulthood Expectations of Work</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>


                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the full adult expected to innovate, to teach his craft, to explore new ideas?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Conversely, is his role to prevent innovation, to guard tradition, to maintain an unbroken line from past history to the future?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does gender, race, or social status change the expectations with which the culture views the full adult and his work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is open to the full adult that is not open to young adults or children?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is closed to the full adult that is available to children or young adults?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the full adult in your culture regard future career advancements?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to change jobs?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to choose different work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is it possible to pursue dreams?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Adulthood Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>


                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will the full adult of your culture find or keep a mate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he or she replace an unsatisfactory mate?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he deal with a mate lost to desertion or death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he deal with sexuality if single?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the culture press the full adult to continue adding to family, to expand numbers of wives or concubines, to support the households of his young adult children and their families?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Must the full adult gather dowries?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the full adult permitted sexual experimentation of any sort, or is that something that must be put aside?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens to those adults who stray outside of the permissible modes of sexual expression?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Punishment, shunning, banishment, execution?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-adulthood-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Adulthood Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture view the rebellion of the full adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it treat the rebellious full adult?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the full adult who wants to rebel do so and still survive the experience?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect full adult male in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect full adult female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed full adult male in your culture will....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed full adult female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-social-traditions">
            <title>Old Age Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture determine who is and who is not an elder?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What part do the actions of the full adult play in moving him into the category of elder?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is old age seen as an achievement, or is it something people just age into? Do people attempt to fend it off? How does your culture view old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges does the elder earn by achieving this passage? Are there multiple layers of old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What privileges or later status are withheld for elders, if any?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are these later increases in achievement given?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-rituals">
            <title>Old Age Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What family rituals mark the entrance of full adulthood into old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The successful birth of a first grandchild?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The wedding of the last child?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The giving of a place of honor in the family hierarchy?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Leaving work to retire?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What community rituals mark the entrance of the full adult into old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A place of leadership in a secret society?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A place of prestige in a community group?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A master- raftsman status that brings other masters to study with the elder?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What religious rituals mark the entrance of the full adult into old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The assumption of a role in the religion, or the handing off of responsibilities to someone younger?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A ceremony?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Becoming overseer of the new leaders who teach the religion?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What government rituals mark the entrance of the full adult into old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recognition by a  king or lord?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Retirement from military service with or without pension?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Release from the payment of taxes?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ability to become a leader?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Right to bestow property, or bestow rank or privilege on others?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-expectations-of-work">
            <title>Old Age Expectations of Work</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the elder expected to teach his craft or transmit the culture’s heritage, mores, and conventions? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the elder expected to explore spirituality, to transmit or create laws or other forms of guidance for those coming behind? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the elder expected to find lessons from his long life and turn them into something useful for younger generations?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does gender, race, or social status change the expectations with which the culture views the elder and his work?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is open to the elder that is not open to others? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What work is closed to the elder that is available to others?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the elder in your culture regard future career advancements, or career continuance? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the elder look forward to a future in which he is secure, or into an abyss of gradual poverty and darkness? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is he/she permitted control of his own destiny? </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-expectations-of-sex">
            <title>Old Age Expectations of Sex</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will the elder of your culture deal with a mate lost to desertion or death? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he or she replace a lost mate? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How will he deal with sexuality if single?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does the culture press the elder to maintain and support numbers of wives or concubines, and assist in the upkeep of households of his adult children and their families? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are the responsibilities of the elder to his progeny?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the elder permitted sexual experimentation of any sort, or is that something that must be put aside?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens to those elders who stray outside of the permissible modes of sexual expression? Punishment, shunning, banishment, execution?</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-conformism-and-rebellion">
            <title>Old Age Conformism and Rebellion</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your culture view the rebellion of the elderly?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it treat the rebellious elder? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the elder who wants to rebel do so and still survive the experience?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Cost of Aging</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does your culture fight to prolong life? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In which cases?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What place has it made for dying elders? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do families care for dying elders? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the community care for them? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does religion care for them? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does government care for them?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What respect does the culture show dying Elders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-old-age-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Old Age Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect elderly male in your culture will ....? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The perfect elderly female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed elderly male in your culture will....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The failed elderly female in your culture will ....?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-social-traditions">
            <title>Death Social Traditions</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the culture treat the death of one of its members? Does it treat the deathdifferently by age, by status, by gender, by singleness, or if the dead was paired, or familied?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Does it treat the death differently when it occurs by different means–suicide or murder,disease or illness, when caused by congenital problems, accident or old age?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the family deal with the death of a member, and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the community deal with death and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does religion deal with death and those bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does government deal with death andthose bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-rituals">
            <title>Death Rituals</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals do the family and/or friends perform or require for the dead?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does the community perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does religion perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What rituals does the government perform or require for the dead or from the bereaved?</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-expectations">
            <title>Death Expectations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does the culture as a whole view the future of the dead person?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does that future vary related to the life the person lived?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does that future vary related to the person’s status, or gender, or age at death, or religious or government affiliation?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-norms-and-behaviors-death-success-vs-failure">
            <title>Death Success or Failure</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Razors</emphasis>Razors
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>So with that in mind, how does your culture define a success in death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does it define a failure in death?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What variables in religion, age, status, gender and so on will change whether the deceased dies a success or a failure?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization">
        <title>Thenean Social Organization</title>
        <para>How a culture structures relationships and roles in society.
            Includes family dynamics, gender roles, class systems, and community hierarchies</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the rules? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who made the rules?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does society get its rules?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is justice dispensed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are criminals apprehended?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What punishments are used?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who are the rulers?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How has the presence of magic and magicians affected law and
                        government?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are wizards barred from certain kinds of government jobs or
                        offices?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do some government jobs require that their holder be a wizard?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What forms are used in neighboring countries, and why are they the same or
                        different?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What services does the government or head of state provide: schools, wells,
                        courts, an army to protect people from the Vikings?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What services are provided locally or privately?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who has the right to levy taxes?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For what?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On what or whom?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Can taxes be paid in kind, or do certain things require money?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who provides support services for the head of state?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are they called: King’s Counselors, Cabinet Ministers, Secretary of
                        State, Good Ol’ Girls?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they hereditary offices, civil servants, appointees, military,
                        elected?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is the relative power of a country or ruler usually measured by the size of
                        its army, the number and ability of its wizards, or the amount of money/trade
                        flowing through it?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is considered a citizen, with the rights and privileges
                        thereof?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are those rights and privileges (voting, protection from thieves, the
                        right to a hearing in Rome) and what responsibilities go along with them (jury
                        duty, providing funds or knights for the lord’s army?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there certain classes of people (wizards, foreigners, children,
                        peasants, women) who have fewer legal rights or less recourse than full
                        citizens?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they considered mentally or morally deficient, a danger to the state, or
                        is there some other rationale?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the easiest/most common ways to advance in status — amass more
                        money, marry well, get the ruler’s eye, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much resistance is there to someone advancing in social status?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who will take over running the government if the current head of state is
                        incapacitated?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is this determined?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there an heir apparent (either actual or political)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What happens if the heir is a minor?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who gives orders?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are they picked?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is responsible for protecting the head of state?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>His personal guard, the Secret Service, an elite group affiliated with the
                        regular military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What safeguards have they got against assassins, poisoning, direct assault,
                        magical attack?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who can give orders (to military, to tax collectors, to servants, to
                        ordinary folks on the street)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How are such people chosen?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who is responsible for coinage: the ruler, local barons, someone else
                        (merchant guilds)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there generally acceptable standards?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How easy/common is counterfeiting?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there an organized system of education?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If so, who provides it: government, churches, private persons?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How is it supported?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who can call up men for an army, and how?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the ruler ask the nobility for men, who in turn draft their peasants,
                        or can the ruler go straight to the bottom?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much formal spying and intelligence gathering is normally done by
                        governments?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Merchant guilds and wealthy tradesmen?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there actual organizations, or is spying done by diplomats and/or
                        freelance agents?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How effective is it currently?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do relations between countries depend mainly on the relations between the
                        heads of state, or can two rulers hate each other’s guts without being able to
                        just declare war and drag their countries into it?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there times when people are expected to fast, or feast (e.g., before
                        solstice, after the birth of a child, during Lent or Ramadan, after the death of
                        a ruler, etc.)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there occasions when the ruler is expected to provide a celebration or
                        spectacle for the people to enjoy, (e.g., the Roman gladiatorial
                        games)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much influence do “special interest groups” such as merchants, wizards,
                        or various religions, have on court politics?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they exercise their influence — indirectly (by talking nobility or
                        council members into taking their sides) or directly (by bribery, coercion,
                        having their own representatives on the council)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there any shaky political alliances between disparate groups?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Why were they formed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How long is it likely to be before they fall apart?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When they do, what will the effects be?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What ancient rivalries and hatreds still affect current attitudes and
                        political positions (examples: Scottish and Welsh separatist groups; Catholics
                        vs. Protestants vs. Muslims; dwarves vs. elves; Hatfields vs. McCoys)?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-power">
            <title>Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the source of power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What groups have power and who are the players?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What groups have the most political power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-government-type">
            <title>Type of Government</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the basic style of government: feudal, aristocratic, oligarchy,
                        absolute ruler, democracy, what?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who are the rulers?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are the rulers chosen?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is power passed on to the next leaders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What is the basic style of rule</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who will take over running the moeity if the current ruler is incapacitated?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How is this determined?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is there an heir apparent (either actual or political)?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What happens if the heir is a minor?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who gives orders?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are they picked?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who is responsible for protecting the ruler?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What safeguards have they got against assassins, poisoning, direct assault, magical attack?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What impact on the above does Magic or Magic Users have?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-government-executive-power">
            <title>Executive Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who or what is the recognized head of your government?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>King, President, Council of Regents, Office of Bureaucratic Muckety-Mucks, High Priestess, Supreme Warchief, guy with the biggest stick, guy with the biggest brain?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the executive office a figurehead office, or one with real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does your leader delegate power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To whom does your leader willingly listen and from whom does he willingly take advice? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To whom does your leader unwillingly listen, and from whom does he unwillingly take advice? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If your leader is a figurehead, who holds the real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How did that person or group get real power?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How does he or the group hold it?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who opposes your leader? Why?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How deep does the power of your head of government go?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is he responsible for the gathering and ordering of armies? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The making of laws? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The dispensing of justice to individuals? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can he go into individual homes and claim property or people? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is he above the law, or must he, too, obey it?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-legislative-power">
            <title>Legislative Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who makes the laws in your culture?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How did this person or group get the job?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do they deal with old laws?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do they have a guiding principle around which they must form their laws (a constitution, a religious book, a historic epic poem, a collection of antiquated laws)?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there areas or subjects about which they may not make laws (religion, sex, pregnancy and childbirth, composition of additives to coffee, availability of booze)?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are the laws required to represent everyone, or do separate laws apply to separate people?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-judicial-power">
            <title>Judicial Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What sort of justice system prevails in your culture?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who judges presumed criminals? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there checks and balances–a mandated government or private representative for the accused, a jury of peers? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Or is guilt presumed with the judge holding the role of judge and jury, and the accused forced to speak for himself and prove his own case?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How are sentences given?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Is there a code with fixed sentences for certain crimes? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there restrictions in the form of sentencing, or can the judge require the convicted criminal to run in circles naked in the town square because he thinks it would be funny?    </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who carries out sentences? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is there a prison system, a series of work farms, a mandatory slavery system, automatic execution? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are there guards, bailiffs, slave markets, overseers? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Is the family of a criminal subject to the same punishment as the criminal? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Can, for example, an entire family be sold into slavery to pay off one man’s unpaid debts? Can an entire extended family be executed because of a “contagion” theory of criminality, where anyone who is related to a criminal is guilty of being a criminal, too</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-surreptitious-power">
            <title>Surreptitious Power</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What surreptitious power-holders does your culture have? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How do they work? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Who can be members?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>What are their goals?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they government insiders, or do they influence the government through secret manipulation from outside, or are their goals unrelated to their own government and their interests turned elsewhere?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they basically good—people working to overthrow corruption and slavery and a regime filled with torture and injustice?</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Are they basically evil—working to acquire ever more power at the expense of people already less powerful? </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-social-organization-zzz3">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-clothing">
        <title>Thenean Clothing</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What do people wear?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How expensive is it?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Can the material be produced locally, or must some or all of it be
                        imported?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are weapons a standard part of dress for any/all segments of
                        society?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Are certain clothes customary for certain occupations — e.g., military
                        uniforms, judges robes/wigs, sports teams uniforms, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How much variation is allowed — could a scholar wear a day-glow green
                        robe as long as the cut is right, or would that be too much?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it color or style that is most important?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Are the dyes for certain colors — purple, indigo, etc. — rare, making
                        cloth of that color more expensive and/or reserved for nobility or other
                        high-status people?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there sumptuary laws, defining who can wear what?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the penalties?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who decides when changes are needed?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How often are they adjusted?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there fashions/fads in things besides clothes — styles of carriages,
                        furniture, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there fashions/fads in magic — are herbal spells “in” this year and
                        ritual spells “out,” or vice versa?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>How many changes of clothes can a normal person afford?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A noble person?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A peasant?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What is the current fashion in clothes?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hats?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Jewelry?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shoes?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do such fashions differ for humans/non-humans?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Between city and country?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What materials are appropriate to the climate?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What materials must be imported, and are therefore for expensive
                        upper-class clothes only?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What things are considered tacky and vulgar, and what things are
                        stylish?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What types of decorations and accessories are common?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What colors and combinations of colors are thought to look well or to
                        clash?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do opinions on this vary from race to race?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>What physical types and characteristics are currently fashionable — tan
                        vs. pale skin, the “consumptive look” vs. robust good health, fat vs. thin,
                        blonde vs. brunette, muscles vs. “dead poet”, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>How do non-human fashions reflect their physiology?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do dragons dress for dinner?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do mermaids have a nudity taboo?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-clothing-birth">
            <title>Thenean</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-art-and-aesthetics">
        <title>Thenean Art and Aesthetics</title>
        <para>Forms of creative expression, including art, music, literature, dance, and architecture.
            Reflects the culture's sense of beauty, symbolism, and storytelling.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is the status of the arts (dance, music, theater, etc.) in this
                        society?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are artists revered or mistrusted?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they considered noble or immoral?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who supports the arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which arts are most highly valued and why?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there permanent theaters or concert halls for the performing
                        arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If so, who owns and runs them?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are they profitable?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there also traveling troupes of players/musicians/dancers?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do their performances differ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Can magic be used in the arts, and if so, how — paint that glows,
                        pictures that move, flutes that play themselves, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do “normal” artists feel about this?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is there a separate branch of purely magical art, such as
                        illusion?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have paper-making and the printing press been invented, or are books and
                        scrolls rare, expensive, handwritten items?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things are considered appropriate subjects for representational
                        arts such as painting and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which are not?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>(Examples: some cultures/religions forbid the painting or sculpture of
                        the human figure, and have abstract art; some have limited painters to doing
                        only “uplifting” religious works, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there non-human races who tend to be naturally talented painters,
                        dancers, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this affect human practitioners of these arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are certain races/cultures considered better at some arts than other
                        races/cultures?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Where do the best dancers, painters, musicians, actors, etc. come
                        from?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have paper-making and the printing press been invented, or are books and
                        scrolls rare, expensive, handwritten items?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What things are considered appropriate subjects for representational
                        arts such as painting and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Which are not?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>(Examples: some cultures/religions forbid the painting or sculpture of
                        the human figure, and have abstract art; some have limited painters to doing
                        only “uplifting” religious works, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there non-human races who tend to be naturally talented painters,
                        dancers, etc.?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How does this affect human practitioners of these arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are certain races/cultures considered better at some arts than other
                        races/cultures?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Where do the best dancers, painters, musicians, actors, etc. come
                        from?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the standards of beauty for people?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paintings and sculpture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Clothes and furniture?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do they differ from the standards in your culture (example: a
                        country which considers fatness a highly desirable beauty trait)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do standard of beauty reflect the physical traits of the various
                        races (examples: dwarves might consider excessive height unattractive;
                        werewolves might be attracted by long teeth or a particular scent)?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What are the mediums of the graphic arts?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What dances do the people do?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What types of music are there?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What themes are present in art, music, dance?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> What is the source of these themes?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-art-and-aesthetics-art">
            <title>Art</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-art-and-aesthetics-music">
            <title>Music</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-art-and-aesthetics-dance">
            <title>Dance</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-art-and-aesthetics-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-religion-and-spirituality">
        <title>Thenean Religion and Spirituality</title>
        <para>Beliefs about the divine, the sacred, and humanity’s place in the universe.
            Includes organized religions and informal spiritual practices.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-religion-and-spirituality-dieties">
            <title>Deities</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-religion-and-spirituality-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-food-and-cuisine">
        <title>Thenean Food and Cuisine</title>
        <para>The types of food a culture prepares, how it is cooked, and its significance in social or ceremonial contexts.
            Example: Mediterranean cultures are known for olive oil and seafood, while Japanese cuisine emphasizes rice and fish.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-food-and-cuisine-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para/>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-technology-and-material">
        <title>Thenean Technology and Materials</title>
        <para>Tools, technology, and objects a culture creates and uses.
            Example: Clothing styles, architecture, transportation, and tools reflect cultural adaptation to the environment.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Metal technology ?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Power technology?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Magic technology?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-technology-and-material-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para> </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-economics-and-trade">
        <title>Economics and Trade</title>
        <para>How resources are produced, distributed, and consumed.
            Examples: Subsistence farming, industrial economies, or global trade networks.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-economics-and-trade-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-military">
        <title>Thenean Military</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of military does your culture have?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To whom or what does it swear allegiance?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does it have a history of coup attempts, or successful coups?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it permanent in nature, or is it something that gathers during threats?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of training does it get?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What sort of hierarchy does it have?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is military membership voluntary or involuntary?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are there benefits to belonging to the military, such as citizenship at the end of service (as in Rome), or healthcare and housing, or regular meals?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Are the families of military members cared for in any way?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the dangers of military membership?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the surrounding population approve of the military, or are parts or all of it anti-military?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the military have definite outside threats to deal with? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is the culture or country at war? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it threatened by invasion? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Is it threatened by war?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Does the military have a positive peacetime role?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-military-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="thenea-culture-esoterica">
        <title>Esoterica</title>
        <para>Use of Psionics, Spirit, Magic etc.. .</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Razors for Distinguishing</title>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do people relate to Esoterica?.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do people relate to Esoteric Practictioners.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <section xml:id="thenea-culture-esoterica-zzz">
            <title>ZZZ</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
