<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD MathML 2.0//EN" "http://www.w3.org/Math/DTD/mathml2/mathml2.dtd">
<?xml-model href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/dbmathmlsvg.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Races and Cultures of Tanah</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>Jim Mochel</personname>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>1987</year>
            <year>2011</year>
        </copyright>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Human Races</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Sarsin</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 5'4"/5'2"</member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 125/110</member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Dark brown</member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Black hair</member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Brown</member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Thenaen</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 6'1"/5'11" </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 175/150 </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Fair skin </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Red </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Grey or Green </member>
                    <member>Inherent Skills - ME(Mana) R0</member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Merovan</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 5'9"/5'6" </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 150/130 </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Light </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Full range </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Full range </member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Kothan</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Avg. Height - 5'11"/5'10" </member>
                <member>Avg. Weight - 165/145 </member>
                <member>Skin Color - Fair </member>
                <member>Hair Color - Light wavy or curly </member>
                <member>Eye Color - blue and green </member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Kalifate</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Avg. Height - 5'8"/5'4" </member>
                <member>Avg. Weight - 155/120 </member>
                <member>Skin Color - Swarthy </member>
                <member>Hair Color - Dark, straight </member>
                <member>Eye Color - Dark Brown to Black </member>
            </simplelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Non Human Races</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Hairochon</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 6'4"/6'4"</member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight 240/210</member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Brown</member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Ash Blond</member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Hazel</member>
                    <member>Stat Mods - PST +1 PEN +1 PSI -2</member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <para> </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Bitadari</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Culture Name - Bitadari </member>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 5'2"/5'0" </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 114/104 </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - NA </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - NA </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Depends on Life Cycle </member>
                    <member>Stat Mods - PST -1,PEN -1,PSI +1,MVMMOD 1.2</member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <para> The Bitadari are not your typical elves. They are a race with a lifestyles and
                cultures based on the fact that they go through different life cycles and forms. </para>
            <para> Bitadari speak of distinct "Life Ages" or K\={i}. These are distinct forms. These
                forms have some basis in how old the elf is\footnote{There is almost no correlation
                to the chronological ages of the entity.} They are in name : Chawara (Infancy),
                Iquira (\={E}-kwer-a) (Childhood), Anatathan (An-a-ta-than) (Young Adult), Laenya
                (L\={a}-\={e}-nya) (Time of Passing), Sheerahnen (She-\={e}-rah-n\={e}n) (Fullness),
                Eya (\={E}-ya) (Inward Turning). </para>
            <para> As a race the population of elves is driven by the environment. If Anatathan are
                needed than more Iquira become Anatathan and less Anatathan become Laenya. In times
                of war there will be more Anatathan than Iquira. </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Chawara (Infancy)</title>
                <para> A path is decided by the first step, and no sooner. - Elven Proverb. </para>
                <para> An elven child is born without hair or nails. Almost no real vision is
                    developed until a month after birth. Empathy, for many, is at the strongest it
                    will be ever be. The environment empathically influences the future forms of the
                    Elf. It is conceivable that the first hint of mage talents could be seen here.
                    For non-mage children this empathy will diminish as the entity enters Iquira.
                    Mesaah (M\={E}-SA-AH) or mage children, will retain much of their empathy. (2-3
                    years) . Twins are almost unheard of and triplets are truly unknown. Eyes are
                    often pale and almost clear. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Iquira (Childhood)</title>
                <para> Empathy tends to drop to its lowest point. Much of the energies turn toward
                    care of almost all domestic activities. Farming is more common than hunting and
                    meat eating is rare. Most of the farming is small lot based. As the elf matures
                    ( 20-200 years) In times of large population growth a small percentage of Iquira
                    never go on to the state of Anatathan. The gradually diminishing empathy comes
                    to be superseded by a mild form of telepathy. Iquira have crystalline colors in
                    their eyes. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Anatathan (Young Adult)</title>
                <para> The anatathan are the warriors, the fighters. As they get older , they gain
                    in natural speed and perception. It is here that most elves can become fertile
                    though only during periods of stress for the race do many anatathan have
                    children. And , when they do, these same children tend to be quick to become
                    Anatathan. It is often that during these periods of stress that Anatathan never
                    become Laenya. It is said to be a sacrifice that the elf's spirit made for the
                    race. For this reason it is appropriate to mourn the passing of an Anatathan
                    where one would not mourn a Laenya ( who did, after all, lived out a full life
                    ). Typically lasts between 20 - 300 years. Anatathan eyes are usually brighter
                    colored , hovering between translucent and transparent. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Laenya (Fullness)</title>
                <para> Those that live on to become Laenya gain in empathy again and tend to pursue
                    their final goals. They become leaders and mages , craftsman and artists. More
                    live to become Laenya during the peaceful times. The natural magics intensify
                    and become very noticeable. The reflexes do not slow but the combat perceptions
                    gradually fade. The elf's knowledge of his body becomes nearly complete.
                    Poisoning and disease becomes rarer. The Laenya eyes tend to be darker and
                    definitely opaque. The period lasts between 900 and 1000 years. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Ea (Inward Turning)</title>
                <para> Those who live to this most venerated state are rare. The elves' empathy
                    becomes almost as great as when they were Chawara. Their empathy gradually
                    extends to all life within their perception. The eyes darken to nearly black and
                    their sight loses all IR and Visible acuity. Only the UV and shorter wavelengths
                    are used. The greatest philosophies and thoughts of the elven culture come from
                    those who have achieved this state. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Abilities of Bitadaran</title>
                <para> In general the elves have a variety of talents. They have a greater than
                    average PSI and are comfortable with basic sorceries. Most forms have a DF +1
                    when doing minor magics or sorceries. Anatathan have a DF-1 to minor magery.
                    Anatathan often produce unpredictable results with those magics they do use. </para>
                <para> Most elves are less physically enduring and less strong then their human
                    counterparts. </para>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Faen</title>
                    <para> Faen is the proximity sense that is first developed by the Iquira and is
                        most visible in the Anatathan. At any point that an entity enters within an
                        Anatathan's perception (GAW in feet) their perception increases briefly (As
                        per setup). </para>
                    <para> All perception rolls are made based on this increased perception. This
                        perception comes to the elf during times of stress and is often visible to
                        others as a drastic change in the reflective patterns of the eyes. Also, any
                        agility or strengthed based feat is a little easier (DF +1). </para>
                </sect4>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Alitharinaa(Sense of self)</title>
                    <para> At a time of injury, infection, or poisoning. The Bitadara often will go
                        into a kind of "Healing Shock". This state is seen as a complete darkening
                        of the entire eye of the Elf. This state allows for the regrowth of
                        endurance as if it were fatigue. (Excludes cold Iron damage) </para>
                </sect4>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Kiilan(Mind Seeing)</title>
                    <para> During Early stages this shows itself as empathy and then telepathy and
                        finally, both. </para>
                </sect4>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Cold Iron(Irinal)</title>
                    <para> Iron (not steel) is the true bane of Bitadaran life. All Iron wounds
                        (Fatigue or endurance) are burns as well as the normal damage. Any such
                        injury requires a MST s.t. to prevent being stunned. Such wounds require $ 2
                        \times $ the normal time to heal. </para>
                </sect4>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Duwan</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Culture Name - Duwan, Half-things, Halflings </member>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 3'5"/3'4" </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 50/55 </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Full Range </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Full Range </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Full Range </member>
                    <member>Stat Mods - PST -2 PAG +1 DEX +1 </member>
                    <member>Inherent Skills - Duwan have full control over the type of light that
                        their eyes are responsive to. Duwan have rank 0 in several stealth magics
                        (Avert Sight, Walk Unheard, Blend)</member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <para> Lithe and fast as a weasal is a typical description of the Duwan. They are small
                hard muscled people with (typically) long hair and saintly faces. </para>
            <para> In general they are a rarely understood or trusted race. They are thought to be
                thieves and murderers as well as smugglers, bringers of disease and general agents
                of chaos. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Rupa Kechil</title>
            <para> Rupa Kechil is a catch phrase that simply means ``skin-turner''. Most people
                assume that all skin-turners are all one species. There are more variations of
                skin-turners than can easily be listed. Simply take these notes as providing the
                average view of all the different subspecies. </para>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Culture Name - Rupa Kechil </member>
                    <member>Avg. Height - NA </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - NA </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - NA </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - NA </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - NA </member>
                    <member>Stat Mods - NA </member>
                    <member>Inherent Skills - Shapeshifting </member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Description</title>
                <para> The names, the history, and the cultures of the shapeshifters are a mystery.
                    What little is known indicates that some skin turners organise themselves along
                    clan or totem lines. There are several animals known to be associated with the
                    changers. </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Tiger Harimau</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Bear Bidok</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Boar Jantan</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Wolf Anjing</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Cheetah Mallini</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Eagle Akila</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para> For as long as Tanah has had a history shapeshifters have been a part of it.
                    In the myths and histories they generally show up as evil mages or children
                    stealers. Only rarely is a shapeshifter portrayed in a positive light. </para>
                <para> It is believed that the shapeshifters hide within whatever culture they are
                    born into. It is said that there is a greater form of shapeshifter which acts as
                    a governer in each loosely knit clan. These are given the title Rajah. It is
                    written that the Rupa-Kechil have a sign language called Sift-Rak and that there
                    is no written language per se but many changers use pictographs of the sift-rak
                    in order to convey a message. </para>
                <para> Some of the following are the typical variations in shapeshifter sub-species: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lunar Linked This is your typical run of the mill shapeshifter. They
                            are able to shapechange with variable success dependent on the phase of
                            the moon. They are most easily damaged with Silver and Magic.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Totem Aware This subspecies is capable of controlled shape change into
                            a normal ({\it i.e.} Non-Magical) version of some totem animal. The
                            changer can shapechange into, communicate with, and sometimes summon the
                            totem species. The term ``totem'' does not mean that the changer
                            worships the species in question. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Totem Linked This sub-species is linked to their totem animal. In
                            other words, all changers of this race have a ``familiar'' of the same
                            species as their totem. The gift of changing is conferred by the
                            presence of the link between familiar and changer. Totem-linked changers
                            are faster at their changing but the loss of the familiar can have very
                            bad effects on the changer's personality and skills for some time
                            afterward. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Dream Dancers Dream dancing involves trancing in order to project a
                            dream self that shapechanges as necessary. The dream self has physical
                            existence and it's physical statistics are derived from the mental
                            statitistics of the changer. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Kurrock</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Avg. Height - 4'6"/4'6" </member>
                    <member>Avg. Weight - 140/135 </member>
                    <member>Skin Color - Chalky white </member>
                    <member>Hair Color - Usually dark brown to black. </member>
                    <member>Eye Color - Black. </member>
                    <member>Stat Mods - PST +2; PAG -2; PEN +1; PSI -4; </member>
                    <member>Inherent Skills - Kurrock are naturals at feats involving physical
                        strength (DF +2). In addition they are able to directly able to convert
                        mental fatigue into physical fatigue. </member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <para> Kurrock are truly the most frightening fighters and drinkers around. They tend to
                get a reputation for just those things as a result but in reality, Kurrock are also
                skilled artisans, mechanicians, and miners. </para>
            <para> They are intense and focused , which makes them a subject of unease for most
                humans. They rarely get distracted and have a strong scorn for those that do. </para>
            <para> Despite their low PSI they seem to excel in producing weapons and tools that are
                almost magical in quality. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tairganik</title>
            <simplelist>
                <member>Race Name - </member>
                <member>Avg. Height - 6'1"/5'11" </member>
                <member>Avg. Weight - 200/170 </member>
                <member>Skin Color - Olive </member>
                <member>Hair Color - Black to Dark Brown </member>
                <member>Eye Color - Light colors </member>
                <member>Stat Mods - PST +1, PEN +1, PAG +1, PSI -4, MST +1, MAG +1 </member>
                <member>Inherent Skills - Their sight extends somewhat into the IR range which
                    allows them to differentiate between reds much more than most. </member>
            </simplelist>
            <para> In general Torgans are a tall ( 6'1" Male and 5'11' Female) race of olive skinned
                individuals. Dark of hair (Black to dark brown with rare auburn ) with light eyes
                and Pronounced jawbones and Bicuspids. Eyebrows tend to arch toward the edges of the
                face. Ears are usually elongated and lobeless. </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Erlani Culture</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Pocket Personality Sketch</title>
            <para>The typical Erlani is independent, practical, and polite but earthy. Not polished
                or likely to give anything other than well earned praise. They love good
                craftmanship, especially in wood. They tend to be hedonistic and ascetic as the
                situation demands. </para>
            <para>They rarely work in groups of more than two and they never, ever appreciate being
                told what to do by someone other than a priest or holy man. They can cooperate on
                the big tasks but not the small. A Erlani may agree to aid in a major group effort
                but each party will work on their piece of it and expect no unwanted offers of
                help.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> The Erlani have few of the more common metal ores. The island is volcanic and has
                some very interesting mineral and gem deposits. Spinels and Tourmalines being
                common. There are some good orchards and the land is fairly fertile even for a
                volcanic region. Pearls, Coral, and Shell are common adornments. </para>

            <para> Some of the Island corals also have multiple uses in magic castings. Few metals
                are available. Obsidian and Onderine are notable structural materials. Some small
                amount of Targs metal is available. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Onderine is the fibrous exudate of the Erlan dragons. It is fire and
                            stain resistant and as resistant to damage as studded leather except
                            that it provides no protection against crushing. It is nearly
                            trunslucent so it is often worn as overclothing. It is often used in
                            making rope or twine.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Targ's Metal is a amalgam derived from dragons eggs exposed to heat
                            for long periods of time.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Sisal Fiber A simple fiber derived from the Conbine plant. It is used
                            in making rope and a heavily narcotic pipeweed.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Tiger's eye Coral A green and yellow coral used in divination spells
                            and sorceries..</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para>The technological levels are very mixed. The Erlani are limited to stone age
                materials but with many skilled mages. The craft of construction is very advanced.
                Building is typically done with obsidian, flint and basalt.</para>
            <para> Optics are well developed. Many colored glasses and some magically active glasses
                have been derived. Knives and other edged implements of glass are actually fairly
                common. </para>

            <para>Weapons technology is limited to some basic staves and hand to hand combat. Though
                they do have ship based ballista and are very familiar with its use. Throwing sticks
                are in common use for hunting.</para>
            <para>Medical technology is very heavily dependent on magery.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para>The Erlani magic is a very educated version of shamanistic wizardry. They have
                only had natural materials to work with yet most magic using Erlani have a very
                clear concept of magic theory (Thenaen based)</para>
            <para> An Erlani views the world as a series of conflicts that combine to form balances.
                They actually understand equilibria of elemental forces. Thus a storm is merely a
                necessary ``ripple'' in the balance.</para>
            <para>Interesting enough they view their shapechanging as a attempt to alter a balance
                and reach a different state. Man is human only so long as his elemental and other
                forces are in balance. When he drives himself man can achieve a different state such
                as cat. Of course, manipulating this balance can be dangerous since the changed
                individual may lack the discipline to alter the balance again.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para>Hunting and fishing are very common. Gardening tends to be very simple (Sow and
                Come back later). The island, while hazardous, does support its population well.
                There are many stands of wild Breadfruit, Papaya, Coconut, and Redfruit. Wine made
                of Papaya and Redfruit are common.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Clothing</title>
            <para>The clothing of the Erlani tends to be a simple vest of leather or ondurine, short
                trousers with a tie up front, a pair of sandals, and a sash belt to cover the top
                edge of the pants. Cloaks are often worn against the rain. Knotted rope shoulder
                sashes are much prized for the skill in knotwork they represent.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para>The Erlani are a very open people among themselves. In order to survive they have
                had to overcome almost every predjudice they have held. As a result, they tend to
                honor idependence above most other things. At least when they can be independent
                they make the most of it. Teamwork is never discussed, just done as quickly as
                possible to get it over and done with. This does not mean that they dislike groups
                of people, they just prefer not share tasks.</para>

            <para>They also understand and encourage curiousity. Nothing strange is to be ridiculed.
                If someone asks a question it is answered. Some believe that the curiousity is
                inherited from the cat based changers.</para>
            <para>They have no nudity or sexual taboos. In addition their understanding of money is
                limited to a knowledge that it is useful and was very important to their
                ancestors.</para>
            <para>They have few formalisms for weddings or divorce. Polygamy is practised in both
                male and female centric forms. Divorce is often a matter of simply leaving the
                unwanted individual's goods out on the stoop.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para> A very bizarre blend of idiomatic Kaliphan, Family Thenaen, and Siftrak hand
                gestures. The written form of the language is mostly written Thenaen with some of
                the Siftrak glyphs for animal related concepts</para>
            <para>Literacy is common though the Craft-men of the monastery do the most reading and
                writing. Writing is kept up as a religious duty more than out of any great secular
                need.</para>
            <para> The language uses many a or aa sounds. With some flowing ae or aea combinations
                from Thenaen. A player attempting an Australian accent will probably get pretty
                close.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Vocabulary and Grammar</title>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Crafter - Shipsman,Sailor, Leader or learned man. </member>
                    <member>Lubber - Disbeliever, ungodly </member>
                    <member>Dragon Eyed - Crazy, Holy </member>
                    <member>Jailbird - Oldtimer of the first ship, Incredibly independent of thought </member>
                    <member>Jailhead - Too independent of thought, stubborn. </member>
                    <member>Mate - A man </member>
                    <member>Sheel - A women </member>
                    <member>Fairsail - Pretty good, Excellent </member>
                    <member>Dragon Taken - Stuck in animal form </member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para> The religion is very independent. There are many totems that may be appealed to.
                Each of the Erlani tends to worship a specific one because they feel that that totem
                more closely expresses their nature than any other. This may be more than wishful
                thinking, many tend to send their respect to the totem they find simplest to
                shapechange to</para>

            <para>Individuals who are known to have a specific favoured form and worship that forms
                totem are known as having a "True Totem".</para>
            <para>The totems are all related to the god of the corresponding shapechanger
                clan.</para>
            <para>
                <simplelist>
                    <member>Harimau - Tiger </member>
                    <member>Bidok - Bear </member>
                    <member>Jantan - Boar </member>
                    <member>Anjing - Wolf </member>
                    <member>Mallini - Cheetah </member>
                    <member>Akila - Eagle </member>
                    <member>Nijaka - Osprey </member>
                    <member>Varahawn - Dragon </member>
                    <member>Thisin - Dolphin </member>
                    <member>Dravanor - Dragon </member>
                </simplelist>
            </para>
            <para>In addition they have deified their sailor ancestors. The holy books are the logs
                of the three ships that brought them to the island. Priests, also called Captains,
                are trained in all of the sailing and leading arts. No Erlani would call himself
                captain until he had been acknowledged a skilled sailor and, as described in fist
                diary of Captain Yolanna, ``a just and fair judge as well as a true spiritual
                guide''. The priests together constitute the Council of Captains, a body that has
                some limited ability to ensure their wishes are carried out. Mostly with the older
                Erlnai, the youths can't sit still long enough to hear pronouncements.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Myths</title>
            <para>There are many myths and tales centering around the wreck of the ships and the
                subsequent taking of the island</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>History</title>
            <para> The first ancestors settled the island some 200 years ago when a set of three
                ships carrying a mixture of Thenaen mages and merchants, some 600 slaves captured by
                the Kalifate during a revolt, and some settlers (mostly Rupa Kechil) ran aground on
                the barrier reef surrounding the Island.</para>
            <para>Due to a few small problems (slave revolt, lizard attacks, storms, eruptions,
                etc..) the initial repair of the craft was delayed. Many of the shipbuilding skills
                existed but no organized shipbuilding began until the council of Captain's decreed
                that some effort should be made to keep the sailing skills alive. </para>
            <para>Some 4 other ships were wrecked on the Reefs in the next two decades after the
                first landing. After that, changing shipping patterns and war left the Isle
                isolated. </para>
            <para>They have gradually developed into a broadly spread collection of diffuse
                communities. </para>
            <para>15 years after the settling of the isle a mage/changer named Targ discovered that
                the eggs of the dragonets could be comverted into a tough, springy metal via a
                simple but lengthy process. This metal, caled Targ's metal, is a standard building
                material for those items that must be built of metal (ships tools, and the
                like).</para>
            <para>13 Years later Ondur the Gray discovered the cloth that can be woven from the
                fibrous exudate in the dragon's lair.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para>The most important traditions focus on the recognition of a child and their
                totems. While their are no sexual taboos, heredity is very important and a great
                deal of work goes into dealing with the child's shapechanging or magery skills and
                whatever Craft skills they may have.</para>
            <para> A parent may state that a child is theirs to raise but if the child gifted in
                such a way that only one of the parents will be able to train them then that parent
                will have to train them. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para>Animal motifs are the most important imagery followed by sailing. These two motifs
                make up better than 95% of the art on the Isle.</para>
            <para>Especially favoured are songs/pictures dealing with deliverence from sea hazards.
                Also well liked are themes involving clever solutions to situations that threaten an
                individual's indepedence</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para> The class structure is complex and yet fairly sparse. Their are the many
                different individuals with their crafts (including Magery), Sailor-Priests, Weather
                Crafters, and the Council of Captains. Sailor Priests have overriding authority on
                their ship and some importance as holy men on land. Weather Crafters are important
                for the knowledge they hold. The Council of Captains is important because the
                Sailor-Priests that make up its membership are more enlightened than the
                run-of-the-mill Sailor-Priest.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure/Legal code</title>
            <para>Usually the law is enforced by group consensus.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Kalifate Culture</title>
        <para/>
        <sect2>
            <title>Pocket Personality Sketch</title>
            <para>Your typical Kalifate is flamboyant in play and taciturn in work. They are
                typically considered hot blooded, quick to anger, and quick to cool down. A murder
                of passion is far more likely for a Kalifate then one that is calculated. They enjoy
                beautiful music with a strong rhythm and tragic love stories.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Locale</title>
            <para>The Kalifate culture spans from the northernmost seacoast of the Maldevar coast
                all the way down to the edge of the Tarmanian plains. It is an area similiar in
                climate and terrain to the southern coast of Spain.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para>The Kalifate have a great bounty in both ocean based goods and fruit of the land.
                They have ships and good wood for ship building. There are figs, olives, grapes,
                fish, lotus, myrrh, and hemp.</para>
            <para>There is cinnabar, amber, coal, limestone, marble, and basalt. There is ample iron
                ore. Horses seem to thrive.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para>Steel and Bronze, simple dome ovens, heated baths, simple oil lamps, basic carts ,
                wagons, and buggys. Horseshoes, stirrups, simple looms.</para>
            <para>Medical technology is straight forward. A knowledge of bleeding, bandaging,
                cautery, and stitching is well spread but there is no knowledge of hygiene.</para>
            <para>The weapon technology is advanced with breakfront crossbows, spears, rapiers,
                daggers, capes, and light lance.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para>The high magics of wizardry are known as well as sorceries. Mages are tolerated
                but often viewed with suspicion. Priestly magic is trusted and encouraged. There are
                several magic cults based on the worship of the Lady in her maiden or hag modes.
                These are viewed with some suspision.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para>The Kalifate as a group are accustomed used to living in a fairly sparse
                environment. They tend to live in large estates called {\it Estanzia}. Each estanzia
                has its own fields, gardens and its own stock. Some estanzia, notably those near the
                ocean, have so called fish pens that are fed by the tides. Hunting is common,
                especially for birds.</para>
            <para>Children often do trapping and simple hunting. Fields tend to grow corn, grapes,
                and cotton. Most Estanzia have 100-200 adults and some outlying homes. Most have
                some woods within an hours ride for hunting. Many Estanzisa have trees planted in
                the center as well as a family "oasis".</para>
            <para>Trade tends to travel in large gypsy and trader caravans.</para>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para>Personal bravery is valued as is good horsemanship. Killing an equal opponent is
                considered a brave act, killing a lesser opponent is diminishing of the winners
                skill. Dueling is rarely to the death unless the opponent is equally skilled and
                there is no other recourse. More often a fight is to the humiliation, not death.
                Recklessness and Style are very important. A truly brave and able opponent may be
                awarded with the table de' muerte. Don't say "Su Madre". A noble woman is valued for
                her skill in riding, it is part of her dowry.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Language Tree</title>
                <para>The kalifate language is very similiar to spanish in flow and rythm.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Literacy</title>
                <para> Literacy is limited to priests, accountants, and the nobility. All woman know
                    how to read dance and musical notations. Priests keep track of the
                    history.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para>The Kalifate religion seems to be based on the Lord and the Lady but with strong
                cult leanings for each. There are many little signs that show the Kalifates leaning
                away from worship of the Lord and the Lady and more toward a cult of worship of the
                Lady.</para>
            <para>Religous observances are split among men and women. Usually men go to temple early
                in the morning and women go later in the day.</para>
            <para> Worship of the Lord refers to him as our Lord patron in addition there is a
                strong following for one of the fourteen caldes who meet with the Lord who brought
                with them promises of land and saftey to the people.</para>
            <para>--Names of the Caldes</para>
            <para>--there should be a name for the Estanzia owned by descendants of the
                Caldes</para>
            <para> There is also a third form of worship for the Steeds of the Lord and the Lady who
                are known as Rolan and Aphrodie.</para>
            <para> There are a series of strictures layed down to the fourteen Caldes. No blood
                should be spilled on a holy day, no set of single lovers shall be kept
                apart....</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para>All women must be trained to ride and to shoot crossbows.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para>Two thirds of Kalifate society is involved directly or indirectly with some sort
                of cult. The cult may be something as innocous as a religous meeting group or as
                sinister as the El Tigre hunting club.</para>
            <para>Several other cults: there are two women only religous cults of which very little
                is known, one is known as the moon maidens and the other is called the Lady's
                Hand's.</para>
            <para>Descent is reckoned through the female line. So the children of the noble mothers
                and common fathers are born noble. Childern of noble fathers and commoner women are
                born one grade below that of the father</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para>The titles of Priests and Priestess are typically variations on the theme
                "reflected lights".</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Tairganik</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para> Probably one of the most sophisticated races technologically, the Torgans have
                the beginings of a true steel based economy. THey have many skilled mechanicians and
                and understand much of basic physics. Simple steam engines, Lanterns, Screws and
                levers are quite common. Metal springs are known as are simple mechanical dart guns.
                The use of a simple smoke powder is well known and so is the use of Naptha. Water
                clocks and a standard set of weights and measures. Surveying and road building are
                well honed skills. Plumbing is a known quantity as is composting sewage. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Both hunters and farmers. Their hunts tend to be of a communal type. Well
                advanced in farming and erosion theory. Generally comfortable with grains and root
                crops as well as fruit orchards. Vine crops are also very common - Especially wine
                grapes and climbing melon. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para> Torgans value bravery, skill and beauty. They are much given to song and music.
                Generally they will hold a singer or harper inviolate unless the harper blasphemes.
                They particularly honor bravery evidenced by self sacrifice and favor tragic and
                loving songs. Kinships are reckoned by descent through the female and are very
                important to Torgans. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Language Tree</title>
                <para> The Torgan language is not Orcish as would be expected from their appearance.
                    It is a fairly formal latinesque language. It shares some common roots with the
                    elven tounge spoken today. In particular it uses the older elven phrases for
                    special names and formal phrases. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Literacy</title>
                <para> Literacy is restricted to Women, Seers, Mages and scribes. Fairly widepread
                    but with definitive degrees of literacy between various classes. Military
                    leaders often learn a basic battle language called Habaksa. A mixture of old
                    Sift-Rak and written symbols derived from hand motions. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Writing Forms</title>
                <para> They use a stilted and formal runic language. Shares some traits with written
                    Bitadari and Dwarven. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Vocabulary and Grammar</title>
                <para>
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>ambassador Legatus </member>
                        <member>Yes Sertae </member>
                        <member>No Non </member>
                        <member>Hand Manus</member>
                        <member> Scout Konsilum</member>
                        <member>Trooper Katern</member>
                        <member>Hand Leader(Ldr of 5) Praetor</member>
                        <member>Lance(Ldr of 50) Sarisanar</member>
                        <member>Ldr of 100 Centurion</member>
                    </simplelist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para> The Torgans believe in the Nadir or fates, and a pantheon of gods reminescent of
                Roman and Syria. They are fairly pious and hold most reverence for the father and
                mother of the gods. </para>
            <para> Each household rests their fortunes with a founding spirit and each legion
                believes themselves to be the incarnation of their totem. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para> Names and Naming traditions are a major part of Torgan life. There is a use name,
                a true name, a house name, and a fame name. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Command</title>
                <para> The command structure of the Torgan legions is fairly complex. The complexity
                    is not due to their chain of command this is actually fairly simple, it is due
                    to the additional layer of cultural interaction and training. </para>
                <para> The Chain of command goes in the following order: </para>
                <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
                    The Senate Council
                    |
                    |
                    V
                    The 13 Legions ---> The High Battle Masters
                    |
                    |
                    V
                    Kinturions ( Leader of 1000 )
                    |
                    |
                    V
                    Centurions ( Leader of 100 )
                    |
                    |
                    V
                    Sarisani ( Leader of 50 )
                    (Lance Leader)
                    |
                    |
                    V
                    Praetor ( Leader of 5 (hand) )

]]>

</programlisting>
                <para> Each of the 13 legions actually varies in number between one thousand and six
                    thousand troopers or Katern. Each of the legions is noted for a particular
                    specialty , usually related in someway to the legion totem. </para>
                <para> The 13 legions are : \begin{itemize} \item [The Auric Dragon] The Very Best
                    \item [The Crystal Pheonix] Strategists and Tacticians \item [The White Wolf]
                    Scouts and Hunters \item [The Black Courser] Mounted Lance \item [The Red Bear]
                    Shock Troops \item [The Scarlet Hynd] Runners and Mappers and Signalers \item
                    [The Argent Pard] Acrobatics and Climbing \item [The Shadowed Falcon] \item [The
                    Wolverine Bronze] Engineering \item [The Verdant Griffon] \item [The Nameless]
                    \end{itemize} </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Routine</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Arms</title>
                <para/>

                <sect4>
                    <title>Trooper</title>
                    <para> \begin{verbatim} Full Leather Cuirass, Bracers, Large Shield Short Sword
                        R2 Running R2 Javelin R2 Dagger R1 Hvy Crossbow R2 Large Shield R2 Armoured
                        Move R1 \end{verbatim} </para>
                    <para> \subsubsection{Squad Leader} \begin{verbatim} Chain and Leather, Bracers,
                        Large Sheild Short Sword R3 Running R2 Javelin R2 Dagger R1 Hvy Crossbow R2
                        Large Shield R2 Armoured Move R2 Mil Sci R1 Horsemanship R1 Signaling R1
                        \end{verbatim} </para>
                </sect4>

                <sect4>
                    <title>Scout</title>
                    <para> \begin{verbatim} Light Leather, Bracers, Small Sheild Short Sword R2
                        Running R3 Swimming R1 Tracking R1 Small Shield R2 Javelin R2 Dagger R1
                        Armoured Move R3 Signaling R1 \end{verbatim} </para>
                </sect4>

                <sect4>
                    <title>Century Leader</title>
                    <para> \begin{verbatim} Improved Plate(+8), Bracers, Large Sheild Short Sword R3
                        Running R2 Javelin R2 Dagger R1 Hvy Crossbow R2 Large Shield R2 Armoured
                        Move R4 Mil Sci R5 Horsemanship R3 Signaling R1 \end{verbatim} </para>
                </sect4>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Outfitting</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Theory</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Thenaen Culture</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> The Thenaen culture is limited to a fertile but small set of islands called,
                appropriately enough, the Thenaen Islands. The area is rich in good soil, jewels,
                gems, and the bounty of the sea. </para>
            <para> The trade currents of both the south and north lead to Thenae, though the
                northerly current subsides to deep water before reaching the islands. The trade
                currents, combined with the volcanic nature of the region, provide for a great
                variety in the flora and fauna of the ocean. </para>
            <para> There is little in the way of iron ore. The Thenaens depend on two very light
                metals called {\it Limena } and {\it Taen}. Both are ill suited for sword blades but
                useful for structural tasks. </para>
            <para> Most of the islands are high mana areas. Almost all of the major clans have a
                meeting house or demense in a high mana area. </para>
            <para> The Thenaens depend on wind power to provide them with much of their basic energy
                needs. Windmills and windturbines as well as water turbines are common. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para> A strange combination of magic and mechanics the Thenaens have a good knowledge
                of leverage and simple engines such as windmills. They have almost no knowledge od
                the use of beasts of burden and thus lack much of the attendant skills. Little or no
                leather craft. No ability to make steel. </para>
            <para> \begin{itemize} \item[General] \item[Medical] \item[Weapon] \end{itemize} </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para> \begin{itemize} \item[General] \item[Medical] \item[Weapon] \end{itemize} </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Language Tree</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Mapping</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Dialects</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Literacy</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Writing Forms</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Sounds</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Vocabulary and Grammar</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Religion</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Cosmology</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Deities</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Myths</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>History</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Wedding</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Bedding</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Birthing</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Battle</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Other</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Rites and Rituals</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Religious Norms</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Symbolism</title>
                <para/>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Common Motifs</title>
                    <para/>
                </sect4>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Significant Numbers</title>
                    <para/>
                </sect4>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Art</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Architecture</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Leadership</title>
                <para/>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Stated</title>
                    <para/>
                </sect4>
                <sect4>
                    <title>Actual</title>
                    <para/>
                </sect4>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>Making the Laws</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Enforcing the Laws</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Ownership of Goods</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Land</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Male and Female Roles</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Church and State</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Death by Suicide</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Death by Anothers Hand</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Death in Self Defense</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Outfitting</title>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Shan Culture</title>

        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para>Ponies, Iron, Glass </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Generally there is a strict division of labor: The women gather vegetables and
                grains, handling the normal moving chores and directing the times and methods for
                the worship of the Sun. </para>
            <para> Men are active hunters and fishers, building stone weirs that bring in a good
                amount of fish. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para/>
            <sect3>
                <title>The "Great Game"</title>
                <para> Among the Shan there is one theme that is found throughout the culture: The
                    believe that they have been put on the land as a test and a game. Each Shan,
                    woman or man, has their own "Magic". For each, this resides in both the person
                    and the tools they use. </para>
                <para> The great game demonstrates to all this magic and keeps one prepared for
                    "what comes after". A typical part of play is to count coup by attacking another
                    in such a way as to demonstrate the attacker's skills while making the defender
                    look foolish. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Kinship</title>
                <para> All of the same generation are brother and sister. If they are actually
                    siblings of your own parents, they are referred to by their ages. If they are to
                    young to have gone through the comng of age ceremony then they are all just
                    "timsa" or younglings. </para>
                <para> Parents are referred to by father and mother but all others are simply "kiha"
                    or older relatives. </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Near History</title>
                <para> The Shan were originally nomadic wanderers. Dependent upon their ponies and
                    their skills as hunter - gatherers. Approximately twelve generations ago the
                    Shan settled on a sheltered and almost inaccessable set of plateaus. Until
                    recently these plateaus provided for their daily needs. Around four years ago,
                    as a result of an earthquake, several ares of the lowland gained access to the
                    plateau. Among them were the lands of the Kargans, known to the Shan as "Ugly
                    Talkers". </para>
                <para> The councils of each lodge have decided to send out many scouts to determine
                    the best path to use in order to escape from the Kargan. </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics and Warfare</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military Structure</title>
            <para> Structure, what structure ? This is a purely cooperative society. </para>

            <sect3>
                <title>Command</title>
                <para> Usually given, at the appropriate time, to the person best able to handle the
                    situation. In enemy territory he who knows the land best is often it. Of course,
                    they can always ask for advice from a more experienced warrior. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Arms</title>
                <para> General weapons among the Shan are simple. Steel daggers, Horse Bow, Bolas,
                    Whip, Net, and Javeins, and Spears. </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Kurrock Culture</title>
        <para> Kurrock are very hard to figure as a culture simply because they are so directed
            towards creation and artisanry that the have little time for politics. Skill in ones
            chosen field is what rules. Such are the tastes of Kurrock that all will agree who does
            what better than whom. If you ask in a village, who is your best warleader they will all
            agree. If you ask them who is the best smith they will agree. </para>
        <para> They spend much of their time improving themselves. They practice continually and
            contests of a monthly nature are not unheard of. All Kurrock want to be known as being
            the very best at something. </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> Kurrock tend to settle into regions of rich mineral deposits and care less for
                the aboveground fertility of the land than most races. Iron and coal as well as the
                precious metals tend to be their favorite materials. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Kurrock tend to farm both below and above ground.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Duwan Culture</title>
        <para> The Duwan are a very small group and fairly little is known about them. They
            generally have roundish and clear bright eyes, Furry feet , and a good appetite. There
            is a tendency towards good lying/ storytelling in the culture. </para>
        <para> One of the strangest things about Duwan is that some goodly number of their
            population often go on walkabouts. The walkabouts are rarely short. An interesting
            sidenote is that because Duwan seem to be rather careless of most others' property
            rights other than their own their need to collect mementos of their travels has
            contributed to their reputation as thieves. </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> Usually they settle in areas that have enough farming land and some iron ore.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para> Most Duwan settlemnents are fairly low on the technical end, but they need
                little. If they do set out to get tools they are often attracted to the intriguing
                rather than the useful. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para/> 
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> They tend to have a fairly sophisticated farming setup. Most food is grains and
                rootstocks with some of the simpler meats such as fish </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para> Duwan value thrift and cunning. Orderliness is a desireable trait and well
                thought of. Courtesy and style are foremost in most duwan minds. They care well for
                their own and care little for the tall folk. Not disdain, just disinterest. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para> Duwan speak Duwan. They rarely use trade talk. Most can read and write in Duwan.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para> </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para> Duwan traditions and rituals very from village to village and hutch to hutch. In
                most cases , holidays are caused by events of local noteriety and little else.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para> Most actual ruling is that of self rule combined with detailed traditions.
                Usually there is a judge or elder to interpret the laws as necessary. The Duwan
                truly believe that "There taint na sech ting as a fraa lunch", with the corallary
                "'Cept dat which ya borra for y'self". </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Dalesmen</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> Fertile lands, good clays, coal and oil. Copper, Iron. Aliantha plants. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Grain and fruit growing as well as trade. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para> Patriarchal with a strong male rule. They value practicality, thrift and caution.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para> A very broadly spoken slow and low tongue similiar to welsh. All males are taught
                to read to rank 4 or more. No woman is taught to read beyond rank 3. They share a
                written runic form with the Vairmen. H\={o}tman means Headman. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para> Like many of the cultures of the region the men of the dale worship the Lord and
                the Lady. The dalesmen view the Lord as the master and the Lady as the subservient
                adjunct to the Lord. The Lord appears as a tall bald man with a hammer and an Axe in
                hand. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <para> The bride generally marries into an already established family and becomes the
                ``Least Wife''. She is called this until a newer wife comes into the family. </para>
            <para> Heavy incest taboos, no particular age taboos. It is a punishable offence if a
                woman expresses interest in a man. As a esult of their culture there are a large
                number of lesbian relationships. </para>
            <para> There are many traditions regarding the planting of crops and such. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para> Priests of the Dalesmen are bald and each carries and Adax (Hammer and Axe combo)
                They are each assigned two wives at their ordination. This is based on the belief
                that no man can comptemplate the Lord's will when burdened with wordly problems.
                They often act as judges for the whole community. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military</title>
            <para> </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Arsa'e</title>

        <sect2>
            <title>Locale</title>
            <para> The Arsa'e are found in the desert bowl surrounded by the Blood Mountains. It is
                a fairly ``wet'' desert in that there are a number of water sources flowing through
                or around it. Perhaps the closest thing in our world would be the Arizona or
                Colorado regions near the Colorado river. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> The Arsa'e are blessed with many riches of the earth. There is abundant amounts
                of many different clays, suitable for pottery. There are opal,turquiose,and pyrites
                easily available. There is sand and Soda lime suitable for glass. </para>
            <para> In addition there are a wide range of grains and fruits that grow wild, among
                them are peaches, apples, melons, wheat, corn, tobacco, sunflowers and wildrice. </para>
            <para> \begin{quote} There is plenty of gold and silver ores though they are not mined
                often. In addition there is a good quality iron available as the result of a large
                number of meteor strikes in the deep desert. \end{quote} </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para> The level of Arsa'e technology is impressive and unevenly spread. Glassblowing
                has been taken to a high art. Glass suitable for sophisticated bottles is routinely
                produced. Simple magnifying glasses have been seen in the hands of the Arsa'e but
                none have ever been taken from one. </para>
            <para> \begin{quote} Magnifying glasses are called ``Goddess Eyes'' or ``Gods Eyes''
                depending on the gender of the shaman blessing it. There are also powerful
                telescopes that are never shown to outsiders. \end{quote} </para>
            <para> Arsa'e builders have mastered the production of structural clay to act as
                structural beams such as ladder crossbars. The clay is also useful for producing
                millstones. </para>
            <para> The potters of the Arsa'e rival the finest of the potters of China. They are able
                to produce a wide range of fine pottery that graces almost every home. The kilns
                seem to be made of another type of clay. </para>
            <para> Weaving is well advanced. Both broadlooms and knitting are known. Cotton and wool
                are the most common materials. Dyes are brilliant and basic hues such as red, brown,
                black, yellow, purple, and a light blue. </para>
            <para> Leather working is usually only used to produce saddlery for the ponies they
                raise. </para>
            <para> Medically they are skilled at basic wound treatment, repairing cavities with gold
                and silver, supportive treatment and basic hygiene. </para>
            <para> \begin{quote} Light for nighttime is raised from another type of clay pottery
                that glows when warmed \end{quote} </para>
            <para> The Arsa'e have a sophisticated method of irrigation and terrace farming. </para>
            <para> Cooking is done in domed ovens (for bread), open fires (especially for ceremonial
                meals or celebration), solar reflectors (for every day dry cooking), and
                solar-follow crock pots (for everyday meals). </para>
            <para> Beds are typically hammocks. </para>
            <para> Steel is exclusively used for weapons or religious artifacts. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para> Magic is a part of every Arsa'e life. But they do not consider it magic. There
                are prayers for almost every major event in Arsa'e culture and each one is a small
                spell. The prayer for the rising of the bread actually helps the bread rise, the
                prayer for the granting of a boy child or a female child does influence the gender
                of the child to be born. </para>
            <para> What an Arsa'e considers to be magic are the Shaman great songs and dances: the
                summonings of the {\it Blessing Way} and the {\it Ghost Way}, the banishings of the
                {\it Dying Way}. All of these are the great magics and only a shaman can attempt
                such. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Arsa'e are farmers and hunters. The farming is dependent on the irrigation and
                terrace-culture techniques. The hunting mostly consists of the six-legged lizard
                called the {\it tyrik} or ``Little Dragon'' and mountain pronghorns. There are many
                smaller species that provide eggs and meat at various times. Fish are a rare
                delicacy. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para> The Arsa'e value harmony above all else. Outbursts of emotion in public are not
                considered part of the {\it Way}. A true Arsa'e accepts all that occurs with a quiet
                face. Anyone who displays anger in public is tainted by some spirit and must go to a
                shaman for a blessing or exorcism. </para>
            <para> As part of their desire for harmony they do not rush anything they do not have
                to. Conversations start with a long discussion of the weather and relatives before
                it ever gets to the actual topic to be discussed. </para>
            <para> Extra Notes to be dealt with </para>
            <para> Towns are designated as for war or for alliance clan groups and moieties
                (botherhoods) in pueblo acoomadtion units pit dwellings as comtemplation chambers
                semi-circular town regions farmers,weavers,potters,builders drummers,singers,dancers
                jewelry - Carnelian, Pyrite, turquiose Great craters throughout the region. Slave
                warriors ! Janizeros Domed or wall ovens Sacred Birds, raised for the royal religion
                permeates all aspects of life. Each peublo is a self contained religious as well as
                political unit. Snake dances and other hazardous dancers foot racing bullroarers
                head tattoos group expression of religion should be the opposite of the normal
                demeanor killing, even in self defense, causes one to become a member of the
                brotherhoods </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Vairman</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para> Tough, not plentiful woods. Tourmaline, opal, and sapphires. Silver, Mercury,
                Tin, and Lead. Wyvern, Beast hounds, Pards, Lerna. </para>
            <para> Aliantha plants (Heal-All). Grapes and a large apple like fruit that ferments up
                quite handily to form a nasty brew. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Technology</title>
            <para> Good steel working is fairly common. Mostly used for crossbows and large curved
                throwing and fighting knives. </para>
            <para> Wood working, basic oil lamps, some simple chemistry, very good dyes. </para>
            <para> Tin, Bronze, Brass and other small metal work is very good. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Magic</title>
            <para> They have several monasteries that provide the Star Mages and Shadow Mages used
                as judges for both the Dalesman and Vairman cultures. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
            <para> Raising sheep and lerna. Some trade. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Values and Kinship</title>
            <para> Equipartioned between male and female. Child is given the name of the parent it
                chooses on its 3rd birthday. </para>
            <para> Bravery and honesty are foremost amiong the virtues. To be graceful is the
                highest aesthetic virtue. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Language</title>
            <para> The vairman language is a broad mixture of a sharply spoken hispanic tongue and
                of a gaelic tongue. Tends to be very sing song or ``chanty''. Most vairman are
                literate in the basic symbols and handtalk. Only mages or totem holders are taught
                to read. The written alphabet is the same as that of the Dalesmen. The sounds tend
                towards k\={e}, s\={e}, la, t\={a}. \begin{tabbing} {\it Meaning} \= {\it Word} \\
                Tasela \> light woman \\ Tasel \> Pleasure Love \\ Melante \> Measure of Honor or
                interest \\ Hotman \> Headman \\ Chelket \> Sister \\ Maske \> rabble rouser \\
                Tolla \> Balance (revenge) \\ Berma \> Sick with hunting after pleasure \\ Kushla \>
                Brother or Sister in arms \\ \end{tabbing} </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Religion,Myths,and History</title>
            <para> The people of the Eyrie worship the Lord and the Lady. The Lord and Lady are a
                brother/sister/ fighter/hunter/lover combination. They are always potrayed as twin
                vairman dressed in the simplest of clothes . Both have long black hair of equal
                length. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Tradition</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Wedding</title>
                <para> When a couple decides to become lifemates there are several events including
                    a house raising and a land gifting. It is not unheard of for a vairman to marry
                    two women or vice-a-versa. Usually these double pairings involve two of the same
                    sex from the same family. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Bedding</title>
                <para> \begin{quote} Start young, start well \end{quote} It is believed that the
                    best lovers one can have when young is a cousin or closer sibling. Few unwanted
                    pregnancies occur. </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Other</title>
                <para> The concept of revenge or Balanace is well developed. It is rare that the
                    balance due any group or individual ends up requiring a life. </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Institutions</title>
            <para> A great deal of importance is attached to the exchange of knives or bracelets.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clergy</title>
            <para> Priest and Priestesses are always ordained in pairs. Usually a brother/sister or
                cousin/cousin pair are ``called'' together. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Art, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Politics</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Class Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Judicial Structure</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Legal Code</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Military</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Section1 Title</title>
        <para>An equation: <equation>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                    <mml:semantics>
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mfrac>
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">F</mml:mi>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mfrac>
                                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mfrac>
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                        <mml:mi>q</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                                        <mml:mfenced>
                                            <mml:mrow>
                                                <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi>
                                                <mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
                                                <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">B</mml:mi>
                                            </mml:mrow>
                                        </mml:mfenced>
                                        <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mfrac>
                            </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:semantics>
                </mml:math>
            </equation></para>
        <para>An inline SVG graphic: <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata>
                        <svg:svg xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="3cm" height="3cm"
                            viewBox="0 0 400 400">
                            <svg:g style="fill-opacity:0.7; stroke:black; stroke-width:0.1cm;">
                                <svg:circle cx="6cm" cy="2cm" r="100" style="fill:red;"
                                    transform="translate(0,50)"/>
                                <svg:circle cx="6cm" cy="2cm" r="100" style="fill:blue;"
                                    transform="translate(70,150)"/>
                                <svg:circle cx="6cm" cy="2cm" r="100" style="fill:green;"
                                    transform="translate(-70,150)"/>
                            </svg:g>
                        </svg:svg>
                    </imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <index/>
</article>
