h64878
s 00252/00000/00000
d D 1.1 00/12/08 09:40:44 jmochel 2 1
cC
cF1
cK29248
cO-rw-rw-rw-
e
s 00000/00000/00000
d D 1.0 00/12/08 09:40:44 jmochel 1 0
c BitKeeper file f:/Repository/BardicTales/ShapeShifters/Elves.xml
cBjmochel@devilmountain|ChangeSet|20001208143925|39592|56cfc6eb
cHdevilmountain
cK21065
cPShapeShifters/Elves.xml
cR678cdbbf
cV3
cX0x180
cZ-05:00
c______________________________________________________________________
e
u
U
f e 0
f x 0x1a1
t
T
I 2
The Fey are the children of Correlan. They include the Eldar and the Golden
Ones. They are all affected by the elf-bane, the metal of earth pure Iron. 
There are five types:

Faer-Han (Grey Elves)

6.5 - 8.5' tall . Light Build. Three Fingered and pointed ears.
Large slanted eyes and eyebrows. Grey, Silver or blonde hair. Tend to
be thinner. +5 to appearance. Pale skin.


+10 Power
+20 Vision
Str -5
Con -5
Dex +3
Agl +1
Aura +4
Drv -1
Int +3
Dsc +3

All grey elves have a gift (+30 to some sorceries) and no
weapons training.

All grey elves take a d4 (HTK) from touching Iron and also take
x2 damage from Iron weapons and must save versus willpower or be
stunned d4+4 cts. Grey elves cannot survive on this plane for longer
than a few weeks. They lose one point of constitution each week until
they reach 0 constitution, at which point they die.

Upon death Faer-Han fade away after five minutes and their
spirit becomes one with Corellan. They are creatures of AIR and LIGHT
and have no LIFE to them. DEATH spells do not affect them. The Faer-Han
serve Corellan in all things. They are immortal. 



DarHan (Droh)(Dark elves)(Punk Elves)

In all things the Droh are like the Gray elves but some take on
the appearance of dark hair, black skin, and black eyes.

+10 Power
+20 Vision
Str -3
Con -3
Dex +1
Agl +1
Aura +3
Drv -1
Int +3
Dsc +1

All Droh have a gift(+30 to some sorcery). +10% to long sword, +5%
to crossbow.

Droh are as Faer-Han in terms of treatment of Iron and our plane. In
sertvice they give worship to Kisoreth and the lord of Darkness. They
are creatures of AIR and DARK and have no life to them. Hel is a Droh.
Only forty still exist. They are immortal.



Ossar-Ey (Sea Fey )

4-5.5' tall. Medium Build( Never Heavy) ; Three fingered
(webbed) Pointed, large ears. Large slanted eyes. No eyebrows, greenish
dark hair, generally long and stiff ( Ossar ey hair dressers don't do
perms) Greenish skin and gold scales. Gills.

\begin{verbatim}
+10 Power
+20 Vision
-10 End
Str -1
Con -2
Dex +0
Agl -1
Aura +2
Drv -0
Int +2
Dsc +0
\end{verbatim}

30 % of the Ossar-ey have gifts. +10% with harpoon, +5% Irith.

Ossar-ey are as Faer-han with respect to Iron. Unlike Faer-han
they last up to ten minutes after death. Also, every hour that they are
out of water they lose one point of Con. When they reach 0 they die.
This can be avoided by spending a tenth of that time doused with water.
Ten minutes of water restores one point of Con.

The Ossar-ey worship little but perhaps Correlan and Mannanon
MacLir . They are creatures of LIGHT and WATER. They are the results of
magical/genetic experiments by Faer-han. They are immortal to a point.
Most Osssar-ey take the Long Path after 500 years.

Quentar (High Elves)

The high elves are much like humans. They have a lighter build,
pointed ears, and slanted eyes. The eyes are blue, green, or crystal
eyes. Hair is blonde, white, grey, silver, brown or red hair; Usually
the hair is thin and straight.


+2 Appearance. Pale skin.
+10 Perception
-5 end
+5 Pow
+10 vis
Str -2
Con -2
Dex +2
Agil +2
Aur +2
Drv -1
Int +1
Dsc +1.

Some 30% of the Quentor have a gift. (+30 to some sorcery ).
Quentor take but a d2 of damage upon contact with Iron and only take 1/2
again damage from weapon strikes. Quentor are attuned to this plane.
Upon death a Quentor will remain substantial for his or her Con in
hours before disintegration. They are creatures of AIR and LIGHT but
these are tinged with LIFE. They are truly aclimitized to the prime
material plane. They have lifespans extending beyond 4 centuries.

Sylvantar (Wood)

The Sylvantor are short (3-4'); Of very lightbuild. Three fingered ,
having large pointed ears. Large slanted eyes and eyebrows. Brown,
Black, Auburn or ( occasionally) white hair. Usually they have green
eyes though sometimes brownish black. Brownish skin. +3 App. +20
Perception +10 Vision -5 End Str +0 Con +0 Dex +4 Agil +4 Aur +0 Drv -3
Int -1 Dsc -1 Have sylvan gifts. (?????) +15\% Elven Bow.

Sylvantor are affected by Iron as Quentor are.





First Elder paused and a ripple shimmered across the assembly.

Mazientir of the Sword frowned as more and more of the fifth generation
stepped from the pattern into the meeting hall in Yris.  Yris's Conversation
Holders filled the balconies almost to the point of having to grow them
deeper into the Tree.  He hated being responsible for the Safe Speaking in
this cluttered, reality-bound place on the Prime Agreement.

His will expanded out to include the whole hall and as the last of the fifth
generation that were expected stepped into the hall he sealed the Wards
protecting the room.  He sensed no Malice, nor Danger in the minds around
him.  He searched for and could not find any servants of the Wanderer.  Of
course, if the Wanderer chose to be here, then he was here somewhere.

He re-directed his primary view to the branch that the First Elder were
standing on.  He was joined by several other Elders- and the young Warden -
from the Thalionsaer family- that was sent by the Second Power to this
Agreement to monitor and integrate and express the will of the Second Power.
He looked at him with undisguised curiosity.   He was accelerated in
experience far beyond his temporal range.  He de-focused and studied the
intentions in the room and the ward as the First Elder began speaking again.

"The Balance."  A stir of thoughts and concerns filled the room.  "It is...
in question. "

An audible gasp ran through the room.  Every being in the room stood still
and directed their aura up at the First Elder.  "As you all know the beings
of the Second Power integrated the Balance as a primary thread in the
conversation of the Prime Agreement.  This was aligned on by all the
Secondaries in all the Prime Agreement Verticals that are translatable from
this Agreement."

A young Quentar- one of the sixth generation- sent an interrogative pulse to
the First Elder, he acknowledged it with a flick of thought.  "Elders- then
how can it be in question?  There has been no unraveling, and no force has
been generated contra to that thread!  What you are saying is impossible
unless the Victim is about to be Released- and of that there are few signs.
"

Waves of disapproval rose at the young Quentar's rude, and hasty question.
The First Elder frowned, but the young Warden floating by the First merely
smiled and nodded at the young Quentar.

"Nonetheless.  The Keeper of the Voice of the Secondaries reports that more
and more it is forced to intervene, and soon it will reach its capacity to
do so.  It has been fundamental to this agreement since before time but it
has only become vocalized in the latest iterative transformation at the
stilling of the Second Power 'Kratchelov'"

He paused and a visual representation of the Pattern of the All-World
appeared.  "However, with the exiling of the Shared Voice, the disruption of
Kratchelov's servants, and the resurfacing and unbinding of many of the
Bound Voices it is weak and its conversation threatens to submerge.  We must
therefore take hasty, pre-emptive action to intervene.  Over the several
years more and more of you will be trained to integrate with the Prime
Agreement to add your voices to the Voice.  "

Mazientir smiled grimly as he felt intention and purpose rise from the
gathered Faer-Han.  Then he felt a tickle in the back of his mind, the feel
of something slithering against the ward.  He directed his mind towards it
just a second before he felt the Danger in doing that, and then the Fire
Raver consumed him.

***




off the cuff answers without regard to what the GM thinks:
 
The Elvish Hierarchy is a not that straightforward. The common elven world-view is something like this:
 
Gray-elves (Air-Light), High-elves (Earth-Light), and Wood-elves (Air-Heads) appear to have 
been designed directly by Correllan as they are now (OK, so some fine-tuning 
has occurrred over time). Sea-elves appear to be the result of a Corellan 
approved/aided change (Water in place of Air)  to Gray elves. The Golden-Ones 
were the result of an unopposed but unsanctioned change to Fire-Earth-Light from Earth-Light
in some High Elves. Green-Elves are the result of interbreedings between Sea-Elves and 
other elven races (mostly high). These occur indecently often (at least 7 times in the last 
3000 years !).
 
Sorcery is the elvish common denominator. All the elves appear to be strong (instinctive) sorcery 
users. Almost all elves use some sort of sorcery every day. Wood-Elves are the strongest natural 
sorcerers among the elves.
 
Of the more structured magics, Naming is in common use by the Faer-han and some 70-80% of High-Elves.
With some 20-30% of High-elves using human wizardries.
 
My basic take is that the early period Golden-Ones saw them using sorceries and naming, and then creating 
some things that we would recognize as human style wizardries. They were very big into resurrecting  the 
previous epoch's technology.
 
On a side note, I visualize naming as a very broad collection of skills dealing with the relationship of 
visualizations such as words, gestures, and materials to power patterns. A true master namer (of which 
I think only a few exist (= Labelas, Adonai, Sylvanus)  could create a new "feature" or "verb"  in a wizardry
power pattern by verbalizing with power. So to say that a elf is a namer delineates a broad range of 
possibilities. They may specialize in wizardry power patterns, racial mana-genetics, or any of a set
of skills that add/enforce structure on power. 
 
This to me is one step removed from the Draconic skill of languaging which seems to control the Draconic 
relationship to the environment via the dynamic ateration of the interface from either side. Elves typically only 
control it from environment's side. Ugh, me elf, you are now a new power pattern. Hello power pattern , I am 
a dragon, how would you like to communicate ?
 
Jim
 


Elven names are gener=tic descriptions of the way of being.
E 2
I 1
E 1
