<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/dbmathmlsvg.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>The United Confederation of Systems</title>
    <chapter>
        <title>Brief Description</title>
        <para>
        The Confederation of Systems, more commonly known as the Confederation or Confed, is a collection of solar systems and colonies banded 
        together for both defense and trade. There has been a concerted effort by the Confed to limit interference in the internal workings of the 
        actual systems.
        </para>
        <para>
        The Confed emcompasses a number of major racial groups. The Terrans and the various derivative races of {\it Homo Terra Prime} 
        constitute a major portion of the current population. The Alpha  Centaurans and the derivative races of {\it Homo Alpha Centauran 
        Prime} constitute the next largest group followed closely by the Proximans {\it Homo Proxima Prime}. There are no other known races 
        currently members of the Confed.
        </para>
        <para>
        The duties of the Confederation as a governing body are quite simple:  keep the peace {\em Between member systems}. To this end each system 
        donates a portion of its military services to the Confed as well as some monetary support.
        </para>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>The Three Legs</title>
        <section>
            <title>The Mechanized Infantry</title>
            <subtitle>The MI</subtitle>
            <para>The Mechanized Infantry is one the primary reasons for the continued existence of the Confederation in these troubled times. They constitute a package of deadly force on a highly mobile platform with the ability to perform everything from full scale assualts and armoured support to pinpoint actions in densely populated civilian areas.</para>
            <para>In the MI, there are no armchair officers. When the time to do some ground pounding comes around the officers are right there with their men. An officer in many respects is a very skilled individual simply because he must be able to direct the action and defend himself at the same time.</para>
             <table>
                <title>Table of Organization</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <thead>
                        <row><entry>Unit</entry><entry>Commanded by</entry><entry>Contains</entry></row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row><entry>The Corp</entry><entry>The Commander General (Marion Sutaken)</entry><entry></entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Legion</entry><entry>Legion Commander</entry><entry>10 Jump Battalions</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Battalion</entry><entry>Battalion Commander</entry><entry>10 Jump Divisions</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Division</entry><entry>Field Commander</entry><entry>10 Jump Plexes</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Jump Plex</entry><entry>Sargent Commander</entry><entry>10 Jump Squads</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Hand/Squad</entry><entry>Sargent</entry><entry>9 MI</entry></row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>
                The MI have a need for men or women that are tough, flexible and capable of learning. As a result they have raided jails for potential troopers as well as normal recruiting. If an confed citizen can pass 
                the examinations and initial training then he has a clean record. Any criminal record possessed up to that point is eradicated. By the same token the MI has a far more stringent set of laws and codes with 
                fairly harsh penalties. 
            </para>
            <para>
                All troopers enter a two year training program. This boot camp process is expensive but effective. They are exposed to a wide range 
                of technological skills and are given Bacterial Augmentation injections to improve response speed. 
            </para>
            <para>
                The MI get their name from the powered battle suits which they use almost to the exclusion of all other equipment. 
            </para>
            <table>
                <title>Specialized deployments of MI Suit</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <thead>
                        <row><entry>Name</entry><entry>Usage</entry></row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row><entry>Spook</entry><entry>Long range recon</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Scout</entry><entry>High speed recon</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Command</entry><entry>Battle coordination.</entry></row>
                        <row><entry>Marauder</entry><entry>Battle.</entry></row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>The Marshalls</title>
            <para>
                The Confederation Marshalls were established in the year 325 (CONFED) 
                as a civilian enforcement arm of the Confederation Council by 
                Confederation Governance Action 172-01/325 at the request of 
                Ex-Council Factor Dan Forest-Kell(Terra). Its duties are fairly 
                simply stated: To act as direct representatives of the Confederation 
                in any matter involving the enforcement of Confederation laws on a
                scale smaller than a full scale military action without regard to 
                planetary or spatial boundaries.  
            </para>
            <para>
                The Confederation Marshalls are direct representatives of the 
                Confederation Council and as such can request military action or 
                complete quarantine of a solar system. They are used as guards in 
                situations where military personell are not needed or are 
                undesirable.
            </para>
            <para>
                They are often involved in criminal investigation where a local 
                investigation would be the subject of some discomfort.
            </para>
            <para>
                The Marshalls have little or no access to spacecraft. They typically 
                use military craft or commercial transport, on which they travel at 
                no cost. In addition they are usually able to get access to most 
                government computer systems (within reason ) .
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Regulations</title>
                <para>
                Confederation Marshalls on duty are expected to be armed at all times and to carry their ID with them at all times. There are no "undercover" Marshalls. While there is no 
                standard armament, there is a strong push for the rokie to train and use a slug weapon. The reason seems to lie in the Terran wild west 
                origins of the Marshall concept.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Ranks</title>
                <para>
                    Ranks are very simple. ( Two points of status are required for each rank )
                </para>
                <table>
                    <title>Marshall Ranks</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <tbody>
                            <row><entry>Provo</entry><entry>A rooky - typically assigned to a senior Marshall.</entry></row>
                            <row><entry>1st Star</entry><entry>Attached to a specific region or beat .</entry></row>
                            <row><entry>2nd Star</entry><entry>Attached to a specific duty area.</entry></row>
                            <row><entry>3rd Star</entry><entry>Semi Attached - Qualified for Council Level diplomatique missions.</entry></row>
                            <row><entry>Lone Star</entry><entry> Direct council representative.. Picks his beat and reports in as necessary.</entry></row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>Unattached Marshalls have almost no salary. All of their normal 
                    expenses on duty are paid simply by their ID card. Charges accrue to 
                    the Confed  Council. They may commander equipment as necessary.</para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>The Council</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
        

    </chapter>

<!--    <chapter>
        <title>History</title>

        <sect1>
            <title>
            Pre-space
            </title>
                <para>
                The history of the Confederation is most properly the history of the Terrans. The Terrans were one of the primary forces behind the 
                formation of the Confederation. 

                The Terran History of the years immediately preceeding the year 2560 is found to have a nearly hysterical flavour to those used to reading the
                histories of less divided cultures. Most other cultures in the Confederation of Systems have a sharply defined predilection toward or 
                away from war. Few cultures have the ambivalence of a Terran towards violence.

                During the time period following the Second World War the world focused in conflicts around the two main super powers of the time period. With
                a strong technological lead over the Soviet Bloc, the USA spent a great deal of energy and influence in combatting any gains made by the Soviet
                Bloc. 
                </para>

                <segmentedlist>
                    <segtitle>
                    1969
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg>
                        NEIL ARMSTRONG SETS FOOT ON LUNA
                        </seg>
                    </seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1981
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> 1ST PATENT ISSUED FOR GENETICALLY ALTERED BACTERIA
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1982
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> FUSION BREAKEVEN WAS REACHED (R.I.T)
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1986
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> CHALLENGER SHUTTLE ACCIDENT
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1989
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg>
                        Berlin wall comes down
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                        Major instabilities within the Soviet Union
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1996
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Poland becomes a member of the EEC
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1997
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> First Joint US/Soviet Space mission
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1998
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Argentina announces first cases of what is later to be described as Andes plague
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    1998
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Low Temperature Superconductor (214\degree K) commercially available
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                </segmentedlist>

                    <segtitle>
                    1999
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Fairly minor economic hardship in many regions of the United States of America
                        </seg>
                        <seg> Increasing virulent strains of Aquired Immuno Deficiency virus surface
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                
                    <segtitle>
                    2000
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Two prominent Catholic church officials die in Boston and NYC of AIDS-2
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Israel claims total annexation of Lebanon.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Renewed hostilities between Mohawk nation and Quebec.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> France suffers from the explosion and destruction of the ``Super Pheonix'' reactor
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2001
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Costa Rica is purchased by the Nature Conservancy
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2002
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Japan announces successful cloning of Coelecanth
                        </seg>

                        <seg> General Electric establishes its own armed security force
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2003
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Long Island Blast - Detonation of Shoreham fission plant. accident ? 180,000 killed.
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2005
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> South American University of Ecological Engineering (SAUEE) established in Costa Rica
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2006
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Johannesburg established as only legal residence for whites in South Africa
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Desertification renders large parts of Somalia and Nigeria uninhabitable
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Korea is made a client state of Japan
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Anti-Fission Referendum Approved in the USA
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2008
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Discovery of Mirashi Sun Screen effect by Sanford Ezekial Jackl.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> First reconstruction of Tristamy 13 fetus
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Assassination of USA president Pat Schroeder.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Japanese/Korean team demonstrates cybernetic helmet hookup
                        </seg>

                        <seg> U.N. Research and observation base at tycho Brachae is established
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>


                    <segtitle>
                    2009
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> U.N. is asked to vacate N.Y. by USA.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> U.N. Establishes its Meeting site at Point 7, Antartica
                        </seg>

                        <seg> EEC begins to make all UN support payments as one unit.
                        </seg>

                                <seg> G.E. puts first Mirashi Sun Screen power plant online using black
                        box units supplied by Jackl Power Inc. Power plant comes on line from
                        Los Alamos, Texas.
                                </seg>
                    </seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2011
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> USA and Canada, acknowlegding a growing interdependence, agree to merge their current economic systems. USA agrees to go metric.
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2012
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> Quebec and California declare their independence of the ``NorAm Combine''
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

                    <segtitle>
                    2013
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> First offline run of white sands fusion plant
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

       </sect1>


        <sect1>
            <title>
            Fire Years
            </title>

                <segtitle>
                    2014
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> October : First L-5 orbiting station  ``Lagrange-Five'' made operational by NorAm Combine. Soviet aid accounts for 30% of labor and 20% of materials.
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>


                <segtitle>
                    2015
                    </segtitle>
                    <seglistitem>
                        <seg> December : Second L-5 orbital station made operational by U.N. Joint Technology Mission, SAUEE and Australian Mining concerns.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Guiseppe Lapilito demonstrates the first power armoured suit to a group of skeptical military procurement officers by walking through the Pentagon and into the office of the Secretary of the Army, uninvited.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Quebec Food riots
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Cray VMOP-40 put online at Socorro Research Center, New Mexico . VMOP = virtual memory optical plaques
                        </seg>

                        <seg> General Dynamics demonstrates the first prototype ``Screen-Shuttle''
                        </seg>

                        <seg> California is brought back into the NorAm Combine by use of Blockade.
                        </seg>

                        <seg> Soviet Secretary General Gosseyn is killed as a result of terrorist bombing. The ecological terrorist group ``Golden Monkey Wrench'' claims responsibility.
                        </seg>
                    <seglistitem>

            2021 Regular "screen shuttle" service between the earth and
            moon is established.
            2020 General Dynamics and SovMhD together offer screen shuttle service between Moscow, New York, Antartica, and Tycho Brachae. 

            2017 Darrel Kaven psychic research center is established in Santa 
            Barbara California.
            2024 Establishment of lunar penal colony "Selene" by NorAm Combine.
            2024 Montreal massacre 1,534 dead.
            2025 Sandoz starts marketing male and female contraceptive implants 
            based on non-abusive hormal regulation.
            2030 Mitsubishi unveils first commercially obtainable shuttle craft, the
            Infiniti-2.
            2040 Creation of Ares city on Mars.
            2055 The Federal Bureau of Intelligence is greated powers of 
            interrogation under the Clayton Counterterrorism Act. 
            2056 The L.A. Quake of '56. Richter 9.3. 
            2056 The Bureau of mental Health is established. The bureau is given 
            overriding control over all wards of the state. It also serves as a 
            deprogramming dept.
            2057 First commercial Organ bank is opened up.
            2059 ZPG Act places enforcement of birth limits in the hands of 
            the Bureau of Public Health. (Was Bureau of Mental health).
            2060 Serge - a radical environmental group , succeeds in 
            destroying 2 biological warfare research units. Resulting plagues
            kill 6 million.
            2121 Citing unpaid debts Argentina invades Chile against opposition 
            from NorAm and Chilean troops. War continues for 3 years before the 
            Belmopan Armistice is signed. 
            2123 Costa Rican Conservancy acquires Panama and Nicaragua. All three
            countries become subject to a Conservation Council government. In 8
            years both of the newly acquired regions become profitable and 
            develop one of the highest health and living standards. The region 
            is renamed the Conservancy States. 
            2125 Mexico attempts to invade Gautemala. NorAm funded Mexican forces 
            are defeated and disbanded in less than 6 months by Israeli Officered 
            U.N. forces. The NorAm Combine withdraws from the U.N. 
        </sect1>

        <sect1>
            <title>
            The Diaspora
            </title>
            2045 Launch of gauss jammer "Einstein" by L-5 society with 1221 volunteer colonists.
            2125 Launch of gauss jammers Dyson and Hawkings
            2026 Conservancy designed underwater biosphere ``Jerusalem II'' is 
            established by Israel in Mediteranean.
            2027 1st atificial factor humanoid produced by General
            MagnetoheteroDynamics, inc. (gmd)
            2130 First use of artifacts in mining operations off terra
            2136.0 1st contact between gauss jammer Einstein and Alpha
            Centauran manned probe Fir'A'Naun
            2138.3 Discovery of Mak'kasonar (Alphan) and Cagson (Terran)
            transition made possible by Centauran spacial mathematics and Terran 
            fusion technology. 
            2138.5 Arrival on Alpha of Transition Drive equipped Pinnance carrying
            Mak'kasonor.
            2138.7 Arrival on Terra of Transition Drive equipped Pinnance carrying
            Eli Cagson and his two sons. 
            2138.9 Transition Drive is put in the public domain by executive decree. 
            2139.4 Return of "Einstein " to terra.
            2139.6 Alphan Recording of the Destruction of the Gauss Jammer Hawkings by
            Proximan War vessels.
            2139.9 Formation of the joint alphan/terran coalition. 
            2140.8 Production of first military artificial factor humanoid "artifact" 
            for combat in proximan space.
            2139.7 Production of bacterial augmentation sera for terran troops. 
            2141 Rediscovery of the planet "Wicca"
            2143 Liberation and rediscovery of the planet "Elysia"
            2143 The battle " terragoth" marks end of triculture war. The ``Three 
            Suns Armistice'' lays down the foundation of the Confed council. 
            2044 Declaration of "artifact" non citenship by terra
            declaration of alphan / proximan aftifact citizenship
            2155 You are here \dots


        </sect1>


        <para>
        During this time period there was a gradual decline in the health of
        the economies of the two Blocs as well as in actual scientific rather
        than technological knowledge growth. In addition there was a marked
        increase in religous fundamentalism in both the US and abroad in
        various Islamic and Hindu countries. Both of the superpowers of the 
        time period tended to ignore the economic build up of other countries 
        except when their own immediate well being seem threatened. Certainly 
        , both countries had a great deal to worry about.
        </para>

        <para>
        As the technological wonders mounted in number and variety, so did the
        need for energy to grow and expand. Conventional sources proved
        insufficient and standard nuclear methods proved to be to dangerous.
        During this time period public confidence in conventional
        power sources was on the decline. 
        </para>

        <para>
        The stresses placed on some of the smaller countries by the three ``super powers''
        (EEC,Soviet Union, USA) caused many of the countries to form serious coalitions
        with similiarly inclined republics. Thus came into being the United Islamic States,
        sthe Indos Island States (Phillipines and Indonesia), and the loosley allied 
        Scandinavian Coalition (the Scandic).
        </para>

        <para>
        Multinational Corporations became commonplace as each country's industrial 
        complex bought into the financial structure of several others. Space travel 
        was almost an ignored project with only small bits of developement going on 
        at a relatively low intensity . 
        </para>

        <para>
        Other methods of energy production became standard. With the 
        discovery of a highly efficient technique for solar energy conversion 
        came an increased traffic flow between the planet and its moon.
        </para>

        <para>
        The smaller countries begin to use the U.N. as a fairly sophisticated 
        lever against both of the two super powers. The EEC, Israel, the 
        Islamic state coalition, and the republic of India are primary 
        supporters. in doing so they establish a fairly strong tradition for 
        the U.N. as a military force and the use of Israeli Officers as advisors. 
        </para>

        <para>
        Unrest over food shortages continued. in addition there was
        a slight resurgence of territoriality within the
        northwestern hemisphere.
        </para>

        <para>
        A small group of dedicated visionaries succeeded in secretly
        launching a colony ship from the sirius orbital station. the
        "Gang of l-5" was tried and convicted of treason. later
        pardoned as a result of public outcry.
        </para>

        <para>
        Exploration increased rapidly. all planets except Saturn and
        Jupiter are successfully landed upon.
        </para>

        <para>
        United Nations Standard units of Exchange become a standard 
        media of exchange for all but NorAm Combine and the Soviet Union. 
        </para>

        <para>
        Resource tensions cause the first major conflict of the 21st century, 
        the Brushfire war, which lasts for all of 13 days and renders goodly 
        portions of Somalia and the United Islamic Coordinate unihabitable. 
        The Iraqi valley oil fields are made useless by heavy fallout.   
        </para>

        <para>
        In the year 2046 a the lunar colony selene discovers the
        presence of a space craft landing site - over 2000 years
        old.
        </para>

        <para>
        In the early part of the 2050s there comes a long series of 
        conflicts in the middle European and South American arena 
        that feature major losses for each of the two super powers.
        </para>

        <para>
        During this time period the incarcerations begin. hundreds of thousands of 
        North American citizens are jailed for Un-American and Un-Canadian stances.
        "Proctors" become become overseers of public education. 
        </para>

        <para>
        World economic conditions worsen.
        </para>

        <para>
        The North American States experience the first net emigration of people 
        in two centuries.
        </para>

        <para>
        The Soviet Union switches over to the U.N. Standard of exchange and 
        agrees to adhere to U.N. Resource management restrictions. The 
        founder of Jackl Power Inc. , suffering from a terminal illness, 
        wills his fortune, his entire stock holding in Jackl Power (74\%) , 
        and his land holdings in upper New York State to the Mohawk Nation of 
        Quebec. The Mohawk Nation uses the money to finance the building of 
        the ``Red Jacket University of Power Engineering ''. In addition, 
        they begin one of the largest public relations campaigns in history 
        as part of an attempt to separate from the NorAm combine. 
        </para>

        <para>
        The Alphan 
        </para>

    </chapter>
-->

    <chapter>
        <title>The Races</title>
        <para>
        </para>
        <section><title>Terrans</title><para></para></section>
        <section><title>Alphans</title><para></para></section>
        <section><title>Proximans</title><para></para></section>
        <section><title>Artifacts</title><para></para></section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>The Cultures</title>
        <para></para>
        <section><title>Elysian</title><para></para></section>
        <section><title>Romani</title><para></para></section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>The Colonies</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>The Megacorps</title>
        <para>
        </para>
        <section><title>GMHD</title>
            <para>
                GMHD's work is focused within a group of 121 private and Confederation funded
                Research and Development Centers that perform materials engineering, systems
                engineering, biomedical research and Cybernetics for the military and civilian
                branches of the Confederation.
            </para>             
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Crime Groups</title>
        <para></para>
        <section><title>Black Sun</title><para>Interstellar crime network</para></section>
        <section><title>Nine Families</title><para>Terran mafia centered in South America</para></section>
    </chapter>
    
    
    <chapter>
        <title>The Sub-Cultures</title>
        <para></para>
        <section><title>Wicca</title><para></para></section>
    </chapter>
    

    <chapter>
        <title>Major Terran World Powers</title>

        <glosslist>
            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    The Conservancy
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                    <para>
                    The Conservancy is both a set of Terran republics and the governing body
                    that rules them. It is a quasi-mercantile organization funded by
                    controlled tourism and payment for its Terraforming services.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                    In land area it controls much of what is currently Mexico, Guatamala,
                    all the way down to Peru and Brazil. 
                    </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>

            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    NorAm Combine
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                The North Americam Combined States is the loose coalition of the 
                Mohawk Nation, the United States of America, Canada, and Greenland.
                </para>
                <para>
                While it has adopted the U.N. currency as a monetary standard the NorAm 
                Combine is not a member of the U.N.
                </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>


            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                United Islamic Coordinate
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>

           <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    The United Nations
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                    The largest single world organization on Terra. It is composed, in 
                    the main, of the EEC countries, the Soviet Union, Australia, and 
                    Israel. 
               </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>

        </glosslist>

   </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>Religious Organizations</title>

        <glosslist>
            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    Wiccans
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                    A semi-mystical coalition of churches derived from the pagan 
                    movements of the 1990s, the Unitarian Universalist and Humanist 
                    movements of the 2000s, and the New Bhudda movement of 2020.
                </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>


            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    Cestus Dei
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                    A result of the ``Fire Reformation'' of the Catholic Church and
                    vatican IIII, the Cestus Dei are a missionary organization derived 
                    from the original Society of Jesus. As the name implies, the Cestus 
                    Dei is a militant brotherhood/Sisterhood
                </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>

            <glossentry>
                <glossterm>
                    The New World church
                </glossterm>
                <glossdef>
                <para>
                    Moonies in space.
                </para>
                </glossdef>
            </glossentry>
       
        </glosslist>
    </chapter>
</book>




