<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- edited with XML Spy v4.2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Foliage Engineer (IT) -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd"[
    <!ENTITY tisland "Takeda Island">
    <!ENTITY iisland "Imperial Island">
    <!ENTITY ifamily "Imperial Family">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="F:\docbook-xsl-1.45\fo\docbook.xsl"?>
<book>
	<bookinfo>
		<title>Dal-Kon</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jim</firstname>
			<surname>Jackl-Mochel</surname>
		</author>
	</bookinfo>
	<chapter>
		<title>General Description</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Emperor Sunjuro in the Pond of Hirosawa</attribution>
			<para>The Moon in the Water, the doctrine of Mushin</para>
			<para>The moon has no intent to cast its shadow anywhere, nor does the pond design to lodge the moon: How serene the water of Hirosawa!</para>
		</epigraph>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Islands</title>
			<para>
            Dal-Kon is a volcanic archipelago with about 
            70% of its total land, most of which mountainous, covered with woodlands and 
            forest plantations.  Within the relatively small area of its land, Dal-Kon has three 
            climates - temperate, alpine and sub-tropical, and in most of is 
            regions it has four distinctive seasons.  Temperate regions, which occupy most 
            of its land, and also sub-tropical regions, enjoy relatively warm temperatures 
            and sufficient precipitation to enable a great variety of agriculture even though 
            rice is the primary food crop.
			</para>
        </sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Surrounding Seas</title>
			<para>
            The Seas are uniformly warm and life abounds. The reefs are treacherous and the 
            shoals sharply limit the paths of approach for boats. Despite this fishing 
            and kelp gathering are very common ways of making a living all along the seacoast.
			</para>
        </sect1>        
    </chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Flora and Fauna</title>
		<para>
		The Dal-Kon soil is incredibly fertile. This seems to be a direct side effect 
		of the runoff from various volcanoes. It is especially good for rice and mulberry 
		bushes as well as a variety of fruit trees (Cherry, pear, apple, and plum).
		</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Flora</title>
			<para>
			Silk culture makes up the majority of the exportable goods that leave Dal-Kon. Cultivating the 
			mulberry and the silk worms are considered to be a woman's domain.
			</para>
			<para>
            Dal-Kon grows a variety of woods from near scrub plants 
            such as Bamboo, and Painted Fern to the majestic 
            Cedar and Red Greatwood. From Bamboo and Cedar to Mulberry 
            and Cherry the woods of Dal-Kon are varied and 
			used for the majority of all building and other construction.            
			</para>
            <para> 
            Seaweeds and Kelp abound in the coastal waters. Many of these are gathered 
            for food as well as medicinal purposes.
            </para>
            <para>
            Dal-Kon has many types of fruit trees. 
            Dalk-Kon dami plums are soft and juicy, with flesh that ranges from tart 
            to sweet. These large, round plums are best eaten fresh, and 
            not for drying.
            </para>
            <para>
            Dalk-Kon cherry plum have small, tart fruit, 
            and are used for making jams, jellies, 
            and preserves. These plums are cold hardy and 
            will survive in cool storage bins for the winter
            </para>
            <para>
            Dal-Kon of the Bonsai Tomo grow plums as a favored Bonsai
            in an open vase form (the middle of the tree has no central leader), 
            in an informal fan-trained shape, or in pyramidal shapes. 
            </para>
            <para>
            Red Dawnwood is a large-growing deciduous conifer with fern-like foliage that contrasts 
            beautifully with its deep red wood. It is an excellent choice for providing 
            shade, as well as beauty. Ultimate size is 80-120 feet with 40 feet at 20 years 
            </para>
            <para>
            Bald Cypress grows naturally in swamps and 
            bogs but the tree can thrive in any soil condition. Its smooth red bark contrasts 
            beautifully with its light-green, thread-like foliage. Ultimate size is up to 100 
            feet with 35 feet at 20 years
            </para>
            <para>
            Kitayama sugi or red cedar takes the soaring temperatures 
            of a Dal-Kon seaside summer in stride. This large 
            evergreen is blue foliaged and fast growing. Ultimate size: Up to 50 feet Growth rate
            </para>
            <para>
            River Birch is a large-growing tree that will grow in all conditions - and its 
            ornamental peeling bark. The tree is found naturally 
            in flood plains, but will also flourish in dry soil. 
            Ultimate size: 75 feet; 40 feet at 20 years 
            </para>
            <para>
            Sugar Maple has deep green summer foliage that turns 
            vibrant orange and red in autumn. It is revered for its hard woods and in the 
            more temperate hill regions, for its maple syrup.
            Ultimate size: 80 feet; 30 feet at 20 years
            </para>
            <para>
            batatas or cinnamon vine is a vine that grows up to 10' 
            A vigorous, long-lived twining vine. Much cultivated in Dal-Kon for the large, 
            edible, tuberous roots. The roots are said to remain edible and mild-flavored 
            even when they reach a large size. The small flowers, which appear in summer, 
            are cinnamon scented. Also bears small aerial tubers in the leaf axils. These 
            are edible and can be planted to start new plants.
            </para>
            <para>
            Wild yam's appearance is distinctive in that the leaves grow in whorls of 
            four or more at each node along the vine's lower length. Toward the top, the 
            number of leaves decreases to one or two per node.
            </para>
            <para>
            Juncus Rush. Found mostly in temperate regions, typically occurring 
            on moist or wet soil. ht 2-3' . The Juncus provides a soft rush; 
            This common plant of wetlands is leafless, with round, 
            hollow, green stems. Somewhat similar, in overall appearance, to a 
            large, evergreen chives plant with stiff, slender leaves. The stems 
            are used to weave tatami, the traditional floor covering of 
            Dal-Kon homes.
            </para>
            <para>
            Bamboo. Grasses with perennial, woody stems and, almost always, 
            evergreen leaves. max ht 20' max culm dia 1"  The young shoots 
            are of good quality for eating, and the culms are sturdy and useful 
            for stakes, staves, furniture, and other purposes. 
            </para>
            <para>
            Thorned Cherry. Only found on &tisland, the Thorned Cherry is a fruit tree with a 
            gorgeous bloom (purple, red, white and pink blossoms) bearing a
            delicious fruit. The fruit is , unfortunately, very difficult to harvest for
            being stuck by the thorns of the tree can cause sickness, hallucinations and 
            even madness.
            </para>            
		</sect1>

		<sect1>
			<title>Fauna</title>
			<para>Fish</para>			
            <para>
            The Dal-Kon coastal waters are surrounded by coral reefs. Coral is used as an 
            ornamental material and as a polishing agent. 
            </para>
            <para>
            Ivory is found both from the sea in the form of walrus tusk and
            from the land in the form of Ontabe horn. Ontabe are a large horned 
            rabbit like creature that uses its horn for digging roots.
            </para>
            <para> 
            The Dal-Kon coastal waters abound in fish and shells. 
            Ama (Women divers of the Ama Tomo) search for abalone deep on the ocean floor. (Dal-Kon
            abalone almost inhabit on the rocks of the seabed, not on the kelp bed). It's 
            very dangerous works, so Ama wear a special amulet called Seman Doman that 
            protects them from peril.            
            </para>
            <para>
            Dal-Kon abalones can grow up to 8 inches long and are often 
            covered with worm growths. The outside of the shell is thin and 
            greyish-brown. The blue and green inner shell is covered with an 
            iridescent (a pearl-like shine or luster) mother of pearl layer. 
            </para>
            <para>
            The abalone itself is eaten as a prized seafood. The shells of abalone 
            provide mother of pearl for decorations. Especially prized are the 
            Imperial island black abalone that provide a glowing white mother of pearl
            used in decorating sword racks with cherry blossoms.
            </para>
            <para>
            The viscera of 
            abalone can harbor a poisonous substance which causes a burning, 
            stinging, prickling and itching over the entire body. It does not 
            manifest itself until exposure to sunlight - if eaten outdoors in 
            sunlight, symptoms occur quickly and suddenly. Skin lesions may 
            occur on body parts exposed to the sunlight. It is believed the 
            poison may come from seaweed ingested by the abalone. 
            </para>
            <para>
            Glitter Quills from a puffer fish. Several types of puffer fish in Dal-Kon waters
            provide the Dal-Kon with hollow but flexible needle tipped tubes that are used to 
            inject medicine as well as serving as the basis of decorative beadwork.
            </para>

		</sect1>

		<sect1>
			<title>Mineral and other</title>
			<para>
			The imperial island especially has small but pure iron deposits.
			</para>
            <para>
            Pumice
            </para>
            <para>Obsidian</para>            
            <para>Pottery Clay</para>            
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1>
			<title>Noticeable Other Assets</title>
			<para>Hot Springs</para>
		</sect1>

	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Technology</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>General</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Medical</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Weapon</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Magic</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>General</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Medical</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Weapon</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Subsistence Patterns</title>
		<para>Money is relatively scarce</para>
		<para>Land is relatively Fertile</para>
		<para>Rice and Silk are primaries</para>		
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Values and Kinship</title>
		<para>Uji - membership in the clan.</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Language</title>
		<para>Text</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>History</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Dal-kon Proverb</attribution>
			<para>To be clanless is to be dead</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Diaspora</title>
			<para>Teh leaving from the Golden Empire foloowed by the long trek to Dal-Kon</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Settling</title>
			<para>Settling into the first alluvial basin.</para>
		</sect1>		
		<sect1>
			<title>Expansion</title>
			<para>Battles with the Oni and existing Relanian settlers</para>
			<para>First Shogun, Tamura Moro</para>
			<para>
			Tamura Moro injured in the last major battle with the Rhelanian settlers,
			his wife finishes leading the armies.
			</para>  
			<para>Council rule was breaking down, none could stand alone.</para>
		</sect1>		
		<sect1>
			<title>The Compact</title>
			<para>Acknowledgement of Imperial Rule</para>
			<para>The move of the Capital</para>
		</sect1>		
		<sect1>
			<title>Consolidation</title>
			<para>Gradual aligning of the clans</para>
			<para>Creation of Ninja</para>
			<para>Creation of Sohei</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Troubles</title>
			<para>Increasing influence of the Clans via concubines</para>
			<para>Patronage system of land tax immunities</para>
			<para>Death of Emperor in a duel</para>
			<para>Failed Ascension of Empress Shigei</para>
			<para>Sohei brought to heel</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Modern Era</title>
			<para>Kay and the Silk mission</para>
		</sect1>												
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Religion and Myths</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Religion</title>
			<para>There are many</para>
			<sect2>
				<title>Cosmology</title>
				<para>
				Genesis starts from Chaos. The gods come later (i.e. subject to 
				the rules of the universe)
				</para>
				<para>
                Of old, Heaven and Earth were not yet separated, and the In and 
                Yo not yet divided. They formed a chaotic mass like an egg which 
                was of obscurely defined limits and contained germs. The purer 
                and clearer part was thinly drawn out, and formed Heaven, while 
                the heavier and grosser element settled down and became Earth. 
                The finer element easily became a united body, but the 
                consolidation of the heavy and gross element was accomplished 
                with difficulty. Heaven was therefore formed first, and Earth 
                was established subsequently.				
				</para>
				<para>
				After the creation of Heaven and earth, Divine Beings were 
				produced between them.	Hence it is said that when the world 
				began to be created, the soil of which lands were composed 
				floated about in a manner which might be compared to the 
				floating of a fish sporting on the surface of the water.
				</para>
				<para>
				There is a natural order or Li. An offence against that natural order causes spiritual distractions
				or taints known as pollution. Offence and pollution are inseparable ideas. Pollutions
				are taints that much be removed before man or woman can resume their full role in the life of the 
				community. Death, Birth, sex, disease or causing wounds can all result in such pollution. 
				</para>				
				<para>
				Certain offences such as murder, assault, rape, incest, bestiality all leave a stain that 
				must be ritually expatiated and carry also the need of restitution for the offended individual.
				</para>
				<para>
				The permission of the Samurai to cut down those that stand inthe ways of their duties
                is pragmatic, as it brings the causing of death from a ritual process and restitution 
                to a normal cleansing on the part of the Samurai.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Shinto</title>
			<para>The way of the gods. Attuned to the agrarian common man</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Shizendo</title>
			<para>The way of the ways. Derives into a series of belief codes </para>
			<para>A great deal of stress is placed on the individual's word and way.</para>
            <para>Bushido</para>
            <para>Merchant-do</para>
            <para>Advisor Do</para>
            <para>Gakusho-do</para>            
            <para>Shukenja-do</para>
		</sect1>		
		<sect1>
			<title>Ancestor Worship</title>
			<para>
			Strong worship of the ancestor who established the way of the clan 
			or family. They are assumed to represent and preserve the family, 
			line, clan, or ruling family.
			</para>
			<sect2>
				<title>Deities</title>
                <para>Zenncha - Heimdall</para>
                <para>Amaterasu - Correllan</para>
                <para>? - Dau-Pen</para>                        
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Myths</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Shinto</title>
		<para>The Way of the Gods, also Kannagara: "the way of the kami ." </para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Beliefs</title>
        	<para>			
            All Shinto cults believe in kami, which generally refers to the "divine." 
            Individual clans (uji ), which 
            were simultaneously political, military, and religious units, worshipped a 
            single kami in particular which was regarded as the founder or principal 
            ancestor of the clan. As a clan spread out, it took its worship of a particular 
            kami with it; should a clan conquer another clan, the defeated clan was subsumed 
            into the worship of the victorious clan's kami . What the kami consists of is 
            hard to pin down. Kami first of all refers to the gods of heaven, earth, and the 
            underworld, of whom the most important are creator gods. But 
            kami also are all those things that have divinity in them to some degree: the 
            ghosts of ancestors, living human beings, particular regions or villages, 
            animals, plants, landscape-in fact, most of creation, anything that might be 
            considered wondrous, magnificent, or affecting human life. This meant that the 
            Dal-Kon feel themselves to be under the control not only of the clan's 
            principal kami, but by an innumerable crowd of ancestors, spiritual beings, and 
            divine natural forces. As an example of the potential for divinity: there is a 
            story of an emperor who, while travelling in a rainstorm encountered a cat on a 
            porch that waved a greeting to him. Intrigued by this extraordinary phenomenon, 
            the emperor dismounted and approached the porch. As soon as he reached the 
            porch, a bolt of lightning crashed down on the spot his horse was standing and 
            killed it instantly. From that point on, cats were, in Shinto, worshipped as 
            beneficent and protective kami; if you walk into a Dal-Kon restaurant, you are 
            sure to find a porcelain statue of the waving cat which protects the 
            establishment from harm. 			
			</para>
			<para>
            Shintoists believe that the trees of the forest have souls, known as kodama, and 
            that the Kodama-Kami protect the more exalted of them.
			</para>
			<para>			
            There are Shinto shrines where huge trees hundreds of years old are encircled 
            with shimenawa, straw "belts" that designate them as sacred objects. Each tree 
            represents purity and a divine persona, which explains why its wood is revered 
            even after the tree has fallen. In this regard, the unadorned trunks of trees, 
            which have had little more than the bark removed, may be used in shrine 
            architecture and festivals.
			</para>
			<para>			
			Carrying a handful of soil from one part of the island to the tree is an established custom 
            among worshippers.
			</para>			
			<para>			
            All Shinto involves some sort of shrine worship, the most important is the 
            Izumo Shrine on the coast of the Dal-Kon Sea. These shrines are often 
            a piece of unpolluted land surrounded by trees (himorogi ) or a piece 
            of unpolluted ground surrounded by stones (iwasaka ). Shinto shrines are 
            usually a single room (or miniature room), raised from the 
            ground, with objects placed inside. One worships the kami inside the shrine. 
            Outside the shrine is placed a wash-basin, called a torii , where one cleans 
            one's hands and sometimes one's face before entering the shrine. This procedure 
            of washing, called the misogi , is one of the principal rituals of Shinto, which 
            also included prayer and spells. One worships a Shinto shrine by "attending" it, 
            that is, devoting oneself to the object worshipped, and by giving offerings to 
            it: anything from vegetables to great riches. Shinto prayer (Norito ) is based 
            on koto-dama , the belief that spoken words have a spiritual power; if spoken 
            correctly, the Norito would bring about favorable results. 
			</para>		

		</sect1>
		
		<sect1>
			<title>Practices</title>
			<para>
			The practices of Shinto are normally performed by the worshippers themselves or
			by Gakusho (spirit priests) in someones name. Thus there is a large body 
			of common practices that a farmer would in a year without any intervention on the 
			part of an intermediary.
			</para>
            <sect2>
                <title>Sangaku or Offering Tablets</title>
                <para> 
                The custom of hanging tablets at shrines was established in Dal-Kon 
                centuries before sangaku came into existence. Shintoism
                is populated by "eight hundred myriads of 
                spirits," the kami. Because the kami, it was said, love horses, 
                those worshipers who could not present a living horse as an 
                offering to the shrine might instead give a likeness drawn on 
                wood. As a result, many tablets dating from the founding of Dal-Kon 
                depict horses. 
                </para> 
                <para> 
                The tablets seem to be distributed fairly uniformly 
                throughout Dal-Kon, in both rural and urban districts, with about 
                twice as many found in Shinto shrines as in Sohei or Deitic temples. 
                </para> 
    			<para>
    			Recently, devotees of math, evidently samurai, merchants and some farmers
    			, would solve a wide variety of geometry problems, inscribe their efforts in 
    			delicately colored wooden tablets and hang the works under the roofs 
    			of religious buildings. These sangaku are often acts of homage--a thanks to a 
    			guiding spirit--or in some communitities they have been brazen 
    			challenges to other worshipers: Solve this one if you can! For the most part, sangaku 
    			deal with ordinary Euclidean geometry. Circles and ellipses play 
    			a prominent role: circles within ellipses, ellipses within 
    			circles. Some of the exercises are quite simple and others are 
    			nearly impossible. 
    			</para>
                <para> 
                Most of the sangaku contain more than one theorem and 
                are frequently brightly colored. The proof of the theorem is 
                usually not given, only the result. Other information typically 
                includes the name of the presenter and the date. Not all the 
                problems deal solely with geometry. 
                </para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Class Structure</title>
		<para>
		From the outside it would appear that Dal-Kon's society is compartmentalised into four distinct classes by birth: the Samurai (shi),
		farmers (no), artisans (ko), and merchants (sho). The reality is far more complex. It is true that 
		that is indeed the general ordering of status among the people engaged in those tasks. 
		Careers are hereditary though there is some natural mobility up and down groupings of careers.
		Acclaim can raise the status of someone (especially in a martial class) up to that of Samurai.
		A child's life choice may be changed by a marriage contract that gives over the daughter or 
		, more rarely, the son to the new family. 
		</para>
		<para>
        There are those that gain mobility by being spirit called to a craft or class other than they were born to. 
        It is rare but it does happen (usually several times in a generation per village).
		Thus a son born to an Ashigaru father may become a Samurai by acclaim, or by Kami-kan. A son born to 
		a dyer may be able to become a potter with Kami-kan or contract among the families involved.
		</para>
		<para>
		There are some life choices that wash away most issues of birth class. The Judges pick and choose those that become 
		Judges, Gakusho, and Shukenja without regard to class, only ability. Only the Judges evaluate those that
		believe they are Kami-Kan.
		</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Tradition</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Womens Roles</title>
			<para>
            Samurai women are expected to exhibit loyalty, bravery, and take on the 
    		duty of revenge. As her warrior husband is often absent, the samurai 
    		wife also has important duties at home. Her responsibility is the food 
    		and all the household supplies. She oversaw the harvesting of crops, 
    		managed all the servants, and takes over all financial business. 
    		In matters which concerned the well-being of the family, 
    		her advice is sought and her opinions respected. On her, too, fell the 
    		burden of providing the proper education of her children. She is  to 
    		instill in them a strong sense of loyalty to the samurai ideals of 
    		courage and physical strength.			
			</para>
			<para>
			All brokered marriages are done through the Samurai women with the exact roles 
			taken in the negotiation dependent on the status of the nearest living female 
			relative.
			</para>	
            <para>
            In wartime Samurai women have to defend their homes. Trained in 
            weaponry, women carry a dagger in their sleeves or sashes and can throw 
            with deadly aim. The naginata, a long, curved polearm, is  considered 
            the weapon most suitable for women. All Samurai girls learn the art of 
            naginatajutsu 
			</para>								
			<para>
            Sometimes Saumrai women have joined their men in battle, fighting alongside them 
            or directing the troops. Like their husbands, women are expected 
            to commit suicide if the family is dishonored in any way. Some Samurai women 
            use suicide as a form of protest against injustice, as in the case of 
            one woman who killed herself when her husband mistreated her.
			</para>	
            <para>
            Most Dal-Kon traditions and styles of family life have women in a much more subservient role. 
            Unlike the male children have a household, the female rarely has any say about who or 
            when she marries. 
            </para>
            <para>
            There are a few traditions that give women some openings for self destinatiuon. Some
            Tomo are mother/daughter concerns only and have some protection for the choices they 
            make from within their craft. Geisha, Ama, and Weavers are a few exmples.
            </para>                        
		</sect1>		

		<sect1>
			<title>Wedding</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Bedding</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Birthing</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Battle</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Diaspora</title>
			<para>
			Dal-Kon Commons and Nobles have a special celebration for the successful landing and settlement immediately
			following the collapse of the Golden Empire.
			The Imperial family has its own celebration on the same day that represences the compact to 
			the imperial family.
			</para>			
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Institutions</title>
		<para/>
		<sect1>
			<title>The Emperor</title>
			<para>
			His word is law.His speaking is distributed in several ways.
			</para>		
			<para>
			Mi-Kyo-Sho or letters of Advice about policies. These are general statements 
			of goals that ministers and agents use as guidelines for resolving disputes about 
			turf and tactics. Typically conceived by the Emperor, crafted by the Emperor's Judges,
			and Sealed by the Emperor. 
			</para>					
			<para>
			Kudashi-Bumi or letters of instruction. These are the explicit commands that ministers 
			issue to their agents descrivbing what should be done.
			</para>
			<para>
			Miyo- or Letters In His Voice. These are letters that the Emperor signs for his agents giving them 
			power to resolve or investigate an issue. A similar concept is the "Power of His Hand" carried by 
			the Kaishakunin
			</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1>
			<title>Land Grants: Han, Shoen and Shiki</title>
			<para>
			More or less autonomous, the shoen is under the 
			rule of person (kon-ke) or organiztion (ryo-ke). A Kon-ke may be a 
			Daimyo in whose land the Sho resides or another noble born.
			A ryo-ke is often a great temple. Their interest is in 
			the keeping of their agent residing in the sho. Under 
			these agents are arranged the various tenures of land 
			and the classes of people who hold them.
			</para>
			<para>
			Associated with each sho is a series of "profit rights" or shares 
			called shiki. A shiki of land is a
			separate right or profit derivable from it that is vested in a person --- after
			whom it is named; as, for instance: the Kon-ke-shiki, 
			tenant-shiki, or the like.
			</para>
			<para>
			Sho-tenures. There are three tenures that are recognized in Dal-Kon for 
			land. There are free tenures of possession which have been derived from the first
			cultivation of the soil, or from purchase or other modes of out-right
			acquisition, and which can therefore be bequeathed or disposed of at will, the
			Kon-ke or Ryo-ke exercising little interference with them. These 
			include outright sale to other Kon-ke or Ryo-ke. 
			</para>
			<para>
			When, however, the holder of a free land gives up the 
			title over it to the Kon-ke or Ryo-ke for the purpose of 
			protection or immunity, a second class of tenure 
			results - that of the commended land. Here the Kon-ke
			becomes the titular owner, but is in fact normally merely 
			entitled to certain dues from the land, for the commendor 
			usually remains as its possessor and user, and continues 
			to dispose of it as he pleases. Though of course, in general the shoen
			is typically commended to the Han's Daimyo.
			</para>
			<para>
			The third class of tenure comprises shiki that have been granted 
			either by the seignior or by the proprietor
			and are usually hereditary but presumably at least at the 
			beginning inalienable without permission
			</para>
			<para>			
            A rice tax is levied on the produce of the paddies, and a head tax 
            is levied on adult males or adult females of all female Tomo. The 
            rice tax is low (about 3 percent of the crop), but the head tax, 
            payable in handicrafts such as silk and hemp can impose a 
            significant burden. Moreover, the transport of the goods from the 
            provinces to the capital is the responsibility of the taxed, which 
            involves an enormous labour for those living in distant parts. 
			</para>
			<para>
            Adult males are also obliged to give military service and to provide labour for public works 
            at the command of the local Daimyo or Imperial Agent, amounting to not more than 60 days 
            per year.
            </para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1>
			<title>Guilds (Tomos)</title>
			<para>
			The Dal-Kon maintain a complicated set of craft and other guilds called Tomo.
			The Tomo exist at Imperial grant and cover all the crafts of Dal-Kon. Membership in Tomo
			are father/son or Mother/Daughter relations.
			</para>
			<para>
            Ritualists, Armorers, Ricefield Workers, Weavers, Potters, Scribes, Interpreters, Reciters,
            Grooms, Husbanders, Ironworkers, Smiths, Bowyers, Fletchers, Brewers, Acrobats, Fishers, Amas,
            Geisha, etc..
            And in some cases the tomo may be more general such as "Quiver Bearers" or military support groups 
            for a specific clan.
			</para>
			<para>Most are born into a tomo, some are contracted into a tomo, and a few are Kami-Kan (spirit called). 
			Typically a ritualist will handle the once a year ritual for each Tomo that inducts 
			a son/daughter into the Tomo. A Judge will be preent if there is a question of Kami-Kan.
			</para>
			<para>
			Geisha are one of the few Tomo that habitually learn the skills and crafts of other tomos
			with contracts being negotiated often. Geisha especially have close ties with the ritualists and 
			musical instrument tomos.
			</para>			
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Sohei</title>
			<para>
			The Sohei are warrior monks. Monastic orders of martial practitioners
			who at one time rivaled the Judges and Inner Clans for power.
			Many Sohei form the basis of a martial tradition and may act as the trainers for 
			a specific clan. Some Sohei owe alleigience to a clan.
			</para>
			<para>
            Some few Sohei live in more isolated locales for the pursuit of mental disciplines and
            mystical powers. Such Sohei are know as Yamabushi or Hijiri. Literally a "Mountain Monk". 
            Said to posses a great deal of mystical powers against the supernatural due to they're 
            extreme ascetic lifestyle. They practiced the art of SHUGENDO to attain supernatural powers.
			</para>
			<para>
			It is said that the Judges maintain a Sohei monastary in the Imperial Island
			</para>
		</sect1>				
		<sect1>
			<title>Gakusho</title>
			<para>
            By nature, Shinto is focused on purification and the living, but Shinto Priests 
            must also act as a buffer between the living and the Kami or deities that 
            protect mankind and also demand tribute or become angered. Also, not all Kami 
            are helpful to man and must mere be placated into not showing anger.
			</para>
			<para>
            Most Gakusho are male but a few (about 10%) are female.
			</para>
			<para>
			The Gakusho wield a varied set of powers and abilities. Some of 
			the Gakusho become masters of Tantric or Mantric magic. 
			Based on Shingon or "True Word" it acts most often as a soul 
			shaping craft magic. It is typically constrained to being used 
			on the gakusho themself except when healing is required. 
			These are simply called the Shingon.
			</para>
			<para>
			In addition the Gakusho act as assesors of the Karmic debt that 
			one has accumulated, able to see the threads of the past life as they 
			affect the present and future. In some circumstances they can intervene 
			to alter or lessen the debt. Those who are skilled in this are called Karmic Masters.
			</para>
			<para>
			The Dal-Kon language is said to hold power in it's very structure. Some Gakusho 
			have becoime Masters of the Power of Words, or the craft of Kotodama. Not
            quite true magic in that he must say verses or write down the words of power.
            nonetheless, he or she has the ability to bend the very fabric or reality. This
            works on all creation - not just supernaturals but humans as well. These are called 
            the Kotodama Masters.
			</para>
            <para>
            Some temples shelter blind wise women known as Miko. Miko hold the ability of 
            Powerful Prognostication. They can tell a client the day they will die and 
            why if the client is brave enough. They often 
            come into they're power at puberty but must remain 'pure' to be at they're most 
            powerful. In they're youth they channel Spirits of the Dead and Kami and wield a 
            great deal of power. They go blind in they're 40's as a result but live to be 
            very old. Some say because they see things no mortal is meant to see.            
            </para>			
			
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Judges</title>
			<para>Seven great monastaries</para>
			<para>The Judges have a labour levee that replaces all land taxes and rice levees
			but is porportional to the number of judges available.
			</para>
			<para>The Judges actually sponsor one small specialised Sohei</para>
			<para>The Judges oversee and work with the Gakusho</para>
		</sect1>		
		<sect1>
			<title>Rites and Rituals</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Religious Norms</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Crafts and Arts, Architecture, and Symbolism</title>
		<para>
		There is no culture more oriented toward fine craft work than the Dal-Kon
		</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Utilitarian Hand Crafts</title>
			<para>
			Pottery
			</para>
			<para>
			Papermaking
			</para>
			<para>
			Swordsmithing
			</para>			
			<para>
			Fletcher
			</para>			
			<para>
			Armourer
			</para>			
			<para>
			Lacquer
			</para>			
		</sect1>


		<sect1>
			<title>Arts</title>
			<para>
			Ikebana or Flower Arranging. Kika Shibata is the Patron Kami of the Ikebana Tomo.
			</para>
			<para>
            Suminagashi-literally, 
            "spilled ink" or "ink-floating"-is a Dal-Kon technique for creating 
            free-form marbled patterns on paper or similar surfaces. The design 
            is formed by floating pigments--ink or paint--on the surface of 
            water and then carefully laying a sheet of paper onto the colors, 
            which adhere to the paper and transfer the design to its surface. 
			</para>
			<para>
            kumihimo is the process of creating silk or hemp belts through 
            different methods of braiding, typically done on a takadai loom
			</para>			
			<para>
			Ategami is the art of woodblock printing.
			</para>			
		</sect1>


        <sect1>
            <title>Music</title>
			<para>
            Dal-Kon has a rich musical tradition. This tradition is displayed in 
            part in popular songs and in Shinto ritual and chant as well as the 
            court music and dances 
			</para>			
			<para>
            Music is not a separable element from any other components of a 
            performance. Music is almost always accompanied by some work, story, 
            pantomime, dance, and/or acrobatics and all the musical styles are 
            understood as music and some other component. 
			</para>			
			<para>
            The dominant secular musical style of Dal-Kon is gigaku or Kure-gaku 
            . This is the style of music for the popular dances and pantomimes 
            of Ricefield workers and other manual workers. Later, however, it 
            has risen to become the lowest form of official music 
			</para>			
			<para>
            Sangaku is the most active and exciting of the musics-interspersed 
            between songs were acrobatics and energetic pantomimes. It arose 
            from the original Sohei traditions of battle theater and song.
			</para>			
			<para>
            Shinto chant is chanting performed largely in prayers, the norito , 
            or "divine words." Shinto musical performance is exoteric, designed 
            to be performed and comprehended by anyone with little musical 
            training.
			</para>			
			<para>
            Perhaps the most permanent and complex musical culture developed in 
            Dal-Kon is the gagaku, or court instrumental music. 
			</para>			
			<para>
            In Dal-Kon, gagaku means "refined" (ga ) "music" (gaku ) and so is 
            perfectly in line with the Dal-Kon Courts cultural value of miyabi , 
            or "courtly refinement." Since the emphasis is on refinement or 
            taste, gagaku is largely experienced as an elite or esoteric music, 
            a "high culture" music in contrast to other Dal-Kon musical 
            traditions. Like other Dal-Kon musical traditions, gagaku is not 
            "music alone" but rather music and dance or pantomime. The entire 
            gagaku experience, from the music to the singing to the story to the 
            dance is regarded as refined and elegant. It's important to 
            understand that gagaku is not a distinct musical classification but 
            is a category that subsumes several musical and performance genres. 
            It is largely a distinction between music for refined, courtly 
            tastes, and all other types of music. 			
			</para>			
			<para>
            The daily life of the Dal-Kon imperial court is filled with gagaku. 
            All ceremonies, weddings, funerals, affairs of state, all are 
            accompanied by the musical style most appropriate to the occasion. 
			</para>			
			<para>
            Dal-Kon musical theory is based on the eight categories of sound : 
            metal (bells), stone (stone chimes), earth (ocarina), leather 
            (drums), silk (stringed instruments), wood (double reed wind 
            instruments), gourd (sho, or mouth organ), and bamboo (flute). 
			</para>			
			<para>
            Dal-Kon think of musical instruments as two distinct categories: 
            percussion and all others. The instruments associated with gagaku 
            are stringed instruments and wind instruments similar to the flute; 
            the percussion instruments, however, are seen as lesser instruments.
			</para>			
			<para>
            Principle among the stringed instruments is the biwa, which, like so 
            much else in Dal-Kon music culture, is imported from Rhelania. It is 
            not only the most important instrument in court orchestras, the biwa 
            is also a work of fine art as the biis that are used are among the 
            finest crafted works of the Dal-Kon instruments. 
			</para>			
			<para>
            The biwa is a four-stringed instrument. In gagaku orchestras it is 
            common but tends to be used for the grunt work-the bulk of the 
            musical work is done by the six- stringed wagon and the thirteen-
            stringed koto with their more complex and rich modes. 			
			</para>			
			<para>
            Among the wind instruments, the principle instruments are the 
            shakuhachi, a bamboo flute, and the sho , a mouth organ built of 
            seventeen bamboo pipes arranged in a circle. The shakuhachi flute is 
            played with the flute dangling down in front of the performer; 
			</para>			
			<para>
            Percussion is a standard part of Dal-Kon ensemble music. Three of 
            the tonal categories in Dal-Kon musical theory are taken up by 
            percussion: metal, stone, and leather. The Dal-Kon employed three 
            percussion instruments: a side drum (kakko ), a bronze gong (shoko 
            ), and a large, hanging drum struck by two large, heavy drumsticks 
            (taiko ). As with most percussion, taiko music is very close to the 
            origins of music in the movement of the body and a real experience 
            requires seeing as well as hearing the performance. Taiko 
            performance is based on the modulation between the "female" (left 
            hand) and "male" (right hand) strokes of the drumsticks-the female 
            stroke is always soft and the male is always a strong stroke. The 
            modulation between soft and strong is the primary component of taiko 
            performance. In addition to court music, percussion is a vital part 
            of Shinto ceremonies and processions. The instruments and rhythms 
            are different than court music, but Shinto life and ceremony is 
            filled with percussive richness.    
			</para>			
        </sect1>
                    
		<sect1>
			<title>Symbolism</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Common Motifs</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Significant Numbers</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Art</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Architecture</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Clothing and Color</title>
        <para>
        Love of colour resurfaces again and again throughout Dal-Konese costume history.
        The colours have relationships with Dal-Kon philosophy and superstition.	
        Blue-green represents wood, Spring, and the East.	 Red stands for 
        fire, Summer, and the South.	 White is for Autumn, Metal, and the
        West. The North aligns with Winter, Water, and Black.	 And Yellow
        is the Center and Earth.	 
        </para>
        <para>
        The Dal-Kon practice the use of distinction by colour.	Luckily for most 
        the distinctions are combinations of clothing type and color rather than color alone.
        </para>
        <para>
        Clothing and color among the court and the Inner Clans are more ornate 
        than among the Outer Clans. In fact it can be said that there are two 
        distinct clothing cultures among the Dal-Kon. The Court or Inner Clan 
        Culture and the Outer Clan culture. 
        </para>
        <para>
        In the Dal-Kon Court colours are strict indicators of rank.	 In Dal-Kon, courtiers take the 
        native appreciation of colour and its subtlety to a higher level.	 Although men's court clothing 
        is regulated by rank, a man in casual dress showed his refinement and sensitivity by pairing 
        colours according to the season, the occasion, or his mood.	 And if Dal-Kon men excel at this 
        practice, Dal-Kon women are masters.	 Less restricted by rank colours than men, a Dal-Kon lady can 
        make or break her reputation with her choice of colours to wear in combination. Indeed, the mistress 
        of the household (that is, the principle wife) is responsible for all the dyeing that goes on.
        The Dyers Tomo associated with a Han is beholden and reports to the ranking woman of the Han.
        It is no surprize that the Imperial post of Mikushige-dono, Mistress of the Wardrobe, is often 
        held by the oldest Imperial concubine.
        </para>
        <para>
        The
        ranking colours had to be produced precisely using the correct materials.	
        These colours are purple, blue, red, yellow, white and black.
        </para>
        <para>
        In the Dal-Kon court there are several official clothing colours in addition
        to white. These colors, when combined, with specific types of court costume are 
        used to denote ranking within the court. Each color is produced with 
        dyestuffs referenced in the Dal-Kon Classics.	Yellow is made from gardenia hulls and bark
        of the Amur cork tree.	Purple is from Murasaki roots. Red
        is from madder root. Blue-green is from indigo overdyed with yellow
        for green. Black is produced from the shell of the Abalone.
        </para>
        <para>
        The Imperial Household has authorized an official Dyers Tomo or Naisenshi for the official colors.	 
        </para>
        <para>
        Murasaki is native to Dal-Kon. In some periods this beautiful but 
        non-lightfast purple was restricted to Imperial ladies only.	 In 
        addition to its ephemerality, a careful process of premordanting 
        had to be followed in order to produce the correct shade.
        Often called simply iro ("colour" in Dal-Kon), there is no doubt that it is 
        THE colour of the Court.
        </para>
        <para>
        Suo is imported from Rhelania as dried wood chips 
        from the Suo or Sappanwood tree.	 This redwood is of the same species as the 
        basilwood and produces the same dyestuff.	 Again, its lack of lightfastness makes this 
        colour desirable.	 By manipulating the dyebath by the addition of wood ash water 
        of vinegar, the imperial dyers can produce everything from deep eggplant to 
        lavender and maroon to ox-blood red.
        </para>
        <para>
        Benibana or safflower is probably the most fleeting of all the dyes.
        Like murasaki, benibana is also a restricted dye, though courtiers favoured by 
        the Emperor were often given special permission to wear it.	 Dyeing with 
        safflower requires careful manipulation of the acid dyebath.	 Anyone can produce 
        yellow from the petals.	 Orange requires more skill.	 But pink ( kurenai) 
        is the restricted colour.	 
        </para>
        <para>
        The colour combinations (called kasane no irome in Dal-Kon) are stylised 
        and many combinations have a name.	 Late Dal-Kon period texts such as Masasuke's 
        "Notes on Costume" catalog these outfits.	 
        </para>
        <para>
        Austerity is the hallmark of the Outer Clans.	 Fashion reflects this rebellion against the 
        perceived decadence of the Dal-Kon court. Instead of many layered silk garments, Outer Clan 
        ladies wear "underwear." White kosode and red hakama, which on the Dal-Kon Inner Clan noblewoman is rarely seen, 
        became the utilitarian garb of the Outer Clan.	 There is strong significance in the names of the main 
        garment - ko-sode (small sleeve) as opposed to hiro-sode (wide sleeve) or o-sode (big sleeve) 
        as the Dal-Kon Inner Clan layers are sometimes called.	There is even an anecdote that relates how an
        Outer Clan Daimyo chopped off his own brother's big sleeves with a sword because he believed him to 
        be reverting to courtly decadence.	 
        </para>
    </chapter>	
	
	<chapter>
		<title>Politics</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Leadership</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Fellowship?</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Judicial Structure</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Making the Laws</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Enforcing the Laws</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Legal Code</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Ownership of Goods</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Land</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Male and Female Roles</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Church and State</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Death by Suicide</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Death by Anothers Hand</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Death in Self Defense</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Military</title>
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Standing</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Command</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Routine</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Arms</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Outfitting</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Theory</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Military</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Takeda Toshiro, founder of Clan Takeda, in his clan </attribution>
			<para>
			I was flinging drops of sweat when I completed the dance. I felt full of power;
			like a glowing lump of iron fresh from the forge. All the rage had accumulated in 
			the middle. This was a imperial rage, a righteous wrath. At the center of my mind 
			, wreathed in fire, was the image of the Emishi general. There lay the deepest inner 
			rage, radiating fury: Emishi, through all these years, true source of these atrocities.
			</para>
			<para>
			I stripped off my inner robe. I was vageuly aware of soldiers that had gathered to 
			sit on hay bales and watch. I drew my Swords with a hard strike-draw combination and
			saluted the air with a flourish of edges. In that air hung the face of an Emishi. An
			Emishi general of great skill. Yes, clever man, with his priests behind him.
			</para>
			<para>
			I began the Bladestorm. I was tired and that drove me at an even greater pace than my 
			teacher ever used - which was foolish. The swords whined in the air with a sound I 
			had never heard from them before, the droning whine of the legendary Bladestorm of 
			my teacher's own teachers. Bladestorm was for the suicidal idiot whirling in a 
			light footed fight across the unstable scree of a cliff, over loose rocks, 
			among multiple enemies. An error in timing or breath control with the whirling blades
			caused the dancer to slash himself. Such was the concentration required that a dancer did not 
			bleed from cuts. There stories of dancers bowshot, gutted and gashed and never noticing it, 
			never stopping, until the end of the dance - when they dropped dead over their 
			shredded victims.
			</para>
			<para>
			The hilts of the swords slapped my hands lightly, spun and reversed hands, and 
			rose to salute the air, and I was done. I stood there blinking a moment before 
			I could break myself from the rhythm. My breath came in great regular heaves. 
			The air felt to thick for breathing. Somehow my body, arrogant in the sight of so
			many eyes, pulled itself upright. I sheathed my blades and reached for a rag to 
			wipe the sweat from my shoulders. To me, the sound of my breathing was deafening. 
			My nephew Higaru reached forth a hand with a flask of sake spiked water. I had 
			just touched it to my lips when stirrings at the edge of the camp announced 
			what we had waited for. The Emishi marched to meet us. 
			</para>
			<para>
			As I prepared my armor and lost myself in the chatter of a camp preparing to 
			march, I wondered whether I had become a great master or an even greater fool. 
			The only answer to hand was that I didn't know. It was the barest beginnings
			of wisdom.
			</para>
		</epigraph>		
		<para>Text</para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Standing</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Command</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Routine</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Arms</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Outfitting</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Theory</title>
			<para>Text</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	<glossary>
		<glossdiv>
			<title>Institutions</title>
			<glossentry id="shoen">
				<glossterm>shoen</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>The generic name applied to several species of private domains</para>
					<para>
    			    Each shoen is a corporation of villa (sho), land (en) and 
    			    people (semmin) managed under the patronage of some person 
    			    of influence or of an institution, known as the hon-ke and 
    			    ryo-ke. 
    			    </para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="en">
				<glossterm>en</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
    				<para>
        			Each en is a tract of land associated with a shoen.
        			</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>			
			<glossentry id="semmin">
				<glossterm>semmin</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
    				<para>
        			A semmin is the body of people bound or associated with a shoen.
        			</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>									
			<glossentry id="sho">
				<glossterm>sho</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
    				<para>
        			Each sho	is a villa associated with a shoen.
        			</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="honke">
				<glossterm>hon-ke</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para/>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="jizo">
				<glossterm>jizo</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Handhewn roadside guardian deities representing the attainment of enlightenment for the sake of others</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="sohei">
				<glossterm>Sohei</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Warrior Monks</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="han">
				<glossterm>Han</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A feudal province considered the dwelling place or property of a clan</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="jito">
				<glossterm>jito</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Stewards of a Sho</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="compact">
				<glossterm>The Compact</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>
					The Dal-Kon imperial family is said to maintain a compact or contract with the Dragons 
					of Dal-Kon that allows the imperial family to preserve and maintain the country. What the 
					Dragons would get out of this compact is unknown.
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="ujikami">
				<glossterm>Ujikami</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>
					The object of clan veneration is the Ujikami, or clan god. They may be a forefsather,
					departed leader, local god or Kami, OR in one case a greater deity.
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>			
		</glossdiv>
		
		<glossdiv>
			<title>Ranks</title>
			<glossentry id="daimyo">
				<glossterm>Daimyo</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A feudal overlord of a clan's Han</para>
					<para>A Daim-yo can have as few as three Cho-hans and as many as twenty if he is insanely powerful</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="samurai">
				<glossterm>Samurai</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Samurai (that can control 20 - 200 Bushi)</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>			
			<glossentry id="kaishakunin">
				<glossterm>kaishakunin</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A emperor's officer charged with acting as a executioner at a Daimyo's act of seppuku</para>
					<para>Only a kaishakunin may so act for a Daimyo.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>			
			<glossentry id="chohan">
				<glossterm>Cho-Han</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A Military rank. A commander of Samurai. Cho-han can command up to 50 Samurai and up to 1000 Bushi</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
		</glossdiv>
		
		<glossdiv>
			<title>Concepts</title>
			<glossentry id="kanjo">
				<glossterm>Kanjo</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Concept of warfare defining the soldiers of a lord as the shield of the castle</para>
					<para>Kan, The Shield. The Shield, the Soldier. The Soldier, the Castle.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>

    		<glossentry id="kamikan">
				<glossterm>Kami-Kan</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>
					Spirit called. (literally Spirit House) 
					When a young man or woman believes they have been called to 
					another Tomo than the one they have been born into.
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>	
		</glossdiv>
		
		<glossdiv>
			<title>Objects</title>
			<glossentry id="mon">
				<glossterm>mon</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A Small copper coin</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry id="ryo">
				<glossterm>Ryo</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A Small gold coin</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>

		</glossdiv>
		

		<glossdiv>
			<title>Places</title>
			<glossentry id="koyasan">
				<glossterm>Koyasan</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>
                    Koyasan is a mountaintop basin resting over 2400 feet above sea level and 
                    measuring 2 miles  east to west, 1.5 miles north to south. The basin is surrounded by two 
                    concentric rims of hills, each of which is comprised of eight peaks. The basin 
                    thus resembles the shape of an unfolding lotus flower. The marvellously purplish 
                    mists that drape the sacred peaks at dawn and dusk present a suitably sublime 
                    figure
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
		</glossdiv>
		
		<glossdiv>
			<title>People</title>
			<glossentry id="saicho">
				<glossterm>Saicho</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>Founder of the Tendai Lotus Sect of the Sohei (became the judges)</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
		</glossdiv>		
	</glossary>
</book>
