<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Hybrid Character Generation</title>
    </info>
    <part>
        <title>Creating a Character</title>
        <chapter>
            <title>Basic Method</title>
            <sect1>
                <title>Process</title>
                <para>The player starts with a set of points for buying statistics and a set of
                    points for buying skills. The two pools are the Stat Pool and the Skill Pool.
                    The player starts with 125 points in teh Stat Pool statistics and 10 points in
                    the Skill Pool. </para>
                <para> With these points the player buys what is needed for the initial character
                    development. This includes the Race, Special Abilities, and Culture of the
                    character. </para>
                <para> Then the player generates the history of the character. The player picks the
                    career path the character will follow and uses the results of that career to put
                    points into the other pools. </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <title>Statistics</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick Primary Statistics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Buy Limitations and Enhancements</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <orderedlist>
                    <title>Buy </title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick a race</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick a gender (if applicable)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Apply modifiers from the racial description</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Calculate remaining statistics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Calculate Statistics</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <orderedlist>
                    <title>Buy Culture Template </title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick a culture</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Apply modifiers from the cultural description</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick base skills from the cultural description</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Pick the skills</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <orderedlist>
                    <title>Story</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Work out the story to explain the character.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Primary Statistics</title>
                <para> In generating the statistics of the character the player distributes 125
                    points among the 10 primary statistics. The minimum number of points that may be
                    put into a statistic is 5. The maximum amount that may be placed into a
                    statistic is 25. </para>
                <para> The following gives the name and abbreviation of each primary statistic and
                    describes what the statistic represents.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <title>Primary Statistics</title>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Strength</term>
                        <term>PST</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Physical Strength is the overall power of body. This represents
                                the character's raw muscle power and is not tied to some particular
                                set of limbs. Actions such as lifting are based on PST..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Endurance </term>
                        <term>PEN</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Physical Endurance is the physical resilience and stamina of body.
                                This is a measure of the character's overall endurance and ability
                                to resist hardship as well as the ability to bounce back from
                                hardship..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Dexterity </term>
                        <term>DEX</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Dexterity is the eye and hand coordination and speed of hand
                                movement. This is specifically tied to the character's hands (or any
                                alien equivalent)..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Agility </term>
                        <term>PAG</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Physical Agility is the overall flexibity and responsiveness of
                                body. This affects the whole body actions of the character. Dodging
                                is an action based on PAG..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Awareness </term>
                        <term>PAW</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Physical Awareness is how sensitive the character is to the
                                physical part of the environment. If you are using any of your
                                physical senses, you are using PAW..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Strength </term>
                        <term>MST</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Mental Strength is raw mental power. It is a measure of the
                                characters overall computational and reasoning strength. It is also
                                associated with the character's strength of will. Using memory is an
                                action based on MST..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Endurance </term>
                        <term>MEN</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Mental Endurance is resilience and stamina of mind. It is a
                                measure of the mind's ability to recover from shock or
                                disorientation..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Agility </term>
                        <term>MAG</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Mental Agility is the overall flexibility and responsiveness of
                                mind. In another day and age this might be called ``Cunning'',
                                ``Canniness'', or ``Shrewdness''. .</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Psi Potential </term>
                        <term>PSI</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Psi Potential is a measure of how easily a character can gain
                                access to their ``supernatural'' or psychic abilities. In fantasy
                                campaigns this also governs the use of magery..</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Awareness </term>
                        <term>MAW</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Mental Awareness is how sensitive the character is to the
                                non-physical part of the environment. .</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <para> The typical non-player character average and the ranges of the primary
                    statistics are given in the table below. </para>
                <table>
                    <title>Human Average Stats and Full Range</title>
                    <tgroup cols="4">
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Statistic</entry>
                                <entry>Minimum</entry>
                                <entry>Maximum</entry>
                                <entry>Average</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PST</entry>
                                <entry>1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PEN</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>DEX</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PAG</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PAW</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MST</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MEN</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MAG</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PSI</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MAW</entry>
                                <entry> 1</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                                <entry>12</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Pick a Race and Gender</title>
                <para>Once the primary statistics have been chosen the race of the character must be
                    selected. The racial template includes modifiers for primary statistics and
                    other statistics as well as any special abilities of the race. The racial
                    template includes Stat modifiers, Special Abilities and Limitations. Some races
                    will have a cost that must be paid from the Personal Development pool.</para>
                <para>See your obliging GamesMaster for a list of racial descriptions.</para>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Modifying Statistics for Race</title>
                    <para>The racial description may include modifiers to the character's
                        statistics. Primary Statistic modifiers are applied right away. Modifiers to
                        calculated stats are applied after generating the background of the
                        character.</para>
                    <para>There may be other limitations or enhancements to be noted due to race.
                    </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Modifying Statistics for Gender</title>
                    <para>The player should note whether the character is male or female (if the
                        character's race supports multiple genders). If there are any modifiers to
                        statistics for a specific gender they should be applied. These modifiers
                        will be listed in the racial description.</para>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Secondary or Calculated Statistics</title>
                <para>With the race and gender selected all of the primary statistics are modified
                    and the secondary statistics are determined. Secondary statistics are determined
                    from the primary stats. Like the primary statistics they break down evenly into
                    mental and physical categories.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <title>Calculated Statistics</title>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Body</term>
                        <term>PBD</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The amount of physical damage a character can absorb. Derived from
                                PST and PEN.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PBD = PST+PEN x Racial Modifier</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Fatigue</term>
                        <term>PFT</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The amount of energy a character can expend, either in combat or
                                in work. Derived from PEN and PAG.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PFT = (2 x PEN) + PAG</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Exhaustion</term>
                        <term>PEX</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> The amount of energy reserve a character can expend as the result
                                of damage or from work. Derived from PEN and PAG.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PEX = (4 x PEN)+PAG</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Movement</term>
                        <term>PMV</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of the character's movement rate. Derived from PST and
                                PEN and racial modifiers.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PMV = ((PST+PAG)/5) x Racial Modifier</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term> Mental Body</term>
                        <term>MBD</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The amount of mental damage a character can absorb. Derived from
                                MEN and MST.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MBD = (MST+MEN) x Racial Modifier</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Fatigue</term>
                        <term>MFT</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The amount of mental energy a character can expend, either in
                                damage or in work. Derived from MEN and MAG.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MFT = (2 x MEN)+MAG</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Exhaustion </term>
                        <term>MEX</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The amount of mental reserve energy a character can expend, either
                                in combat or in work. Derived from MEN and MAG.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MEX = (4 x MEN)+MAG</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Movement</term>
                        <term>MMV</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> A measure of the characters rate of movement in the purely mental
                                realms of psionics, magery, and computer interfaces.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MMV = (MST+MAG)/5) x Racial Modifier</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Accuracy</term>
                        <term>ACC</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of the character's effectiveness with projectile or
                                missile weapons. Derived from PST and DEX. Could also be called
                                Physical Accuracy.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>(PST+DEX)/2</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Combat Ability</term>
                        <term>PCA</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of a character's ability to inflict damage in
                                hand-to-hand and melee combat. Derived from PST, PAG, DEX.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PCA = (PST+DEX+PAG)/3</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Defense</term>
                        <term>PDF</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of a character's ability to dodge or evade to avoid
                                taking damage in hand-to-hand or melee combat. Derived from PAG,
                                DEX.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>PDF = (PAG+DEX)/2 </mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Focus</term>
                        <term>FCS</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of the character's effectiveness with focused mental
                                actions. Derived from MST and MAG. could also be called Mental
                                Accuracy.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>FCS = (MST+MAG)/2</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Combat Ability</term>
                        <term>MCA</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of a character's ability to inflict damage in Mind to
                                Mind combat. Derived from MST, MAG, PSI</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MCA = (MST+PSI+MAG)/3</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Defense</term>
                        <term>MDF</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A measure of a character's ability to avoid taking damage in
                                mental combat or highly stressful situations. Derived from
                                MAG.</para>
                            <equation>
                                <mathphrase>MDF = (MAG+PSI)/2</mathphrase>
                            </equation>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <table>
                    <title>Calculated Statistics</title>
                    <tgroup cols="4" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Statistic Name</entry>
                                <entry>Formula</entry>
                                <entry>Typical Range</entry>
                                <entry>Human Average</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PBD</entry>
                                <entry>((PST+PEN) x Racial Modifier</entry>
                                <entry>2-60</entry>
                                <entry>30</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PEX </entry>
                                <entry> ((4 x PEN) + PAG ) </entry>
                                <entry> 15-150 </entry>
                                <entry> 75 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PFT </entry>
                                <entry> ((2 x PEN) +PAG) </entry>
                                <entry> 09-90 </entry>
                                <entry> 45 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PMV </entry>
                                <entry> (((PAG+PST)/5) x Racial Modifier) </entry>
                                <entry> 0.4-12 </entry>
                                <entry> 6 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MBD </entry>
                                <entry> ((MST+MEN) x Racial Modifier) </entry>
                                <entry> 02-60 </entry>
                                <entry> 30 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MEX </entry>
                                <entry> ((4 x MEN) + MAG ) </entry>
                                <entry> 20-150 </entry>
                                <entry> 75 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MFT </entry>
                                <entry> ((2 x MEN) + MAG ) </entry>
                                <entry> 09-90 </entry>
                                <entry> 45 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MMV </entry>
                                <entry> (((MAG+MST)/5) x Racial Modifier) </entry>
                                <entry> 0.4-12 </entry>
                                <entry> 6 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>ACC </entry>
                                <entry> ((PST+DEX)/2 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PCA </entry>
                                <entry> ((PST+DEX+PAG)/3 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>PDF </entry>
                                <entry> ((PAG+DEX)/2 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>FCS </entry>
                                <entry> ((MST+MAG)/2 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MCA </entry>
                                <entry> ((MST+PSI+MAG)/3 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>MDF </entry>
                                <entry> ((MAG+PSI)/2 ) </entry>
                                <entry> 3-30 </entry>
                                <entry> 15 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Other Statistics</title>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Height</title>
                    <para>Height (HT) Expressed in Centimeters. If the creature being described is
                        quadrapedal, the height given is the height to the shoulder. </para>
                    <para>If the player has no preference regarding the height of the character the
                        height may be randomly generated using the following formula: </para>
                    <equation>
                        <mathphrase>Height = Average Height + ( (2d10 - 11)/10) x Height Variation
                        </mathphrase>
                    </equation>
                    <para>The Average Height and Height Variation is given in the racial
                        modifiers.</para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Weight</title>
                    <para>Expressed in Kilograms. If the player has no preference regarding the
                        weight of the character the weight may be randomly generated using the
                        following formula. </para>
                    <equation>
                        <mathphrase>Weight = Average Weight + ( (2d10 - 11)/10 x Weight
                            Variation)</mathphrase>
                    </equation>
                    <para>The Average Weight and Weight Variation is given in the racial
                        description. </para>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Appearence</title>
                    <para>A measure of how physically attractive a character is to others of their
                        race. It ranges (typically) from +5 to -5 and has a default of 0. Characters
                        that wish to be more or less attractive can buy appearance as an enhancement
                        or limitation. </para>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Speed of reaction</title>
                <para>There are some statistics that are calculated from a table. </para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Mental Speed</term>
                        <term>MSPD</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Speed of reaction in mental actions is given by Mental Speed. It
                                is derived from the Mental Awareness stat using the table below. An
                                average Mental Speed is 4.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Physical Speed</term>
                        <term>PSPD</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Speed of reaction in mental actions is given by Physical Speed. It
                                is derived from the Physical Awareness stat using table
                                ~\ref{Table:Speed} on page~\pageref{Table:Speed}. An average
                                Physical Speed is 4.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <table>
                    <title>Reaction Speed Table</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Awareness Statistic</entry>
                                <entry>Resulting Speed</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>1-2 </entry>
                                <entry> 0 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>3 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>4-5 </entry>
                                <entry> 1 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>6-8 </entry>
                                <entry> 2 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>9-11 </entry>
                                <entry> 3 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>12-15 </entry>
                                <entry> 4 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>16-19 </entry>
                                <entry> 5 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>20-24 </entry>
                                <entry> 6 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>25-29 </entry>
                                <entry> 7 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>30-34 </entry>
                                <entry> 8 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>35-35 </entry>
                                <entry> 9 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>36-39 </entry>
                                <entry> 9 </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>40-45 </entry>
                                <entry> 10 </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Cultural Skills and Knowledge</title>
                <para> The player should determine the culture and the home environment the
                    character is raised in. Both of these will have a major effect on the numbers
                    and types of skills that a player character starts out with. Some cultural
                    templates may have a cost that must be paid from the Personal Development
                    pool.</para>
                <para> As a result of growing up in a given environment the character gains skill in
                    how to maneuver in that environment. i.e. A character born and raised in an
                    zero-gravity environment will have high skills in Movement:0-g and little or no
                    skills in Movement:1-g. </para>
                <para> The character will start out with a knowledge of how to use the technology
                    common to their culture and what the social dos and and donts are. </para>
                <para> These types of skills are listed in the table below.along with some specific
                    examples.</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <title>List of points that can be distributed among basic cultural
                        skills</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>20 points of skills in written (if it is a literate culture) and
                            spoken language.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>20 points of skill in Cultural Lore. Both local and larger
                            scale.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>20 points of skill in education appropriate to the culture. What ever
                            would be considered appropriate education for a character of the social
                            level.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>20 points of skill in Lore:[Tech Index] of Culture</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>15 points of manuevering skills for the native environment</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
                <title>Skills, Stats, Limitations and Enhancements</title>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Buying Skills</title>
                    <para>The Personal Development pool serves as the point pool for increasing a PC
                        statistics, skills, or creating special abilities. The Personal pool serves
                        as the point pool for increasing a PC statistics, Skills, or creating
                        special abilities.</para>
                    <para> In addition a player can add and subtract to/from the pools by the usage
                        of Enhancements and Limitations. See section \ref{Sec:Enhancements}.</para>
                    <sect3>
                        <title>Skill Costs</title>
                        <para> When characters are first generated they can buy single skills using
                            points from the personal pool. During character generation all skills
                            cost 1 point per rank to purchase. So rank 0 costs 1 point, rank 1 costs
                            2 points , and so on. After characters have been generated they advance
                            in their skills according to rules described in the Players
                            Guide.</para>
                        <para>In summary single skills cost $ 1 + Rank $ in personal development
                            points.</para>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title>Skill Ranks</title>
                        <para>The meaning of skill ranks varies somewhat based on the rarity of the
                            skill and so on but, in general, the skill ranks map to expertise
                            according to table ~\ref{Table:SkillRanks} on
                            page~\pageref{Table:SkillRanks}.</para>
                        <para>Someone is familiar with the skill if they have tried it enough that
                            the tools and techniques are known even if the character has no real
                            practice with them.</para>
                        <para> A character is at a begginer level of skill if they have used the
                            skills enough to be comfortable with all the basic techniques needed
                            even though they may not be consistent in their execution.</para>
                        <para> A character is at a dedicated amateur level of skill if they are
                            consistent in executing all the basic skills even though they have no
                            real comfort with any of the advanced techniques</para>
                        <para>A solid workaday craftsman is consistent and accomplished in executing
                            all the basic skills and are familiar with the advanced techniques and
                            tools.</para>
                        <para>A professional is consistent and accomplished in te full range of
                            basic and advanced techniques used in routine application of the
                            skill.</para>
                        <para>An expert is consistent and accomplished in all the basic and advanced
                            techniques used in routine application of the skill as well as being
                            familiar with techniques and tools needed for less common usage of the
                            skill.</para>
                        <para>An master is consistent and accomplished in all the techniques used in
                            most applications of the skill. In addition they are familiar with some
                            esoteric techniques needed for bizarre and unusual applications of a
                            skill.</para>
                        <para>An character at a mystical mastery level accomplished in all the
                            techniques used in almost all known applications of the skill. In
                            addition they have a whole series of special techniques and tools they
                            have developed for themselves.</para>
                        <table>
                            <title>How Ranks in a skill show up in the "Real World"</title>
                            <tgroup cols="2">
                                <tbody>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 0 </entry>
                                        <entry> Familiar with the skill </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 1-3 </entry>
                                        <entry> Beginner </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 4-6 </entry>
                                        <entry> Dedicated Amateur </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 7-10 </entry>
                                        <entry> Solid Workaday Craftsman </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 11-14 </entry>
                                        <entry> Professional </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 15-18 </entry>
                                        <entry> Expert </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 19-25 </entry>
                                        <entry> Mastery </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 25+ </entry>
                                        <entry> Mystical Mastery </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title>Skill Packages</title>
                        <para>What we have discussed up till now has been single skills. Quite often
                            the character will be using a skill package. A skill package is a
                            collection of related skills that have a bundled at a bargain cost. </para>
                        <para> A typical skill package would be :</para>
                        <example><![CDATA["Terran Law Enforcement Officer Package
        Lore: Terran Law
        Culture Lore: Terran LEO
        Weapon: Pistol 
        Weapon: Tonfa
        Weapon: Taser
        Streetwise
        Interrogation
        Data Analysis
        Computer Ops
        Cost: 5"]]></example>
                        <para>This package would cost 5 points to get rank 0 in all the listed
                            skills, 10 points to get rank 1 and so on. This compares well to 9
                            points to get rank 0 in all the skills and 18 points to get rank 1 and
                            so on. After character generation, these skills are raised individually
                            just like any other skill according to rules described in the Players
                            Guide.</para>
                    </sect3>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Buying increases in statistics</title>
                    <para> When characters are first generated they can buy statistics using points
                        from the personal pool. During character generation all stats are raised
                        using the costs from the table ~\ref{Table:StatCosts} on
                        page~\pageref{Table:StatCosts}. So adding 1 point of PST costs 4 points,
                        adding 2 costs 8 points, and so on. After characters have been generated
                        they advance in their stats according to rules described in the Players
                        Guide.</para>
                    <table>
                        <title>Costs for buying statistics at the beginning</title>
                        <tgroup cols="6">
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> Stat </entry>
                                    <entry> Cost </entry>
                                    <entry> Stat</entry>
                                    <entry> Cost </entry>
                                    <entry> Stat </entry>
                                    <entry> Cost </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> PST </entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    <entry> PBD </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                    <entry> ACC </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> PEN </entry>
                                    <entry> 3 </entry>
                                    <entry> PSE </entry>
                                    <entry> 5 </entry>
                                    <entry> PCA </entry>
                                    <entry> 3 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> DEX </entry>
                                    <entry> 3 </entry>
                                    <entry> PFT </entry>
                                    <entry> 1 </entry>
                                    <entry> PDF </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> PAG </entry>
                                    <entry> 5 </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> PAW </entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    <entry> PMV </entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> MST </entry>
                                    <entry> 8 </entry>
                                    <entry> MBD </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                    <entry> FCS </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> MEN </entry>
                                    <entry> 6 </entry>
                                    <entry> MSE </entry>
                                    <entry> 5 </entry>
                                    <entry> MCA </entry>
                                    <entry> 3 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> MAG </entry>
                                    <entry> 12 </entry>
                                    <entry> MFT </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                    <entry> MDF </entry>
                                    <entry> 2 </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> PSI </entry>
                                    <entry> 10 </entry>
                                    <entry> MMV </entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry> MAW </entry>
                                    <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </sect2>
                <sect2>
                    <title>Enhancements and Limitations</title>
                    <para> After a character has some points in the three pools associated with
                        character creation ( personal, wealth, status) they may choose to use them
                        to buy Enhancements that will add flavour to the character. </para>
                    <para> There are always the base enhancements allowed to the character. The
                        points in the personal pool can be used to buy skills at the generation
                        cost. The points in the personal pool can be used to buy stats at the costs
                        listed in the stat cost tables. </para>
                    <para> Enhancements are gains in either background or special abilities that can
                        be paid for with points from one of the pools. There are two main types.
                        There are Character Enhancements and there are Environmental Enhancements. </para>
                    <para> Character Enhancements are natural aptitudes that are typically permanent
                        and inherent to the character's makeup. Enhanced hearing or eidetic memory
                        are examples of Character Enhancements. </para>
                    <para> Environmental Enhancements are typically advantages that depend on the
                        character to maintain them. Such as inherited wealth and various components
                        of status. </para>
                    <sect3>
                        <title>Character Enhancements</title>
                        <para> Character Enhancements have both Depth and Scope to help govern their
                            cost. Depth refers to the numeric advantage given by the enhancemnet in
                            a given area. The scope denotes the number of different areas that the
                            spab may be applicable to. In the case of raising a character statistic
                            the scope refers to the number of other stats affected. </para>
                        <para> A character enhancement that involves enhancing a statistic is
                            different from raising the statistic. A raised statistic ends up
                            increasing the SB of the character in that stat. The enhanced stat
                            increases the Rank of the character for any direct rolls against that
                            stat. Thus an Enhanced Stat affects Saving Throws and Concentration
                            Checks. </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <title>Character Enhancements</title>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Ambidexterity</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Ambidexterity allows the character to use either hand when
                                        performing actions. The character takes no off-hand
                                        penalties. Costs 10 Personal Development Points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Eidectic Memory</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Exact recall (given successful roll against MST) of
                                        events. Adds DF 2 to any memory roll. Costs 12 Personal
                                        Development points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Photographic Memory</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Exact recall of (given successful roll against MST) any
                                        image or visual happening. Costs 12 Personal Development
                                        points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Lightning Calculator</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Ability to instantly execute complex arithmetic and
                                        mathematical calculations. Costs 5 Personal Development
                                        points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Active PSI</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Character has concious knowledge and use (though no
                                        training) of their psionic abilities. Costs 20 Personal
                                        Development Points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Mage Ability</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Character has concious knowledge and use (though no
                                        training) of their magical abilities. Costs 20 Personal
                                        Development Points</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Enhanced Statistics</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Most of the enhancements that involve heightened stats in
                                        specialised areas have a simple cost equal to $ 1/2 $ the
                                        purchase cost of the stats. So someone with a heightened
                                        sense of smell would pay one half the cost of Physical
                                        Awareness (PAW) or $ 1/2 \times 4 = 2$ for each additional
                                        point of increase. So someone with a 12 PAW could pay 8
                                        points of ersonal Development and get a PAW (for smells) of
                                        16.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>PSI Gift</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> The heightening of PSI for broad categories of PSI skills
                                        such as Temporokinetics has a cost equal to $ 3/4 $ of the
                                        PSI stat or 8 points. So someone with a gift for
                                        Temporokinetics would pay 8 points per point of heightened
                                        PSI in that area. The heightening of PSI for specific PSI
                                        skills such as Teleportation has a cost equal to $ 1/2 $ of
                                        the PSI stat or 5 points. So someone with a gift for
                                        Teleportation would pay 5 points per point of heightened PSI
                                        in that area. </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Presence</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> This enhancement reflects other people's innate awareness
                                        of the character in a given area. A person with a high
                                        presence is hard to ignore. It is calculated in just the
                                        same way as other enhanced stats. So Enhanced Physical
                                        Presence is 2 points per additional effect. Decreased
                                        Physical Presence is 2 points per subtracted effect.
                                        Enhanced Mental Presence is 2 points per additional effect.
                                        Decreased Mental Presence is 2 points per subtracted effect.
                                        The decreased presence enhancements are, in effect, stealth
                                        enhancements. </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </sect3>
                    <sect3>
                        <title>Environmental Enhancements</title>
                        <para>Environmental Enhancements are typically advantages that depend on the
                            character to maintain them. Such as inherited wealth and various
                            components of status. These also have a ongoing impact on how friendly
                            or hostile the world occurs.</para>
                        <para> Environmental Enhancements have both Depth and Scope to help govern
                            their cost. Scope is the number of people affected by the
                            enhancement.</para>
                        <table>
                            <title>Cost of Environmental Enhancement Scope</title>
                            <tgroup cols="3">
                                <tbody>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Scope </entry>
                                        <entry> Number of People </entry>
                                        <entry> Cost </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^0 </entry>
                                        <entry> 1 </entry>
                                        <entry> 1 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^1 </entry>
                                        <entry> 2-10 </entry>
                                        <entry> 2 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^2 </entry>
                                        <entry> 11-100 </entry>
                                        <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^3 </entry>
                                        <entry> 101-1000 </entry>
                                        <entry> 8 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^4 </entry>
                                        <entry> 1001-10000 </entry>
                                        <entry> 16 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^5 </entry>
                                        <entry> 10001-100000 </entry>
                                        <entry> 32 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> 10^6 </entry>
                                        <entry> 100001-1000000 </entry>
                                        <entry> 64 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                        <para>Depth is how deeply they are affected by the enhancement.</para>
                        <table>
                            <title>Cost of Environmental Enhancement Depth</title>
                            <tgroup cols="3">
                                <tbody>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Depth </entry>
                                        <entry> DF </entry>
                                        <entry> Cost </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Low </entry>
                                        <entry> 1 </entry>
                                        <entry> 1 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Medium Low </entry>
                                        <entry> 2 </entry>
                                        <entry> 2 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Medium </entry>
                                        <entry> 4 </entry>
                                        <entry> 4 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Medium High </entry>
                                        <entry> 6 </entry>
                                        <entry> 8 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> High </entry>
                                        <entry> 8 </entry>
                                        <entry> 10 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <entry> Very High </entry>
                                        <entry> 12 </entry>
                                        <entry> 20 </entry>
                                    </row>
                                </tbody>
                            </tgroup>
                        </table>
                        <para> So for determining the cost of a single ( Scope = 10^0 ) friend
                            willing to help you all (Depth = Very High ) the time is simply 1 + 20 .
                            The DF describes how willing the person is to help you. So in the
                            example DF = 12 implies +60% to the chance for aid from that person. </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <title>Environment Limitations and Enhancements</title>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Wealth</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>The first and most commonly used is the wealth advantage.
                                        This differs from the basic wealth that can be gained by
                                        spending the points from the wealth pool in that the gain is
                                        approximately one third that of a pure monetary spend, but
                                        the gain so obtained is income that will continue to be
                                        generated for as long as the PC pays attention to the
                                        interests that generate the funds. The larger the income the
                                        more work involved in maintaining it.</para>
                                    <para> The scale of the income is derived from table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts}. The amount
                                        of freedom from managing that income is given by the table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts}.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Friends,Allies, and Contacts</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para> Another important Environmental Enhancement is that of
                                        Friends. Number of friends is derived from table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts}. The
                                        willingness to help is given by the table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts}.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Reputation</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>The scale of the reputation is derived from table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementScopeCosts}. The amount
                                        of recognition is given by the table
                                        ~\ref{Table:EnvironmentalEnhancementDepthCosts}.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term>Continued Careers</term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>A continued career as a Law Enforcement Officer or soldier
                                        is a balanced ad and disad situation. Yes, the character has
                                        enemies, but the backing of the organization offsets
                                        this.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </sect3>
                </sect2>
            </sect1>
        </chapter>
    </part>
</book>
